<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/CSS/heresies_cwrc.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Why Women Need the Goddess</title>
            <author>Carol P. Christ</author>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Eowyn Andres</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Lyndon Beier</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-2025)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Mia DeRoco</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-2025)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
               <resp>Editor, encoder (2021)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Zoha Nadeer</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Bri Perea</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Carrie Pirmann</persName>
               <resp>HTR editor, encoder (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Ricky Rodriguez</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Valeria Riley</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Zaely Rodriguez</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2025-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2025)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Kelly Troop</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-2025)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Lucy Wadswoth</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2025)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Anna Marie Wingard</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-2025)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Olivia Wychock</persName>
               <resp>Graduate Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
            <funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
            <funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
            <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <name>Bucknell University</name>
               <address>
                  <street>One Dent Drive</street>
                  <settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
                  <region>Pennsylvania</region>
                  <postCode>17837</postCode>
               </address>
            </distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0
                  International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
               <licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title>The Great Goddess</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and Politics</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>
                        <address>
                           <name>Heresies</name>
                           <postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
                           <settlement>New York</settlement>
                           <region>New York</region>
                           <postCode>10013</postCode>
                        </address>
                     </pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <pb n='8'/>
			<p>
				<lb/>Why Women Need the Coddess
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>Carol P. Christ
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>At the close of Ntosake Shange’s stupendously success
				<lb/>ful Broadway play For Colored Cirls Who Have Con
				<lb/>sidered Suicide When the Rainbow Is Enuf, a tall beautiful
				<lb/>Black woman rises from despair to cry out, &quot;l found God
				<lb/>in myself and 1 loved her fiercely.”1 Her discovery is
				<lb/>echoed by women around the country who meet spon
				<lb/>taneously in small groups on full moons, solstices anc
				<lb/>equinoxes to celebrate the Goddess as symbol of life and
				<lb/>death powers and waxing and waning energies in the
				<lb/>universe and in themselves.2
				<lb/>It is the night of the full moon. Nine women stand in a
				<lb/>circle, on a rocky hill above the city. The western sky i
				<lb/>rosy with the setting sun; in the east the moon’s face begins
				<lb/>to peer above the horizon. .. The woman pours a cup of
				<lb/>wine onto the earth, refills it and raises it high. “Hail Tana,
				<lb/>Mother of Mothers!&quot; she cries. &quot;Awaken from your long
				<lb/>sleep, and return to your children again!&quot;3
				<lb/>What are the political and psychological effects of this
				<lb/>fierce new love of the divine in themselves on women
				<lb/>whose previous spiritual experience has been focusec
				<lb/>upon the male God of Judaism and Christianity? Is the
				<lb/>spiritual dimension of feminism a passing diversion, an
				<lb/>escape from difficult but necessary political work? Or
				<lb/>does the emergence of the symbol of Goddess among
				<lb/>women have significant political and psychological ram
				<lb/>ifications for the feminist movement?
				<lb/>To answer these questions, we must first understand
				<lb/>the importance of religious symbols and rituals in human
				<lb/>life. According to anthropologist Clifford Geertz religious
				<lb/>symbols shape a cultural ethos, defining the deepest
				<lb/>values of a society and the persons in it. “Religion,
				<lb/>Geertz writes, &quot;is a system of symbols which act to pro
				<lb/>duce powerful, pervasive, and long-lasting moods and
				<lb/>motivations”“ in the people of a given culture. A &quot;mood
				<lb/>for Geertz is a psychological attitude such as awe, trust or
				<lb/>respect, while a “motivation” is the social and political
				<lb/>trajectory created by a mood which transforms mythos
				<lb/>into ethos, symbol system into social and political reality.
				<lb/>Symbols have both psychological and political effects be
				<lb/>cause they create the inner conditions (deep-seated at
				<lb/>titudes and féelings) which lead people to feel com
				<lb/>fortable with or to accept social and political arrange
				<lb/>ments that correspond to the symbol system. Because
				<lb/>religion has such a compelling hold on the deep psyches
				<lb/>of so many people, feminists cannot afford to leave it in
				<lb/>the hands of the fathers. Even people who no longer &quot;be
				<lb/>lieve in God&quot; or participate in the institutional structure
				<lb/>of patriarchal religion still may not be free of the power of
				<lb/>the symbolism of God the Father. A symbol’s effect is not
				<lb/>dependent on rational assent, for a symbol also functions
				<lb/>on levels of the psyche other than the rational. Religion
				<lb/>fulfills deep psychic needs by providing symbols and
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>rituals which enable people to cope with difficult situa
				<lb/>tions? in human life (e.g., death, evil, suffering) and to
				<lb/>pass through life’s important transitions (e.g., birth, mar
				<lb/>riage, death). Even people who consider themselves com
				<lb/>pletely secularized will often find themselves sitting in a
				<lb/>church or synagogue when a friend or relative gets mar
				<lb/>ried, or when a parent or friend dies. The symbols associ
				<lb/>ated with these important rituals cannot fail to affect the
				<lb/>deep or unconscious structures of the mind of even a per
				<lb/>son who has rejected these symbolisms on a conscious
				<lb/>level—especially if that person is under stress. The reason
				<lb/>for the continuing effect of religious symbols is that the
				<lb/>mind is uncomfortable with a vacuum. Symbol systems
				<lb/>cannot simply be rejected, they must be replaced. I be
				<lb/>lieve where there is no replacement, the mind will revert
				<lb/>to familiar structures at times of crisis, bafflement or
				<lb/>defeat
				<lb/>Religions centered on the worship of a male God keep
				<lb/>women in a childish state of psychological dependence
				<lb/>on men and male authority, and at the same time legit
				<lb/>imate the political and social authority of fathers and sons
				<lb/>in the institutions of society. The damage done to women
				<lb/>by exclusively male symbolism in religion and culture is
				<lb/>both psychological and political: women feel their own
				<lb/>power is inferior or dangerous and they therefore give
				<lb/>over their will to male authority figures in family and
				<lb/>society.
				<lb/>Religious symbol systems focused on exclusively male
				<lb/>images of divinity are psychologically devastating to
				<lb/>women because they create the impression that female
				<lb/>This message need never be explicitly stated (as for ex
				<lb/>ample it is in the story of Eve) for its effect to be felt. A
				<lb/>woman completely ignorant of the myths of female evil in
				<lb/>Biblical religion nonetheless acknowledges the anomaly
				<lb/>of female power when she prays exclusively to a male
				<lb/>God. She may see herself as like God (created in the
				<lb/>image of God) by denying her own sexual identity and
				<lb/>affirming God’s transcendence of sexual identity, but she
				<lb/>can never have the experience which is freely available to
				<lb/>every man and boy in her culture, of having her full sexual
				<lb/>identity affirmed as being in the image and likeness of
				<lb/>God. Her mood is one of trust in male power as salvific
				<lb/>and distrust of female power in herself and other womer
				<lb/>as inferior or dangerous. Such a &quot;powerful, pervasive, and
				<lb/>long-lasting” mood cannot fail to become a motivation
				<lb/>which translates into social and political reality.
				<lb/>As Z Budapest has noted, the easiest way to conquer a
				<lb/>people is through religion, because after the people in
				<lb/>ternalize the symbols of a religion, they function as their
				<lb/>own &quot;internal policemen” and force is no longer necessary
				<lb/>to keep them in line.° The conquest of the psyche ensures
			</p>
			<pb n='9'/>
			<p>
				<lb/>control of the body politic, as politicians as diverse as
				<lb/>Hitler and Mao have known well.
				<lb/>Feminist theologian Mary Daly has detailed the polit
				<lb/>ical ramifications of Father religion for women in Beyond
				<lb/>Cod the Father:
				<lb/>If God in “his&quot; heaven is a father ruling his people, then it
				<lb/>is the &quot;nature” of things and according to divine plan and
				<lb/>the order of the universe that society be male-dominated
				<lb/>Within this context a mystification of roles takes place: the
				<lb/>husband dominating his wite represents God “himself.&quot;
				<lb/>The images and values of a given society have been pro
				<lb/>jected into the realm of dogmas and “Articles of Faith,
				<lb/>and these in turn justify the social structures which have
				<lb/>given rise to them and which sustain their plausibility.
				<lb/>The secular philosopher Simone de Beauvoir is well
				<lb/>aware of the function of patriarchal religion as legitimater
				<lb/>of male power:
				<lb/>Man enjoys the great advantage of having a god endorse
				<lb/>the code he writes; and since man exercises a sovereign
				<lb/>authority over women it is especially fortunate that this
				<lb/>authority has been vested in him by the Supreme Being.
				<lb/>For the Jews, Mohammedans, and Christians, amongothers,
				<lb/>man is Master by divine right; the fear of God will therefore
				<lb/>repress any impulse to revolt in the downtrodden female.à
				<lb/>The political consequences of patriarchal religion were
				<lb/>evident to nineteenth-century suffragist Elizabeth Cady
				<lb/>Stanton who came to view the churches as the single most
				<lb/>potent force opposing female suffrage. Thus she brought
				<lb/>together her now famous revising committee to write The
				<lb/>Women’s Bible, an early feminist attempt to challenge
				<lb/>directly the power of patriarchal religion
				<lb/>This brief discussion of the psychological and political
				<lb/>effects of God religion puts us in an excellent position to
				<lb/>begin to understand the significance of the symbol of
				<lb/>Goddess for women. But before proceeding to that dis
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>cussion, let me briefly identify the sources for the sym
				<lb/>bolism of Goddess as it is reemerging in womanspirit and
				<lb/>of traditions but their attitudes toward these traditions are
				<lb/>eclectic and selective. Ancient traditions are filtered
				<lb/>through modern experience and there is no sense that
				<lb/>every aspect of ancient or culturally distant religious con
				<lb/>sciousness must be adopted as whole cloth.
				<lb/>At the simplest and most basic level, the symbol of
				<lb/>Goddess is an acknowledgment of the legitimacy of fe
				<lb/>male power as a beneficent and independent power. A
				<lb/>woman who echoes Ntosake Shange’s dramatic state
				<lb/>ment, &quot;I found God in myself and I loved her fiercely, is
				<lb/>saying, &quot;Female power is strong and creative.” She is say
				<lb/>ing that the divine principle, the saving and sustaining
				<lb/>power, is in herselt, that she will no longer look to men or
				<lb/>male figures as saviors. This meaning of the symbol of
				<lb/>Goddess is simple and obvious, and yet it is difficult for
				<lb/>many to comprehend. It stands in sharp contrast to the
				<lb/>paradigms of female dependence on males which have
				<lb/>been predominant in our culture. The internationally ac
				<lb/>claimed French novelist Monique Wittig captured some
				<lb/>thing of the novelty and flavor of the affirmation of fe
				<lb/>male power when she wrote in her mythic work Les
				<lb/>Cuérillères:
				<lb/>There was a time when you were not a slave, remember
				<lb/>that. You walked alone, full of laughter, you bathed bare
				<lb/>bellied. You say you have lost all recollection of it, remem
				<lb/>ber. .. you say there are no words to describe it, you say it
				<lb/>does not exist. But remember. Make an effort to remem
				<lb/>ber. Or, failing that, invent.9
				<lb/>While Wittig does not speak directly of the Goddess, she
				<lb/>nonetheless captures a sense of the mood created in
				<lb/>women who define their identities through the symbol of
				<lb/>Goddess. This mood is one of a joyous celebration of
				<lb/>female freedom and independence, as well as a fearless
			</p>
			<pb n='10'/>
			<p>
				<lb/>ale
				<lb/>point discussed more
				<lb/>affirmation of
				<lb/>body
				<lb/>fully below.
				<lb/>The affirmation of female power contained in the sym
				<lb/>bol of Goddess has both psychological and political con
				<lb/>sequences. Psychologically it means the defeat of the in
				<lb/>ternal policeman who reminds women that their power is
				<lb/>inferior and dangerous. This new mood of affirmation of
				<lb/>female power leads to new motivations; it supports and
				<lb/>undergirds women&apos;s trust in their own power and the
				<lb/>power of other women in family and society.
				<lb/>have said that the simplest meaning of the symbo
				<lb/>&quot;Goddess&quot; is an affirmation of the legitimacy and benef
				<lb/>icence of female power. For one raised in the West, a
				<lb/>question immediately arises, &quot;ls the Goddess simply fe
				<lb/>male power writ large, and if so, why bother with the sym
				<lb/>bol ’Goddess’ at all? Or do you really mean to refer to a
				<lb/>Goddess ’out there&apos; who is not reducible to a human
				<lb/>potential?” Many women have rediscovered the power of
				<lb/>Goddess in solitude as a result of their own inner quests,
				<lb/>or with other women through the women’s spirituality
				<lb/>movement; their answers to this question vary. Three
				<lb/>meanings attach to the symbol &quot;Goddess” for these wom
				<lb/>en: (1) the Goddess as divine female, as personification
				<lb/>who can be invoked in prayer and ritual; (2) the Goddess
				<lb/>as symbol of the life, death and rebirth energy in nature
				<lb/>and culture, in personal and communal life; (3) the God
				<lb/>dess as affirmation of the legitimacy and beauty of female
				<lb/>power (made possible by the new becoming of women in
				<lb/>the women’s liberation movement). If one were to ask the
				<lb/>women who participate in the symbol of Goddess which
				<lb/>of these meanings is the &quot;correct” one, different responses
				<lb/>would be given. Some would assert that the Goddess is
				<lb/>definitely not “out there,” that the symbol of a divinity
				<lb/>&quot;out there” is part of the legacy of patriarchal oppression,
				<lb/>which brings with it the authoritarianism, hierarchicalism
				<lb/>and dogmatic rigidity associated with Biblical mono
				<lb/>theistic religions. They might argue that the symbol of
				<lb/>Goddess reflects the sacred power within women and
				<lb/>nature, suggesting the connectedness between women&apos;s
				<lb/>cycles of menstruation, birth and menopause and the life
				<lb/>and death cycles of the universe. Others seem quite com
				<lb/>fortable with the notion of Goddess as a divine female
				<lb/>protector and creator and would find their experience of
				<lb/>Goddess limited by the assertion that she is not also out
				<lb/>there as well as within themselves and in all natural
				<lb/>processes. When asked what the symbol of Goddess
				<lb/>meant, feminist witch Starhawk replied, &quot;It all depends
				<lb/>on how 1 feel. When 1 feel weak, She is someone who can
				<lb/>help and protect me. When I feel strong She is the symbol
				<lb/>of my own power. At other times 1 feel her as the natural
				<lb/>energy in my body and the world.&quot;”° How are we to evalu-
				<lb/>ate such a statement? Theologians would call these the
				<lb/>words of a sloppy thinker. But my deepest intuition tells
				<lb/>me they contain a wisdom Western theological thought
				<lb/>has lost.
				<lb/>To one trained in theology these differing views of the
				<lb/>&quot;meaning&quot; of the symbol of Goddess sound like an incipi
				<lb/>ent Trinitarian controversy. Is there, I wonder, a way of
				<lb/>developing a theology that does not lead into dogmatic
				<lb/>controversy or require us to say definitively that one un
				<lb/>derstanding is true and the others false? Could we possibly
				<lb/>share our common relation to the symbol and make that
				<lb/>primary and yet allow our varying interpretations? The
				<lb/>diverse explications of the symbol “Goddess&quot; suggest that
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>ne explica
				<lb/>the symbol has a richer significance t
				<lb/>tion can express. This phenomenological fact suggests the
				<lb/>need for an abstract theory of symbol in which the symbol
				<lb/>is viewed as the primary fact and the meanings are viewed
				<lb/>as secondary. It also suggests that a thea-logy” of the
				<lb/>Goddess would be very different from the theo-logy we
				<lb/>know in the West. But to spell out the primacy of symbol
				<lb/>in thea-logy in contrast to the primacy of explanation in
				<lb/>theo-logy would be to write another paper. Let me simply
				<lb/>state that I believe it is incumbent upon woman, who
				<lb/>have been deprived of a female religious symbol systen
				<lb/>for so long and who are therefore in an excellent position
				<lb/>to recognize the power and primacy of symbols, to devel
				<lb/>op a theory of symbol and thea-logy congruent with their
				<lb/>experience
				<lb/>A second important implication of the Goddess symbol
				<lb/>for women is the affirmation of the female body. Because
				<lb/>of women’s unique position as menstruants, birth-givers,
				<lb/>and because they have traditionally cared for the young
				<lb/>and the dying, women’s connection to the body, nature
				<lb/>and finitude has been an obvious fact. In early religious
				<lb/>consciousness birth-giving powers were celebrated and
				<lb/>women were positively valued. But as Western religions
				<lb/>entered into a state of alienation from the body, nature
				<lb/>and this world, women were denigrated because they
				<lb/>seemed more carnal, fleshy and earthy than the culture
				<lb/>creating males.12 The misogynist anti-body tradition in
				<lb/>Western thought is symbolized in the myth of Eve who is
				<lb/>traditionally viewed as a sexual temptress, the epitome of
				<lb/>women’s carnal nature. This tradition reaches its nadir in
				<lb/>the Malleus Maleficarum (The Hammer of Evil-Doing
				<lb/>Women) which states, “All witchcraft stems from carna
				<lb/>lust which in women is insatiable.&quot;1
				<lb/>The denigration of the female body is also expressed in
				<lb/>the taboos of our culture that surround menstruation and
				<lb/>childbirth. While menstruation taboos may have originat
				<lb/>ed in a perception of the awesome powers of the female
				<lb/>body,”4 they have degenerated into a simple perception
				<lb/>that something is “wrong” with female bodily functions
				<lb/>Menstruation is viewed as a curse, and women grow up
				<lb/>believing that the bloody facts of menstruation are best
				<lb/>hidden. Judy Chicago’s Menstruation Bathroom broke
				<lb/>these taboos. In a sterile white bathroom she exhibited
				<lb/>boxes of tampons and Kotex on an open shelf, while the
				<lb/>wastepaper basket overflowed with bloody tampons and
				<lb/>Kotex.15 Many women who saw the piece felt relieved to
				<lb/>have their &quot;dirty secret” out in the open.
				<lb/>The denigration of the female body and its powers is
				<lb/>further expressed in Western culture’s attitudes toward
				<lb/>childbirth. Civing birth is treated as a disease requiring
				<lb/>hospitalization and the woman is viewed as a passive ob
				<lb/>ject, anesthetized to ensure her acquiescence to the will
				<lb/>of the doctor.16. The women’s liberation movement has
				<lb/>aided the advocates of natural childbirth and home birth
				<lb/>by emphasizing the need for women to control and take
				<lb/>pride in their bodies.
				<lb/>The symbol of Goddess aids this process of naming and
				<lb/>reclaiming the female body and its functions. In the an
				<lb/>cient world and among modern women, the Goddess sym
				<lb/>bol represents the birth, death and rebirth processes of the
				<lb/>natural and human worlds. The female body is viewed as
				<lb/>a direct expression or incarnation of waxing and waning,
				<lb/>life and death cycles in the universe because of the con
				<lb/>nection between the 28-day cycles of menstruation and
			</p>
			<pb n='11'/>
			<p>
				<lb/>the 28-day cycles of the moon. How amazing it is for
				<lb/>modern women to learn that many of the ancient Goddess
				<lb/>figures were painted with red ochre between the legs, the
				<lb/>menstrual blood out in the open, a symbol of female
				<lb/>power.&quot;7. The Goddess is often depicted in the act of giv
				<lb/>ing birth, and the birth process is viewed as a symbol of
				<lb/>the life-giving powers of the universe.18 The possibilities
				<lb/>of reclaiming the powers of the female body in Goddess
				<lb/>rituals are expressed in the summer solstice ritual created
				<lb/>by Barbry MyOwn and Hallie Mountainwing. In this ritual
				<lb/>the women simulated a birth canal through which they
				<lb/>birthed each other into their circle. They raised power by
				<lb/>placing their hands on each other’s bellies and chanting
				<lb/>together. Finally, they marked each other’s faces with rich
				<lb/>dark menstrual blood saying, “This is the blood that prom
				<lb/>ises renewal. This is the blood that promises sustenance.
				<lb/>This is the blood that promises life.&quot;19 From hidden dirty
				<lb/>secret to symbol of the life power of the Goddess, wom
				<lb/>en’s blood has come full circle. The degree to which this
				<lb/>ritual seems indelicate or shocking indicates how far
				<lb/>modern culture is from perceiving the sacrality of the
				<lb/>female body
				<lb/>The mood created by the symbol of Goddess as life
				<lb/>and birth power is one of positive, joyful affirmation of
				<lb/>the female body and its powers and processes. The mo
				<lb/>tivations are to overcome the stereotypes of menstruant
				<lb/>women as hysterical, to recognize the blood bonds shared
				<lb/>by women, to value birth as an expression of the ultimate
				<lb/>life power, to return the birth process to the hands of
				<lb/>women and to overcome the spirit/flesh dualism of West-
				<lb/>ern culture.
				<lb/>While the symbolic reclamation of the body and na
				<lb/>ture is especially important to women who have been as
				<lb/>sociated with the despised body, it also has profound sig
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>nificance for men and all beings. The denigration of the
				<lb/>body and the spirit/flesh, mind/body split has been in
				<lb/>jurious to men too. The denigration of the body and
				<lb/>nature has also contributed to our current ecological crisis
				<lb/>because nature has been viewed simply as material for
				<lb/>human consumption. Thus, the Goddess as symbol of the
				<lb/>revaluation of body and nature can pull together many of
				<lb/>the themes addressed separately in the human potential
				<lb/>and ecology movements. In this case the mood is one of
				<lb/>affirmation, awe and respect for the body and nature and
				<lb/>the motivation is to respect the teaching of the body and
				<lb/>the rights of all living beings
				<lb/>A third important implication of the symbol of God
				<lb/>dess for women is the positive valuation of will in a Cod
				<lb/>dess-centered framework. Here 1 am not referring to the
				<lb/>symbol of Goddess in general, but specifically to the no
				<lb/>tion of will in Goddess-centered ritual magic and spell
				<lb/>casting. The basic notion behind ritual magic and spell
				<lb/>casting is energy as power. The Goddess is a center or
				<lb/>focus of power and energy; She is the personification of
				<lb/>the energy which flows between beings in the natural and
				<lb/>human worlds. According to Starhawk, “witches conceive
				<lb/>of psychic energy as having form and substance that can
				<lb/>be perceived and directed by those with a trained aware
				<lb/>ness. The power generated within the circle is built into a
				<lb/>cone form, and at its peak is released—to the Goddess, to
				<lb/>reenergize the members of the coven, or to do a specific
				<lb/>work such as healing.&quot;20 In ritual magic, energy is direct
				<lb/>ed by will power.
				<lb/>The emphasis on the will is important for women be
				<lb/>cause women traditionally have been taught to devalue
				<lb/>their wills, to believe that they cannot achieve their will
				<lb/>through their own power and even to suspect that the as
				<lb/>sertion of will is evil. Faith Wilding&apos;s poem &quot;Waiting
				<lb/>sums up women’s sense that their lives are defined not by
				<lb/>their own will, but by waiting for others to take the in
				<lb/>itiative.
				<lb/>Waiting for my breasts to develop
				<lb/>Waiting to wear a bra
				<lb/>Waiting to menstruate
				<lb/>Waiting for life to begin, Waiting..
				<lb/>Waiting to be somebody
				<lb/>Waiting to get married
				<lb/>Waiting for my wedding day
				<lb/>Waiting for my wedding night
				<lb/>Waiting for the end of the day
				<lb/>Waiting for sleep. Waiting... 21
				<lb/>Patriarchal religion has enforced the view that female
				<lb/>initiative and will are evil through the juxtaposition of Eve
				<lb/>and Mary. Eve caused the fall by asserting her will over
				<lb/>and against the command of God, while Mary began the
				<lb/>new age with her response to God’s initiative, “Let it be
				<lb/>done to me according to thy word” (Luke 1:38). Even for
				<lb/>men, patriarchal religions value the passive will. The
				<lb/>classical doctrines of sin and grace view sin as the prideful
				<lb/>assertion of will and grace as the obedient subordiatnion
				<lb/>of human will (female or male) to the divine initiative or
				<lb/>order. Although this view of will might be questioned
				<lb/>from a human perspective, Valerie Saiving Goldstein has
				<lb/>argued that it has particularly deleterious consequences
				<lb/>for women in Western culture. According to Goldstein,
				<lb/>secular Western culture encourages males in the assertion
			</p>
			<pb n='12'/>
			<p>
				<lb/>of will; thus in practice we may find that the male form of
				<lb/>sin is an excess of will. But since culture discourages fe
				<lb/>males in the assertion of will, the traditional doctrines of
				<lb/>sin and grace encourage women to remain in their form of
				<lb/>sin, which is self-negation or insufficient assertion of
				<lb/>will.22 One possible reason for the denigration of will in a
				<lb/>patriarchal religious framework is that both human and
				<lb/>divine will are often pictured as arbitrary, self-initiatec
				<lb/>and exercised without regard for other wills.
				<lb/>In a Goddess-centered context, in contrast, the will is
				<lb/>valued. A woman is encouraged to know her will, to be
				<lb/>lieve that her will is valid and to believe that her will can
				<lb/>be achieved in the world—three sources of strength and
				<lb/>motivation to take direct action, sources traditionally
				<lb/>denied to her in patriarchy. In a Goddess-centered frame
				<lb/>work a woman’s will is not subordinated to the Lord God
				<lb/>as King and Ruler, nor to men as His representatives. Thus
				<lb/>a woman is not reduced to waiting for and acquiescing to
				<lb/>the will of others as she is in patriarchy. But neither does
				<lb/>she adopt the egocentric form of will that pursues self
				<lb/>interest without regard for the interests of others
				<lb/>The Goddess-centered context provides a different un
				<lb/>derstanding of will than that available in the traditiona
				<lb/>patriarchal religious framework. In the Goddess frame
				<lb/>work, will can be achieved only when it is exercised in
				<lb/>harmony with the energies and wills of other beings. Wise
				<lb/>women, for example, raise a cone of healing energy at the
				<lb/>full moon or solstice when the lunar or solar energies are
				<lb/>at their high points with respect to the earth. This dis
				<lb/>cipline encourages them to recognize that not all times
				<lb/>are propitious for the achieving of every will. Similarly
				<lb/>they know that spring is a time for new beginnings in work
				<lb/>and love; summer, a time for producing external man
				<lb/>ifestations of inner potentialities; and fall or winter, times
				<lb/>for stripping down to the inner core and for extending
				<lb/>roots. Such awareness of waxing and waning processes in
				<lb/>the universe discourages the arbitrary ego-centered asser
				<lb/>tion of will, while at the same time encouraging the as
				<lb/>sertion of individual will in cooperation with natural
				<lb/>energies and the energies created by the wills of others.
				<lb/>Wise women also have a traditional belief that whatever is
				<lb/>sent out will be returned, and this reminds them to assert
				<lb/>their wills in cooperative and healing ways rather than in
				<lb/>egocentric and destructive ones. This view of will allows
				<lb/>women to begin to recognize, claim and assert their will:
				<lb/>without adopting the undesirable characteristics of the
				<lb/>patriarchal understanding and use of will. This is not,
				<lb/>however, to imply that women invariably exercise their
				<lb/>wills for good. Women have as much of a capacity for
				<lb/>positive and negative thoughts and actions as men do. All
				<lb/>1am saying is that in the Goddess-centered context, the
				<lb/>will of women is not devalued per se as it is in the Biblical
				<lb/>and theological traditions discussed above.
				<lb/>In the Goddess-centered framework the mood is one of
				<lb/>positive affirmation of personal will in the context of the
				<lb/>energies of other wills or beings. The motivation is for
				<lb/>women to know and to assert their wills in cooperation
				<lb/>with other wills and energies.
				<lb/>The fourth and final aspect of the symbol of Goddess is
				<lb/>the significance of the Goddess for a revaluation of
				<lb/>mother-daughter relations and women’s heritage. Accord
				<lb/>ing to Virginia Woolf, a sentence such as “Chloe liked
				<lb/>Olivia,” which describes a woman’s relationship to an
				<lb/>other woman, rarely occurs in stories written by men be
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>cause men wri
				<lb/>women only in their relationship to a
				<lb/>man (or men).23 Adrienne Rich points out that the mother
				<lb/>daughter relationship, perhaps the most important rela
				<lb/>tionship of woman to woman, a relationship &quot;resonant
				<lb/>with charges. ..the flow of energy between two biolog
				<lb/>ically alike bodies, one of which has lain in amniotic bliss
				<lb/>inside the other, one of which has labored to give birth to
				<lb/>the other”24 is rarely celebrated in patriarchal religion anc
				<lb/>culture. Christianity celebrates the father’s relation to the
				<lb/>son and the mother’s relation to the son but the story of
				<lb/>the mother and daughter is missing.
				<lb/>In patriarchal literature and psychology, the relation
				<lb/>ship between mothers and daughters is seldom considered
				<lb/>or even mentioned. As de Beauvoir has noted, the mother
				<lb/>daughter relationship is distorted in our male-defined
				<lb/>culture because the mother (perhaps subconsciously) be
				<lb/>lieves her role is to prepare her daughter to enter into that
				<lb/>male-controlled culture in which women are viewed as
				<lb/>inferior.25 The mother socializes her daughter to become
				<lb/>subordinate to men, and if the daughter challenges patri
				<lb/>archal norms, the mother is likely to defend the patri
				<lb/>archal structures against her own daughter.
				<lb/>The bond ot woman to woman is beginning to be cele
				<lb/>brated in the new women’s culture. Holly Near has written
				<lb/>several songs that celebrate the woman bond and wom
				<lb/>en’s heritage. In one of her finest songs she writes of an
				<lb/>&quot;old time woman” who is &quot;waiting to die.” A young wom-
				<lb/>an feels for the life that has passed the old woman by and
				<lb/>begins to cry, but the old woman looks her in the eye and
				<lb/>says, &quot;Ifl had not suffered, you wouldn’t be wearing those
				<lb/>jeans/ Being an old time woman ain’t as bad as it seems.&quot;2e
				<lb/>This song expresses and celebrates a bond and a heritage
				<lb/>passed down from one woman to another. In another of
				<lb/>Near’s songs, she sings of &quot;a hiking boot mother who&apos;s
				<lb/>seeing the world/ For the first time with her own little
				<lb/>girl.&quot; In this song, the mother tells the drifter who has
				<lb/>been traveling with her to pack up and travel alone if he
				<lb/>thinks &quot;traveling three is a drag” because “l’ve got a little
				<lb/>one who loves me as much as you need me/ And darling
				<lb/>that’s loving enough.&quot;2 This song is significant because
				<lb/>the mother places her relationship to her daughter above
				<lb/>her relationship to a man, something that is rare for wom
				<lb/>en to do in patriarchy.2
				<lb/>One of the few accounts of a relationship between
				<lb/>mother and daughter that has survived from ancient times
				<lb/>is the myth of the Goddess Demeter and her daughter
				<lb/>Persephone. This story was told, possibly enacted, in con
				<lb/>nection with the religious rites of the Thesmophoria
				<lb/>which were for women only, and the Eleusinian Mysteries
				<lb/>of Greece. In this story Persephone is abducted by the
				<lb/>God of the Underworld and forced to live in the Under
				<lb/>world as his wife. Unwilling to accept this state of affairs,
				<lb/>Mother Demeter, in her rage, withholds the rain and thus
				<lb/>prevents the growth of all food until her daughter is re
				<lb/>turned to her. What is important for women in this an
				<lb/>cient religious story is that the mother fights for her
				<lb/>daughter and for her relationship to her daughter. This is a
				<lb/>completely different view of the mother’s relationship to
				<lb/>her daughter from that which exists in a patriarchal cul
				<lb/>ture. The mood created by the story of Demeter and Per
				<lb/>sephone is one of sacred celebration of the mother
				<lb/>daughter bond and the motivation is for mothers and
				<lb/>daughters to affirm the heritage passed on from mother to
				<lb/>daughter and to reject the patriarchal pattern in which
			</p>
			<pb n='13'/>
			<p>
				<lb/>mother and daughter betray each other for the sake of
				<lb/>men.
				<lb/>The symbol of the goddess has much to offer women
				<lb/>who are struggling to be rid of the “powerful, pervasive,
				<lb/>and long-lasting moods and motivations” of the devalua
				<lb/>tion of female power, denigration of the female body, dis
				<lb/>trust of female will and denial of the mother-daughter
				<lb/>bond and women’s heritage that have been engendered
				<lb/>by patriarchal religions. As women struggle to create a
				<lb/>new culture in which women’s power, bodies, will and
				<lb/>bonds are celebrated, the symbol of the Goddess naturally
				<lb/>reemerges and speaks to the deep mind, expressing our
				<lb/>new vision of the beauty, strength and power of women.
				<lb/>1. From the original cast album, For Colored Cirls Who Have
				<lb/>Considered Suicide When the Rainbow is Enuf by Ntosake
				<lb/>Shange, (Buddah records, 1976).
				<lb/>2. See Susan Rennie and Kirsten Grimstad, “Spiritual Explora
				<lb/>tions Cross-Country,&quot; Quest (Spring 1975), pp. 49-51; see
				<lb/>also WomanSpirit.
				<lb/>3. Starhawk, &quot;Witchcraft and Women’s Culture&quot; (unpublished
				<lb/>manuscript, p. 3.
				<lb/>4. Clifford Geertz, “Religion as a Cultural System,&quot; in Reader in
				<lb/>Comparative Religion, 2nd ed., ed. Lessa and Vogt (New
				<lb/>York: Harper &amp; Row, 1965), p. 206.
				<lb/>5. Ceertz, p. 210.
				<lb/>6. In Ceoria Kaufman’s videotape, “Women, Ritual, and Re
				<lb/>ligion,&quot; 1977
				<lb/>7. Mary Daly, Beyond Cod the Father (Boston: Beacon Press,
				<lb/>1974), p. 13, italics added.
				<lb/>8. Simone de Beauvoir, The Second Sex, trans. H.M. Parshleys
				<lb/>(New York: Knopf, 1953).
				<lb/>9. Monique Wittig, Les Cuérillères, trans. David LeVay (New
				<lb/>York: Avon Books, 1971), p. 89.
				<lb/>10. Personal communication.
				<lb/>11. A term coined by Naomi Goldenberg to refer to reflection on
				<lb/>the meaning of the symbol “Goddess.&quot;
				<lb/>12. This theory of the origins of the Western dualism is stated by
				<lb/>Rosemary Ruether in New Woman: New Earth (New York:
				<lb/>Seabury Press, 1975
				<lb/>13. Heinrich Kramer and Jacob Sprenger, Malleus Maleficarum
				<lb/>(New York: Dover, 1971), p. 47.
				<lb/>14. See Rita M. Gross, “Menstruation and Birth in Rituals in
				<lb/>Australia,” The Journal of the American Academy of Religion
				<lb/>(in press).
				<lb/>15. Judy Chicago, Through the Flower (New York: Doubleday,
				<lb/>1975), plate 4.
				<lb/>16. See Adrienne Rich, Of Woman Born (New York: Bantam
				<lb/>Books, 1977), chap. 6 and 7.
				<lb/>17. Wolfgang Lederer, The Fear of Women (New York: Harcourt,
				<lb/>Brace, Jovanovich, 1958)
				<lb/>18. See James Mellaart, Earliest Civilizations of the Near East
				<lb/>(New York: McGraw-Hill, 1965), p. 92
				<lb/>19. Barbry MyOwn, &quot;Ursa Maior: Menstrual Moon Celebration,&quot;
				<lb/>in Moon, Moon, by Anne Kent Rush (Berkeley &amp; New York:
				<lb/>Moon Books &amp; Random House, 1976), pp. 374-38
				<lb/>20. Starhawk, &quot;Witchcraft and Women’s Culture,&quot; p. 16.
				<lb/>21. In Judy Chicago, pp. 213-217
				<lb/>2. Valerie S. Goldstein, “The Human Situation: A Feminine
				<lb/>View,&quot; Journal of Religion (vol. 40, 1959), pp. 100-112.
				<lb/>23. Virginia Woolf, A Room of One’s Own (New York: Harcourt,
				<lb/>Brace, Jovanovich, 1957), p. 86.
				<lb/>24. Rich, p. 226.
				<lb/>25. De Beauvoir, pp. 488-489.
				<lb/>&quot;Old Time Woman,&quot; lyrics by Jeffrey Langley and Holly
				<lb/>Near, from Holly Near: A Live Album (Redwood Records,
				<lb/>1974).
				<lb/>&quot;Started Out Fine,&quot; by Holly Near, from Holly Near: A Live
				<lb/>Album.
				<lb/>28. Rich, p. 223.
			</p>
			</div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
