<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/CSS/heresies_cwrc.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Changing the Hymns to Hers</title>
            <author>Toni Head</author>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Eowyn Andres</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Lyndon Beier</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-2025)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Mia DeRoco</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-2025)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
               <resp>Editor, encoder (2021)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Zoha Nadeer</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Bri Perea</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Carrie Pirmann</persName>
               <resp>HTR editor, encoder (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Ricky Rodriguez</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Valeria Riley</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Zaely Rodriguez</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2025-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2025)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Kelly Troop</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-2025)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Lucy Wadswoth</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2025)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Anna Marie Wingard</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-2025)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Olivia Wychock</persName>
               <resp>Graduate Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
            <funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
            <funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
            <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <name>Bucknell University</name>
               <address>
                  <street>One Dent Drive</street>
                  <settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
                  <region>Pennsylvania</region>
                  <postCode>17837</postCode>
               </address>
            </distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0
                  International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
               <licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title>The Great Goddess</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and Politics</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>
                        <address>
                           <name>Heresies</name>
                           <postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
                           <settlement>New York</settlement>
                           <region>New York</region>
                           <postCode>10013</postCode>
                        </address>
                     </pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div><pb n='15'/>
            <pb n='16'/>
            <head><title>Changing the Hymns to Hers</title></head>
            <byline><persName>Toni Head</persName></byline>
            <p>
               During the past five years of total immersion in the
               feminist movement, I have shared with other feminists
               the frustration of repeatedly running up against the stone
               wall of religious dogma. This dogma functions to preserve
               patriarchal institutions and to prevent the establishment
               of equal rights and opportunities for women in the United
               States and other countries throughout the world. Far from
               becoming more tolerant as time passes, fundamentalist
               sects are ever more rigid in their efforts to maintain the
               subjugation of women. Ironically, religious faiths, which
               supposedly provide the moral and ethical basis of culture,
               are stubbornly and irrationally opposed to the development of a truly just, humane, equitable society.</p>
               <p>My personal religious beliefs underwent a cataclysmic
               change during adolescence, when overnight I emerged
               from an intensely religious period into what has remained
               a questioning, agnostic search for a satisfactory philosophy to sustain me through life. During my childhood and
               adolescence, I deeply experienced the damage done by
               the prevalent attitudes towards females. Perhaps for this
               reason, 1finally found a possible answer in feminism.</p>
               <p>Of all my experiences, the most fulfilling sense of unity
               and of purpose and belief, within myself and within relationships, has come from reading feminist literature
               meeting, working, demonstrating, agonizing, organizing
               and occasionally celebrating with my sisters. Nevertheless, I still felt a lack, a sense of something missing. When
               my reading progressed to a number of books, which have
               appeared in recent years, describing the matriarchal cultures and religions that existed in prehistoric times,
               began to understand why</p>
               <p>Itried to imagine what it must have been like to live in
               a society where people worshipped a female deity and
               where women held positions of power and responsibility.
               What would it feel like to pray to God the Mother? To sing
               paeans of praise to Her glory? As l experimented, in spite
               of my essential agnosticism, I found myself feeling a great
               sense of peace in the mere act of praying to a loving,
               female God. The experience was light-years away from
               the nightmares I had suffered as a child of being consigned to hell by a punitive male god. I also felt deep
               anguish to know that such religions had existed thousands
               of years ago, only to have been ruthlessly destroyed by
               barbaric patriarchal invaders.</p>
               <p>When I discussed these ideas with feminists from other
               parts of the world, at the International Women’s Year
               Tribune in Mexico City, at the International Tribunal on
               Crimes Against Women in Brussels and with women I met
               during other travels, they were as enthusiastic as my
               sisters closer to home.
            </p>
            <p>
               The IWY Florida Conference in Orlando last July provided the stimulus to goad me into action. Mormons,
               Baptists and various fundamentalist religious groups were
               there in force, joined with the American Nazi Party, John
               Birch Society and Ku Klux Klan to try to subvert the
               conference. When they began singing hymns, I sang along
               but with one major difference: I changed the hymns to
               Hers. When they sang, &quot;He’s got the whole world in his
               hands,&quot; l happily warbled, &quot;She’s got the whole world..
               When the conference closed with a recitation of the
               Lord’s Prayer, I joyfully intoned, “Our Mother who art in
               heaven...&quot; And when I returned home after the conference was over, I sent my granddaughter a new version
               of Jesus Loves Me, which is:</p>
               <p>Isis loves me, this I know
               <lb/>Mother God has told me so.
               <lb/>She is strong and so are we
               <lb/>Fighting for equality.
               <lb/>Yes, Isis loves me
               <lb/>Yes, Isis loves me
               <lb/>Yes, Isis loves me
               <lb/>Our Lady told me so.</p>
               <p>After the Orlando conference, Becky Berg, Florida
               State Coordinator of the National Organization for Women, asked me to help her conduct a workshop on women
               and religion at the Florida NOW State Conference last
               September. In preparation for this conference I began to
               think through some of the ideas that had been taking form
               in my mind.</p>
               <p>The sum total of my experiences led me to realize that
               lack of faith in an organized religion had left a hole in my
               life which no amount of rational, philosophical speculations about the meaning of it all can fill. The fact is
               enjoy the rituals, symbols, songs, processions, ceremonies
               —the full panoply of organized religion. I like to wear
               clothing and jewelry that express my commitment to and
               faith in my beliefs. I enjoy singing along with people,
               joining hands, performing rites and acts that physically
               demonstrate and symbolize my emotional, spiritual and
               philosophical self—my deepest being. But I also realize
               that I am quite incapable of participating in such rituals
               while being totally opposed to the doctrines they represent. There is no way I can take part in a religion that
               preaches the subjugation of women.</p>
               <p>The answer to this dilemma then became so obvious
               that I am shocked not to have found it sooner. I believe
               the answer is to reinstate a feminist religion that can fulfill
               the human need for religious rituals at the same time that
               it celebrates our feminist faith in the ultimate good of
            </p>
            <pb n='17'/>
            <p>
               being female and invokes the Mother-God-given right of
               every woman to enjoy full freedom and equal opportunity
               in all aspects of life.</p>
               <p>Such a religion would provide opportunities for women
               to meet together to take part in ceremonies and to reaffirm our faith in our feminist beliefs. This spiritual and
               emotional renewal would strengthen the bonds among us.
               Besides providing spiritual sustenance, the feminist
               religion could be a powerful tool in our fight for equal
               rights. In spite of the supposed Constitutional separation
               of church and state, the fact is that our legal codes are
               based on patriarchal religious dogmas and customs. The
               frequency with which opponents of the Equal Rights
               Amendment and other feminist issues quote the Bible to
               justify their opposition is evidence enough of the use of
               religion for political purposes. The doctrine of an organized religion that propounds feminist values as the
               direct reflection of Divine Intention is the ultimate answer
               to those who argue that a male god has decreed otherwise. Fighting fire with fire, our rites could help us win our
               rights.</p>
               <p>The NOW conference workshop offered the opportunity to explain these feelings and experiences to other
               women and to propose that we establish our own feminist
               religion. I also offered a few specific suggestions that
               seemed positive. First, that the religion be as undogmatic
               and non-authoritarian as possible to best serve as a vehicle for expressing the thoughts, feelings, needs and
               desires of all of us. Second, that care must be exercised to
               avoid forming the usual hierarchy of clergy as separate
               from congregation and to assure maximum participation
               of everyone concerned in formulating and carrying out
               the doctrines and rituals of a feminist religion.</p>
               <p>I do, however, believe that a formal women’s religious
               organization would be economically advantageous in that
               it would enable us to have access to the tax benefits
               allowed to other religious groups. These benefits could
               help to cover the cost of clinics, publications, learning
               centers and many other aspects of the women’s movement</p>
               <p>In addition to these considerations, there is one fundamental principle that I feel must be basic to our religion
               if it is to express feminist beliefs. This is the divine right of
               every child to be born to a mother who wants it, which in
               turn would assure every woman the right to control her
               own body and to bear children only when and if she
               wholeheartedly wants to do so. I feel that the act of
               exercising this control, whether by means of birth control,
               abortion or abstention, should be considered to be in
               total accord with our belief in &quot;divine intention.</p>
               <p>I would also like to see the physical fact of being
               female sanctified and celebrated. Since the aura of guilt
               and disgust surrounding female physiology promulgated
               by a misogynistic patriarchy is so destructive and damaging to women’s emotional and physical well-being,
               would like to see this attitude replaced by feelings of joy
               and self-affirmation in the inherent good of being female.</p>
               <p>Generally, I would like our feminist religion to be
               positive, joyous and free of fear. Rather than teaching the
               dogma of original sin, we could proclaim the fact of
               original good. I would prefer a list of “Thou shalts” rather
               than &quot;Thou shalt nots&quot; and a philosophy of rewards for
               doing good rather than punishments for doing wrong.
               would like our religion to affirm the intrinsic good of all
               expressions of love between humans, regardless of sex or
               of other artificial restrictions imposed by a patriarchal
               autocracy.
            </p>
            <p>
               Along with the suggestions that have been mentioned,
               we would welcome a wide diversity of other ideas, according to people’s needs and desires. These might come
               from Wicca, Zen or any other source that we feel has
               something valuable to offer us.</p>
               <p>In summary, I would like to mention that the enthusiastic response of those who took part in the NOW work-shop convinced me that many women feel the need for a
               religion of our own and I suggest that the time is ripe for
               establishing it now.</p>
               <p>The Mother Church Inc. is legally incorporated in the
               state of Florida. Its members are now in the process of
               applying for tax exempt status. Toni Head writes, &quot;According to NARAL, various Dioceses and Archdioceses of
               the Catholic Church contributed over §450,000 from January 1976 to March 1977 to the National Committee for a
               Human Life Amendment to make abortions illegal by a
               constitutional amendment. That is only the record of
               contributions of $500 or more. In order to protect the
               principle of separation of church and state, I think that
               there should be no tax exemptions for religions, but since
               there are, it is essential that we share the advantage.</p>
               <p>&quot;The Mother Church Bulletin“ is available from The
               Mother Church. If interested, write to: The Mother
               Church, P.O. Box 2188, Satellite Beach, Florida 32937.
            </p></div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
