<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/CSS/heresies_cwrc.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Issue 5 Masthead</title>
            <author>The Collective</author>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Eowyn Andres</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Lyndon Beier</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-2025)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Mia DeRoco</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-2025)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
               <resp>Editor, encoder (2021)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Zoha Nadeer</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Bri Perea</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Carrie Pirmann</persName>
               <resp>HTR editor, encoder (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Ricky Rodriguez</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Valeria Riley</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Zaely Rodriguez</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2025-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2025)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Kelly Troop</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-2025)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Lucy Wadswoth</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2025)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Anna Marie Wingard</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-2025)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Olivia Wychock</persName>
               <resp>Graduate Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
            <funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
            <funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
            <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <name>Bucknell University</name>
               <address>
                  <street>One Dent Drive</street>
                  <settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
                  <region>Pennsylvania</region>
                  <postCode>17837</postCode>
               </address>
            </distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0
                  International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
               <licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title>The Great Goddess</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and Politics</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>
                        <address>
                           <name>Heresies</name>
                           <postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
                           <settlement>New York</settlement>
                           <region>New York</region>
                           <postCode>10013</postCode>
                        </address>
                     </pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <pb n='0'/>
            <p>
               <lb/>Great Goddess Collective Members: Mary Albanese, Martha Alsup, Tracy Boyd, Janet Culbertson, Rosemary Dudley,
               <lb/>Mary Beth Edelson, Gail Feinstein, Deborah Freedman, Gina Foglia, Donna Henes, Anne Healy, Buffie Johnson, Diane
               <lb/>Levin, Grace Shinell, Merlin Stone, Carolee Thea, Susan Turner, Mierle Laderman Ukeles.
               <lb/>Our Thanks To: Barbara Baracks, Patsy Beckert, Heidi Blocher, Tony deLuna, Cynthia Eardley, Dinah Foglia, Guido
               <lb/>Foglia, Patricia Frascatore, Su Friedrich, Carol Grosberg, Sue Heinemann, Eileen Hickey, Jacqui Holmes, Sarah Jenkins,
               <lb/>Gail Lineback, Joan Lopate, Nina Masonson, Richard Mayer, Maureen McDonough, Margot Norton, Carolee Schnee
               <lb/>mann, Sidele C. Scot , Peggy Shannon, Helen Tannenbaum, Janey Washburn. the Lesbian Herstory Archives.
               <lb/>Layout: Mary Albanese, Gail Feinstein, Gina Foglia, Susan Turner.
               <lb/>The Creat Goddess Collective Statement
               <lb/>In putting together this issue on The Great Goddess/Women’s Spirituality, we wanted to offer a holistic
               <lb/>concept of the Goddess and to move beyond an inside/outside duality. We also recognized a need to counter
               <lb/>the distrust that most women harbor towards religion and any aspect of spirituality because of the oppression
               <lb/>that we have all experienced from patriarchal religions.
               <lb/>During the year that we have been working together, our collective process has passed through several
               <lb/>phases. In the beginning we had meetings attended by 30 or more women, which required us to separate into
               <lb/>committees. The committee division continued to evolve and resulted in three main editorial groupings:
               <lb/>Personal/Ritual/Poetry/Fiction; Archaeological/Historical/Political/Theological; and Visual, which selected
               <lb/>material for submission to the full collective. Initially we attempted to create a review system so that everyone
               <lb/>could have an opportunity to see all submissions. However, some material could not be easily duplicated and
               <lb/>few people made the independent effort to look through the material from other committees. Because we were
               <lb/>committed to the concept of total collective energy and process, we held a marathon weekend on a Long Island
               <lb/>farm where more than 30 women met in a communal atmosphere to review and make recommendations about
               <lb/>submissions. Over the next four months the full collective continued to make selections and often reviewed
               <lb/>rejected material. Committees were engaged in editing, shortening long articles to fit within space limitations,
               <lb/>retyping, phoning and corresponding with contributors and soliciting material. During this intense period,
               <lb/>members often had to attend three and four meetings a week. Our numbers dwindled to about 20
               <lb/>In the next phase we reviewed the editing of accepted pieces and began layout and design of the magazine.
               <lb/>Because we were far behind schedule, a number of women who had worked hard were no longer able to give
               <lb/>priority to their involvement in the collective. Also only a few women were willing to become heavily involved
               <lb/>in production work. Some women pitched in; some women hung in; some women checked in. But, again,
               <lb/>throughout this phase all decisions were open to the full collective at specially arranged meetings. We felt that
               <lb/>we had to make an effort to respect the contributions of all without assessing participation. We did not want to
               <lb/>regard decision-making as a power
               <lb/>There was often muted and, occasionally, dramatic conflict. In a smaller group, confrontation and its
               <lb/>resolution would have had to be more directly resolved, but the size of our group permitted distancing and an
               <lb/>evasion of differences that sometimes left individuals antagonistically engaged or estranged. A basic source of
               <lb/>contention was our disparate definitions of the Goddess. Nor did we find an honest way to handle the implicit
               <lb/>and often explicit coercion involved in submitting our own work. Egotism about individual creations and their
               <lb/>significance/prominence flared. Our own inefficiency and ineptitude wearied us. The work was not equally
               <lb/>shared, although the decision process was. Decision-making in so large a group was extremely slow. Our original
               <lb/>committee division aroused factionalism. Members of committees felt that their subject matter was not being
               <lb/>fully respected by members of other committees and defensive attitudes developed. However, our slowness may
               <lb/>have achieved a greater fairness and even our factionalism may have clarified viewpoints that otherwise would
               <lb/>have been blunted by the consensus-voting process, and right to this moment, we have continued to challenge
               <lb/>ourselves by seeking collective consensus on an infinitude of decisions. We feel that we tested the collective
               <lb/>process and that that process not only produces the most representative work but also withstands the greatest
               <lb/>stresses. Although our sharing must include the knowledge of how we were often divided against ourselves
               <lb/>there were also many good times when we shared a heightened regard for each other, when we felt that we were
               <lb/>touched by the Goddess.
               <lb/>From the Heresies Collective
               <lb/>HERESIES is an idea-oriented journal devoted to the examination of art and politics from a feminist perspective. We believe that what
               <lb/>is commonly called art can have a political impact, and that in the making of art and of all cultural artifacts our identities as women play a
               <lb/>distinct role. We hope that HERESIES will stimulate dialogue around radical political and aesthetic theory, encourage the writing of the
               <lb/>history of femina sapiens, and generate new creative energies among women. It will be a place where diversity can be articulated. We are
               <lb/>committed to the broadening of the definition and function of art
               <lb/>HERESIES is structured as a collective of feminists, some of whom are also socialists, marxists, lesbian feminists or anarchists; oun
               <lb/>fields include painting, sculpture, writing, anthropology, literature, performance, art history, architecture and filmmaking. While the
               <lb/>themes of the individual issues will be determined by the collective, each issue will have a different editorial staff made up of women who
               <lb/>want to work on that issue as well as members of the collective. Proposals for issues may be conceived and presented to the HERESIES
               <lb/>Collective by groups of women not associated with the collective. Each issue will take a different visual form, chosen by the group re
               <lb/>sponsible. HERESlES will try to be accountable to and in touch with the international feminist community. An open evaluation meeting
               <lb/>will be held after the appearance of each issue. Topics for issues will be announced well in advance in order to collect material trom many
               <lb/>sources. Possibly satellite pamphlets and broadsides will be produced continuing the discussion of each central theme. As part of its
               <lb/>commitment to the women’s community, HERESIES provides workshops in all phases of magazine production and maintains the Women
               <lb/>Artists’ Slide Registry
               <lb/>As women, we are aware that historically the connections between our lives, our arts and our ideas have been suppressed. Once these
               <lb/>connections are clarified they can function as a means to dissolve the alienation between artist and audience, and to understand the
               <lb/>relationships between art and politics, work and workers. As a step toward a demystification of art, we reject the standard relationship of
               <lb/>criticism to art within the present system, which has often become the relationship of advertiser to product. We will not advertise a new set
               <lb/>of genius-products just because they are made by women. We are not committed to any particular style or aesthetic, nor to the competi
               <lb/>tive mentality that pervades the art world. Our view of feminism is one of process and change, and we feel that in the process of dialogue
               <lb/>we can foster a change in the meaning of art.
               <lb/>THE COLLECTIVE: Ida Applebroog, Patsy Beckert, Joan Braderman, Mary Beth Edelson, Su Friedrich, Janet Froelich, Harmony Hammond,
               <lb/>Sue Heinemann, Elizabeth Hess, Joyce Kozloff, Arlene Ladden, Gail Lineback, Lucy Lippard, Marty Pottenger, Miriam Schapiro, Amy
               <lb/>Sillman, Joan Snyder, Elke Solomon, Pat Steir, May Stevens, Elizabeth Weatherford, Sally Webster.
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
