<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/CSS/heresies_cwrc.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Three Faces of Goddess Spirituality</title>
            <author>Merlin Stone</author>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Eowyn Andres</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Lyndon Beier</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-2025)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Mia DeRoco</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-2025)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
               <resp>Editor, encoder (2021)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Zoha Nadeer</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Bri Perea</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Carrie Pirmann</persName>
               <resp>HTR editor, encoder (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Ricky Rodriguez</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Valeria Riley</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Zaely Rodriguez</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2025-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2025)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Kelly Troop</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-2025)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Lucy Wadswoth</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2025)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Anna Marie Wingard</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-2025)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Olivia Wychock</persName>
               <resp>Graduate Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
            <funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
            <funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
            <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <name>Bucknell University</name>
               <address>
                  <street>One Dent Drive</street>
                  <settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
                  <region>Pennsylvania</region>
                  <postCode>17837</postCode>
               </address>
            </distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0
                  International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
               <licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title>The Great Goddess</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and Politics</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>
                        <address>
                           <name>Heresies</name>
                           <postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
                           <settlement>New York</settlement>
                           <region>New York</region>
                           <postCode>10013</postCode>
                        </address>
                     </pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         			<div><pb n='2'/>
			<p>
				<lb/>The Three Faces of Goddess Spirituality
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>Merlin Stone
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>In considering the already widespread and in
				<lb/>creasing interest in the diverse manifestations of
				<lb/>Goddess spirituality within the feminist movement,
				<lb/>it may be helpful to clarify at least three emerging
				<lb/>aspects of this relatively new phenomenon. These
				<lb/>three aspects, of what may be the most unexpected
				<lb/>occurrence within the feminist movement, have de
				<lb/>veloped, separately and together, in a rather incred
				<lb/>ibly organic &quot;grass roots” manner. Perhaps only
				<lb/>within the flexibility of a feminism that is continual
				<lb/>ly evolving out of the process of consciousness rais
				<lb/>ing in its truest sense has this outgrowth of feminist
				<lb/>consciousness been able to develop and grow.
				<lb/>Since all three of these aspects of Goddess spir
				<lb/>ituality appear to be simultaneously growing from
				<lb/>one central trunk, I drew lots (a method used at the
				<lb/>prophecy-providing shrines of the Goddess in an
				<lb/>cient times) to decide their linear placement. This
				<lb/>placement in no way implies that one aspect is of
				<lb/>greater importance than another or precedes the
				<lb/>others in actual development and, as you will see,
				<lb/>many connections link the three.
				<lb/>The first aspect of Goddess spirituality is the
				<lb/>emerging interest in the history and prehistory of
				<lb/>ancient cultures that worshipped a female deity and
				<lb/>in the laws and customs of those societies. Through
				<lb/>research in archaeology, history, anthropology
				<lb/>and using this information to analyze ancient lit
				<lb/>erature and mythology—we have begun to discover
				<lb/>that far from the generally accepted idea that the
				<lb/>Judeo-Christian religions rescued women from sup
				<lb/>posedly more barbarian and anti-woman societies
				<lb/>women have actually lost a great deal of status and
				<lb/>physical and material autonomy since the inceptior
				<lb/>of these and other male-worshipping religions. As a
				<lb/>result of this research, which covers the period fron
				<lb/>the Neolithic Goddess shrines of about 8000 B.C. to
				<lb/>the closing of the last Goddess temples in the early
				<lb/>Christian periods of Byzantium, we have learned
				<lb/>that many Goddess-worshipping societies were mat
				<lb/>rilineal, matrilocal and matrifocal. In many of these
				<lb/>societies, women owned property, engaged in busi
				<lb/>ness and held the highest positions of the clergy. In
				<lb/>such societies children automatically belonged to
				<lb/>their mother’s clan and took their mother’s family
				<lb/>name.
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>Through this research we are discovering the
				<lb/>roots of today’s attitudes toward women’s bodies
				<lb/>and minds. These attitudes become clear as we
				<lb/>study them within the context of the original institu
				<lb/>tion of patrilineal, patrilocal and patrifocal systems
				<lb/>under the aegis of the worship of a supreme deity as
				<lb/>male. Though it required many millennia tosuppress
				<lb/>the Goddess religion and its social customs, this
				<lb/>ancient religion was eventually designated as &quot;pa
				<lb/>gan” and its remaining vestiges were obliterated by
				<lb/>early Christian emperors, medieval inquisitions and
				<lb/>witch burnings
				<lb/>In our growing interest and efforts to explore the
				<lb/>truth about the past, we are building, and hopefully
				<lb/>we will continue to build, a body of evidence that
				<lb/>bears witness to the many millennia in which the
				<lb/>Creator was regarded as female and in which womer
				<lb/>held a much higher status than we have known since
				<lb/>that time. This aspect of Goddess spirituality within
				<lb/>the feminist movement is motivated by much the
				<lb/>same feeling that has encouraged us to rediscover
				<lb/>and reclaim female artists, writers, scientists, polit
				<lb/>ical leaders and other important women who were
				<lb/>ignored by the writers of the history books with
				<lb/>which we were educated. This information affords
				<lb/>an entirely new perspective on current stereotypes
				<lb/>of women. It provides a broader view, as the per
				<lb/>spective which allows us to look into the past also
				<lb/>allows us to see further ahead.
				<lb/>The second aspect is that of a growing concern
				<lb/>with a feminist perception of spirituality and theol
				<lb/>ogy. It has emerged from feminist consciousness, an
				<lb/>inkling or more of the first aspect and the perhaps
				<lb/>ever-present search for answers to such theological
				<lb/>questions as the possible purposes (or nonpurpose,
				<lb/>of existence, the true nature of morality (or im
				<lb/>morality), birth, death and the nature of mind as it is
				<lb/>revealed in intelligence, intuition and reason. For
				<lb/>many centuries women have been taught that if they
				<lb/>cared to consider these questions at all (the implica
				<lb/>tion being that such questions were actually too
				<lb/>abstract for female minds), answers were to be
				<lb/>found in the words and writings of male priests
				<lb/>male ministers, male rabbis and male gurus —all of
				<lb/>whom supposedly had greater spiritually contem
				<lb/>plative abilities as well as more direct access to
				<lb/>knowledge of The Divine Plan or Cosmic Process.
			</p>
			
			<pb n='3'/>
			<p>
				<lb/>A feminist contemplation of spiritual and theo
				<lb/>logical questions soon makes us painfully aware that
				<lb/>the answers with which we have so far been provid
				<lb/>ed have existed in close relationship to, or more
				<lb/>often within, a personified Life Force that is nearly
				<lb/>always linguistically, and more often actually, con
				<lb/>sidered to be of the male gender. Not too surprising
				<lb/>ly, &quot;answers” about divine intentions are often as
				<lb/>male-oriented as the men who provide them. The
				<lb/>exceptional rate of growth of feminist concerns with
				<lb/>Goddess spirituality in itself reveals a level of con
				<lb/>sciousness that refuses and refutes this male-de
				<lb/>signed hierarchy and its appropriation of theological
				<lb/>and spiritual considerations—and the subsequent
				<lb/>divine” decrees.
				<lb/>So far, and let us hope in the future as well, fem
				<lb/>inists concerned with Goddess spirituality have sel
				<lb/>dom offered absolute or pat answers to theological
				<lb/>questions. What has been happening is the experi
				<lb/>encing, and at times the reporting, of these personal
				<lb/>or group experiences: how it feels to regard the Ul
				<lb/>timate Life Force in our own image—as females;
				<lb/>how it feels to openly embrace and to share our own
				<lb/>contemplations and intuitive knowledge about the
				<lb/>role of women on this planet; how it feels to gain a
				<lb/>sense of direction, a motivating energy, a strength, a
				<lb/>courage—somehow intuited as coming from a cos
				<lb/>mic female energy force that fuels and refuels us in
				<lb/>our struggle against all human oppression and
				<lb/>planetary destruction.
				<lb/>Some say they find this force within themselves
				<lb/>others regard it as external. Some feel it in the
				<lb/>ocean, the moon, a tree, the flight of a bird or in the
				<lb/>constant stream of coincidences (or noncoin
				<lb/>cidences) that occur in our lives. Some find access
				<lb/>to it in the lighting of a candle, chanting, meditating
				<lb/>— alone or with other women. From what 1 have so
				<lb/>far read, heard or experienced myself, I think it safe
				<lb/>to say that all women who feel they have experi
				<lb/>enced Goddess spirituality in one way or another al
				<lb/>so feel that they have gained an inner strength and
				<lb/>direction that temporarily or permanently has
				<lb/>helped them to deal with life. Most women interest
				<lb/>ed or involved in feminist concepts of spirituality do
				<lb/>not regard this spirituality as an end in itself but as a
				<lb/>means of gaining and giving strength and under
				<lb/>standing that will help us to confront the many
				<lb/>tangible and material issues of the blatant inequities
				<lb/>of society as we know it today
				<lb/>The third aspect of Goddess spirituality is con
				<lb/>cerned with the more circumspect observation of
				<lb/>the organized male-worshipping, male-clergied
				<lb/>religions of today—an examination of the specific
				<lb/>ways in which these religions have instituted and
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>maintained a secondary status for women. Involve
				<lb/>ment in Goddess spirituality has encouraged us to
				<lb/>take a more careful look at the scriptures, rituals and
				<lb/>the gender of the decision-making level of the clergy
				<lb/>of the religions in which we were raised and/or
				<lb/>those that affect the society in which we live.
				<lb/>Some of the most urgent issues confronting con
				<lb/>temporary women all over the planet are those con
				<lb/>cerning economic survival, abortion, contraception,
				<lb/>rape, clitorectomy, infibulation, divorce, attitudes
				<lb/>toward &quot;illegitimacy”, lesbian rights, social pressure
				<lb/>to marry and to have children, physical and psycho
				<lb/>logical violence, attitudes toward women’s bodies
				<lb/>and the stereotypes of woman as follower rather
				<lb/>than leader and sexual and reproductive being rather
				<lb/>than as total human being.
				<lb/>A careful reading of the Bible still used by Judeo
				<lb/>Christian congregations reveals the ancient origins
				<lb/>of many of these important feminist issues. The
				<lb/>proclamation in Gen. 3:16 informs both women and
				<lb/>men that women are expected, as the result of a
				<lb/>divine” decree, to be sexually faithful and subser
				<lb/>vient to their husbands and that the pains of child
				<lb/>birth are to be regarded as &quot;divine” retribution —the
				<lb/>will of God” as it is asserted over the will of woman.
				<lb/>Deut. 22:28,29 requires that a raped virgin be mar
				<lb/>ried to the man who raped her. Deut. 22:22-24 stip
				<lb/>ulates that a raped betrothed woman should be put
				<lb/>to death (unless the rape occurred in the deserted
				<lb/>countryside). Deut. 22:20-22 states that a bride dis
				<lb/>covered not to be a virgin should be dragged from
				<lb/>the house and stoned to death. Deut. 22:22 declares
				<lb/>that a married woman should be put to death if
				<lb/>found lying with a man (no excuse for rape is men
				<lb/>tioned). Deut. 24:1 decrees that a man has the right
				<lb/>to divorce his wife on his decision alone, while no
				<lb/>provision is made for a woman who desires to
				<lb/>divorce her husband. Each of these biblical laws re
				<lb/>veals the intense efforts made to control reproduc
				<lb/>tive capacities, and thus the sexual activities of
				<lb/>women, by the men who wrote these laws and by
				<lb/>those who followed them.
				<lb/>Our understanding and analysis of these biblical
				<lb/>laws and their subsequent effects on contemporary
				<lb/>women become clear only in the context of histor
				<lb/>ical information which reveals that these laws were
				<lb/>devised at much the same time that matrilineal cus
				<lb/>toms were being destroyed and patrilineal systems
				<lb/>initiated. In a patrilineal system, knowledge of
				<lb/>paternity is vital. This knowledge takes on even
				<lb/>greater import when the system is declared to be an
				<lb/>integral aspect of The Divine Plan and thus any chal
				<lb/>lenge to the patrilineal system and certain knowl
				<lb/>edge of paternity may be considered blasphemy—at
			</p>
			<pb n='4'/>
			<p>
				<lb/>times punishable by death. Even today, socio
				<lb/>religious attitudes toward &quot;unwed mothers” and &quot;il
				<lb/>legitimacy” have not yet been thoroughly examined
				<lb/>and challenged as a vital feminist issue.
				<lb/>The institution and maintenance of a patrilineal
				<lb/>system were further abetted by biblical laws such as
				<lb/>Num. 30 requiring that a daughter’s or a wife’s vow
				<lb/>must be regarded as null and void unless confirmed
				<lb/>by father or husband—making it impossible for most
				<lb/>women to engage in business activities and thus lim
				<lb/>iting their access to economic autonomy. Num. 27
				<lb/>explains that the rights to family inheritance are ac
				<lb/>cesssible only to sons, unless there are no male
				<lb/>heirs, and Num. 36 decrees that if a woman does
				<lb/>inherit in such a situation, she must then marry only
				<lb/>within her father’s tribe. Written about 3,000 years
				<lb/>ago, these laws still exist in the Old Testament of the
				<lb/>Judeo-Christian Bible. Though the last few genera
				<lb/>tions may have forgotten or rejected these laws, can
				<lb/>we afford to ignore them in our efforts to understand
				<lb/>the origins of attitudes toward women as wage
				<lb/>earners today?
				<lb/>Judeo-Christian laws and decrees have deeply af
				<lb/>fected the secular laws and attitudes of our contem
				<lb/>porary patrilineal society. All too often we discover
				<lb/>them to be the probable origins of many of the prob
				<lb/>lems we face today such as the right of each woman
				<lb/>to be able to control her own physical body and its
				<lb/>functions; access to abortion; in some countries, ac
				<lb/>cess to contraception and divorce; the concept of
				<lb/>&quot;illegitimacy” and the social and legal pressures sur
				<lb/>rounding it; social and legal attitudes on lesbian
				<lb/>love; physical violence against women, stereotypes
				<lb/>of whore and madonna; double standards for pre
				<lb/>marital virginity and marital fidelity; attitudes toward
				<lb/>women’s access to earning power (including choice
				<lb/>of vocation, education, advancement in chosen
				<lb/>field and levels of economic recompense) and the
				<lb/>so-called &quot;natural” assumption of male leadership
				<lb/>in political, intellectual and spiritual spheres
				<lb/>Each of these issues is an anger-provoking re
				<lb/>minder of the longstanding power of male-oriented,
				<lb/>male-dominated religions. It is for this reason that it
				<lb/>is vital to fully understand the connections between
				<lb/>these attitudes, biblical laws and the initial institu
				<lb/>tion of the patrilineal system in which we live. The
				<lb/>supremacy of “Father in Heaven” is a mere reflec
				<lb/>tion of the supremacy of &quot;father on earth”. The
				<lb/>status of father is magnified beyond biological re
				<lb/>ality by the patrilineal system and it is this system
				<lb/>that is the underlying foundation of all patriarchal
				<lb/>ideas and actions. Refusing to acknowledge paternal
				<lb/>identity may be one of the most revolutionary acts
				<lb/>possible.
				<lb/>Even today, the absence or extreme minority of
				<lb/>women in decision-making levels of the clergy of
				<lb/>nearly all Jewish, Catholic, and Protestant congrega
				<lb/>tions ensures that these biblical decrees and sub
				<lb/>sequent attitudes will retain their original power.
				<lb/>Perhaps more important, we must remember that
				<lb/>biblical laws and attitudes have extended far beyond
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>the walls of any specific church or temple and are
				<lb/>now deeply embedded within so-called secular law
				<lb/>and social custom. Despite the supposed separa
				<lb/>tion of church and state, women’s demands in early
				<lb/>feminist struggles for women’s suffrage were contin
				<lb/>ually challenged and obstructed by clergymen who
				<lb/>claimed sole access to knowledge of The Divine
				<lb/>Plan—and women voting was not part of it.
				<lb/>It is also of interest that along with sexist atti
				<lb/>tudes, racism and slavery were justified by the &quot;re
				<lb/>ligious” idea that heathens had no souls—thus al
				<lb/>lowing &quot;good&quot; Christians to invade the land of the
				<lb/>Native Americans, decimating them as a people and
				<lb/>appropriating their property, and to kidnap Africans
				<lb/>and to use them as slaves. Male-oriented religion&apos;s
				<lb/>more passive acceptance of racism is still to be seen
				<lb/>in the racial segregation of churches.
				<lb/>Goddess spirituality offers us the immediate and
				<lb/>inherent refutation of the institutionalized &quot;re
				<lb/>ligious” values that have for too long been used as
				<lb/>weapons of oppression. From this third aspect of
				<lb/>Goddess spirituality grows the consciousness of, and
				<lb/>the direct challenge to, these “religious” laws and
				<lb/>attitudes that have played such a large part in for
				<lb/>mulating the roles of women in contemporary
				<lb/>society
				<lb/>In all of its aspects, Goddess spirituality has
				<lb/>grown from our continually feeling, speaking, com
				<lb/>paring, analyzing, feminist-consciousness-raising
				<lb/>process—the very core of our new perceptions and
				<lb/>thus our motivating energies. Our consciousness has
				<lb/>now been raised—to the point where we can no
				<lb/>longer ignore the suppression or perversion of
				<lb/>evidence on the roles of women in the ancient God
				<lb/>dess-worshipping cultures; the trivializing of wom
				<lb/>en’s thoughts and ideas on spiritual and theological
				<lb/>considerations of existence, from personal to
				<lb/>planetary; and the oppression of women as it has
				<lb/>been instituted and maintained within the patrilin
				<lb/>eal, male-worshipping religions and the effect this
				<lb/>has had on society.
				<lb/>Though some may want to question the political
				<lb/>viability of Goddess spirituality within the feminist
				<lb/>struggle, few would deny its existence within the
				<lb/>feminist community or the reality of the existence of
				<lb/>the many contributors to this issue (those included
				<lb/>as well as those whose work was not included as a
				<lb/>result of space limitations). We invite you, as a read
				<lb/>er of this issue of Heresies, not only to view or read
				<lb/>the many thoughts and ideas that are included but
				<lb/>to consider them in light of our ever-expanding fem
				<lb/>inist consciousness, that same consciousness that
				<lb/>has until now helped us to avoid the undigested ac
				<lb/>ceptance of other, usually male-developed political
				<lb/>analyses (party lines). Goddess spirituality has
				<lb/>grown from our consciousness-raising process; it has
				<lb/>grown from US. It may be the ultimate heresy—and
				<lb/>it may ultimately be what allows us to succeed
				<lb/>where so many others have failed.
				<lb/>OMERLIN STONE 9978
			</p>
			</div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
