<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/CSS/heresies_cwrc.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>The Three Faces of Goddess Spirituality</title>
				<author>Merlin Stone</author>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Eowyn Andres</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Lyndon Beier</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2023-2025)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
					<resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Mia DeRoco</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2023-2025)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
					<resp>Editor, encoder (2021)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Zoha Nadeer</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Bri Perea</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Carrie Pirmann</persName>
					<resp>HTR editor, encoder (2023-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Ricky Rodriguez</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
					<resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Valeria Riley</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Zaely Rodriguez</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2025-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2021-2025)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Kelly Troop</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2023-2025)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Lucy Wadswoth</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2022-2025)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Anna Marie Wingard</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2023-2025)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Olivia Wychock</persName>
					<resp>Graduate Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
				<funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
				<funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
				<funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>
					<name>Bucknell University</name>
					<address>
						<street>One Dent Drive</street>
						<settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
						<region>Pennsylvania</region>
						<postCode>17837</postCode>
					</address>
				</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial
						4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
					<licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title>The Great Goddess</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and
								Politics</publisher>
							<pubPlace>
								<address>
									<name>Heresies</name>
									<postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
									<settlement>New York</settlement>
									<region>New York</region>
									<postCode>10013</postCode>
								</address>
							</pubPlace>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<pb n="2"/>
				<head>
					The Three Faces of Goddess Spirituality </head>
				<byline>
					Merlin Stone </byline>
				<p> In considering the already widespread and increasing interest in the diverse
					manifestations of Goddess spirituality within the feminist movement, it may be
					helpful to clarify at least three emerging aspects of this relatively new
					phenomenon. These three aspects, of what may be the most unexpected occurrence
					within the feminist movement, have developed, separately and together, in a
					rather incredibly organic &quot;grass roots” manner. Perhaps only within the
					flexibility of a feminism that is continually evolving out of the process of
					consciousness raising in its truest sense has this outgrowth of feminist
					consciousness been able to develop and grow.</p>
				<p>Since all three of these aspects of Goddess spirituality appear to be
					simultaneously growing from one central trunk, I drew lots (a method used at the
					prophecy-providing shrines of the Goddess in ancient times) to decide their
					linear placement. This placement in no way implies that one aspect is of greater
					importance than another or precedes the others in actual development and, as you
					will see, many connections link the three.</p>
				<p>The first aspect of Goddess spirituality is the emerging interest in the history
					and prehistory of ancient cultures that worshipped a female deity and in the
					laws and customs of those societies. Through research in archaeology, history,
					anthropology and using this information to analyze ancient lit erature and
					mythology—we have begun to discover that far from the generally accepted idea
					that the Judeo-Christian religions rescued women from supposedly more barbarian
					and anti-woman societies women have actually lost a great deal of status and
					physical and material autonomy since the inceptior of these and other
					male-worshipping religions. As a result of this research, which covers the
					period from the Neolithic Goddess shrines of about 8000 B.C. to the closing of
					the last Goddess temples in the early Christian periods of Byzantium, we have
					learned that many Goddess-worshipping societies were matrilineal, matrilocal and
					matrifocal. In many of these societies, women owned property, engaged in
					business and held the highest positions of the clergy. In such societies
					children automatically belonged to their mother’s clan and took their mother’s
					family name. </p>
				<p> Through this research we are discovering the roots of today’s attitudes toward
					women’s bodies and minds. These attitudes become clear as we study them within
					the context of the original institution of patrilineal, patrilocal and
					patrifocal systems under the aegis of the worship of a supreme deity as male.
					Though it required many millennia tosuppress the Goddess religion and its social
					customs, this ancient religion was eventually designated as &quot;pagan” and its
					remaining vestiges were obliterated by early Christian emperors, medieval
					inquisitions and witch burnings</p>
				<p>In our growing interest and efforts to explore the truth about the past, we are
					building, and hopefully we will continue to build, a body of evidence that bears
					witness to the many millennia in which the Creator was regarded as female and in
					which womer held a much higher status than we have known since that time. This
					aspect of Goddess spirituality within the feminist movement is motivated by much
					the same feeling that has encouraged us to rediscover and reclaim female
					artists, writers, scientists, political leaders and other important women who
					were ignored by the writers of the history books with which we were educated.
					This information affords an entirely new perspective on current stereotypes of
					women. It provides a broader view, as the perspective which allows us to look
					into the past also allows us to see further ahead.</p>
				<p>The second aspect is that of a growing concern with a feminist perception of
					spirituality and theology. It has emerged from feminist consciousness, an
					inkling or more of the first aspect and the perhaps ever-present search for
					answers to such theological questions as the possible purposes (or nonpurpose,
					of existence, the true nature of morality (or immorality), birth, death and the
					nature of mind as it is revealed in intelligence, intuition and reason. For many
					centuries women have been taught that if they cared to consider these questions
					at all (the implication being that such questions were actually too abstract for
					female minds), answers were to be found in the words and writings of male
					priests male ministers, male rabbis and male gurus —all of whom supposedly had
					greater spiritually contemplative abilities as well as more direct access to
					knowledge of The Divine Plan or Cosmic Process. </p>

				<pb n="3"/>
				<p> A feminist contemplation of spiritual and theological questions soon makes us
					painfully aware that the answers with which we have so far been provided have
					existed in close relationship to, or more often within, a personified Life Force
					that is nearly always linguistically, and more often actually, considered to be
					of the male gender. Not too surprisingly, &quot;answers” about divine intentions
					are often as male-oriented as the men who provide them. The exceptional rate of
					growth of feminist concerns with Goddess spirituality in itself reveals a level
					of consciousness that refuses and refutes this male-designed hierarchy and its
					appropriation of theological and spiritual considerations—and the subsequent
					divine” decrees.</p>
				<p>So far, and let us hope in the future as well, feminists concerned with Goddess
					spirituality have seldom offered absolute or pat answers to theological
					questions. What has been happening is the experiencing, and at times the
					reporting, of these personal or group experiences: how it feels to regard the
					Ultimate Life Force in our own image—as females; how it feels to openly embrace
					and to share our own contemplations and intuitive knowledge about the role of
					women on this planet; how it feels to gain a sense of direction, a motivating
					energy, a strength, a courage—somehow intuited as coming from a cosmic female
					energy force that fuels and refuels us in our struggle against all human
					oppression and planetary destruction.</p>
				<p>Some say they find this force within themselves others regard it as external.
					Some feel it in the ocean, the moon, a tree, the flight of a bird or in the
					constant stream of coincidences (or noncoincidences) that occur in our lives.
					Some find access to it in the lighting of a candle, chanting, meditating — alone
					or with other women. From what 1 have so far read, heard or experienced myself,
					I think it safe to say that all women who feel they have experienced Goddess
					spirituality in one way or another also feel that they have gained an inner
					strength and direction that temporarily or permanently has helped them to deal
					with life. Most women interested or involved in feminist concepts of
					spirituality do not regard this spirituality as an end in itself but as a means
					of gaining and giving strength and understanding that will help us to confront
					the many tangible and material issues of the blatant inequities of society as we
					know it today</p>
				<p>The third aspect of Goddess spirituality is concerned with the more circumspect
					observation of the organized male-worshipping, male-clergied religions of
					today—an examination of the specific ways in which these religions have
					instituted and </p>
				<p> maintained a secondary status for women. Involvement in Goddess spirituality has
					encouraged us to take a more careful look at the scriptures, rituals and the
					gender of the decision-making level of the clergy of the religions in which we
					were raised and/or those that affect the society in which we live.</p>
				<p>Some of the most urgent issues confronting contemporary women all over the planet
					are those concerning economic survival, abortion, contraception, rape,
					clitorectomy, infibulation, divorce, attitudes toward &quot;illegitimacy”,
					lesbian rights, social pressure to marry and to have children, physical and
					psychological violence, attitudes toward women’s bodies and the stereotypes of
					woman as follower rather than leader and sexual and reproductive being rather
					than as total human being.</p>
				<p>A careful reading of the Bible still used by Judeo-Christian congregations
					reveals the ancient origins of many of these important feminist issues. The
					proclamation in Gen. 3:16 informs both women and men that women are expected, as
					the result of a divine” decree, to be sexually faithful and subservient to their
					husbands and that the pains of child-birth are to be regarded as &quot;divine”
					retribution —the will of God” as it is asserted over the will of woman.</p>
				<p>Deut. 22:28,29 requires that a raped virgin be married to the man who raped her.
					Deut. 22:22-24 stipulates that a raped betrothed woman should be put to death
					(unless the rape occurred in the deserted countryside). Deut. 22:20-22 states
					that a bride discovered not to be a virgin should be dragged from the house and
					stoned to death. Deut. 22:22 declares that a married woman should be put to
					death if found lying with a man (no excuse for rape is mentioned). Deut. 24:1
					decrees that a man has the right to divorce his wife on his decision alone,
					while no provision is made for a woman who desires to divorce her husband. Each
					of these biblical laws reveals the intense efforts made to control reproductive
					capacities, and thus the sexual activities of women, by the men who wrote these
					laws and by those who followed them.</p>
				<p>Our understanding and analysis of these biblical laws and their subsequent
					effects on contemporary women become clear only in the context of historical
					information which reveals that these laws were devised at much the same time
					that matrilineal customs were being destroyed and patrilineal systems initiated.
					In a patrilineal system, knowledge of paternity is vital. This knowledge takes
					on even greater import when the system is declared to be an integral aspect of
					The Divine Plan and thus any challenge to the patrilineal system and certain
					knowledge of paternity may be considered blasphemy—at </p>
				<pb n="4"/>
				<p> times punishable by death. Even today, socioreligious attitudes toward
					&quot;unwed mothers” and &quot;illegitimacy” have not yet been thoroughly
					examined and challenged as a vital feminist issue.</p>
				<p>The institution and maintenance of a patrilineal system were further abetted by
					biblical laws such as Num. 30 requiring that a daughter’s or a wife’s vow must
					be regarded as null and void unless confirmed by father or husband—making it
					impossible for most women to engage in business activities and thus limiting
					their access to economic autonomy. Num. 27 explains that the rights to family
					inheritance are accesssible only to sons, unless there are no male heirs, and
					Num. 36 decrees that if a woman does inherit in such a situation, she must then
					marry only within her father’s tribe. Written about 3,000 years ago, these laws
					still exist in the Old Testament of the Judeo-Christian Bible. Though the last
					few generations may have forgotten or rejected these laws, can we afford to
					ignore them in our efforts to understand the origins of attitudes toward women
					as wage earners today?</p>
				<p>Judeo-Christian laws and decrees have deeply affected the secular laws and
					attitudes of our contemporary patrilineal society. All too often we discover
					them to be the probable origins of many of the problems we face today such as
					the right of each woman to be able to control her own physical body and its
					functions; access to abortion; in some countries, access to contraception and
					divorce; the concept of &quot;illegitimacy” and the social and legal pressures
					surrounding it; social and legal attitudes on lesbian love; physical violence
					against women, stereotypes of whore and madonna; double standards for premarital
					virginity and marital fidelity; attitudes toward women’s access to earning power
					(including choice of vocation, education, advancement in chosen field and levels
					of economic recompense) and the so-called &quot;natural” assumption of male
					leadership in political, intellectual and spiritual spheres.</p>
				<p>Each of these issues is an anger-provoking reminder of the longstanding power of
					male-oriented, male-dominated religions. It is for this reason that it is vital
					to fully understand the connections between these attitudes, biblical laws and
					the initial institution of the patrilineal system in which we live. The
					supremacy of “Father in Heaven” is a mere reflection of the supremacy of
					&quot;father on earth”. The status of father is magnified beyond biological
					reality by the patrilineal system and it is this system that is the underlying
					foundation of all patriarchal ideas and actions. Refusing to acknowledge
					paternal identity may be one of the most revolutionary acts possible.</p>
				<p>Even today, the absence or extreme minority of women in decision-making levels of
					the clergy of nearly all Jewish, Catholic, and Protestant congregations ensures
					that these biblical decrees and subsequent attitudes will retain their original
					power. Perhaps more important, we must remember that biblical laws and attitudes
					have extended far beyond </p>
				<p> the walls of any specific church or temple and are now deeply embedded within
					so-called secular law and social custom. Despite the supposed separation of
					church and state, women’s demands in early feminist struggles for women’s
					suffrage were continually challenged and obstructed by clergymen who claimed
					sole access to knowledge of The Divine Plan—and women voting was not part of
					it.</p>
				<p>It is also of interest that along with sexist attitudes, racism and slavery were
					justified by the &quot;religious” idea that heathens had no souls—thus allowing
					&quot;good&quot; Christians to invade the land of the Native Americans,
					decimating them as a people and appropriating their property, and to kidnap
					Africans and to use them as slaves. Male-oriented religion&apos;smore passive
					acceptance of racism is still to be seen in the racial segregation of
					churches.</p>
				<p>Goddess spirituality offers us the immediate and inherent refutation of the
					institutionalized &quot;religious” values that have for too long been used as
					weapons of oppression. From this third aspect of Goddess spirituality grows the
					consciousness of, and the direct challenge to, these “religious” laws and
					attitudes that have played such a large part in formulating the roles of women
					in contemporary society.</p>
				<p>In all of its aspects, Goddess spirituality has grown from our continually
					feeling, speaking, comparing, analyzing, feminist-consciousness-raising
					process—the very core of our new perceptions and thus our motivating energies.
					Our consciousness has now been raised—to the point where we can no longer ignore
					the suppression or perversion of evidence on the roles of women in the ancient
					Goddess-worshipping cultures; the trivializing of women’s thoughts and ideas on
					spiritual and theological considerations of existence, from personal to
					planetary; and the oppression of women as it has been instituted and maintained
					within the patrilineal, male-worshipping religions and the effect this has had
					on society.</p>
				<p>Though some may want to question the political viability of Goddess spirituality
					within the feminist struggle, few would deny its existence within the feminist
					community or the reality of the existence of the many contributors to this issue
					(those included as well as those whose work was not included as a result of
					space limitations). We invite you, as a reader of this issue of Heresies, not
					only to view or read the many thoughts and ideas that are included but to
					consider them in light of our ever-expanding feminist consciousness, that same
					consciousness that has until now helped us to avoid the undigested acceptance of
					other, usually male-developed political analyses (party lines). Goddess
					spirituality has grown from our consciousness-raising process; it has grown from
					US. It may be the ultimate heresy—and it may ultimately be what allows us to
					succeed where so many others have failed.</p>
				<p>©MERLIN STONE 9978 </p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
