<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BucknellDSC/heresies/main/CSS/heresies_cwrc.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Masks, Power and Sisterhood in an African Society</title>
            <author>Carolee Thea</author>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Eowyn Andres</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Lyndon Beier</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-2025)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Mia DeRoco</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-2025)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
               <resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
               <resp>Editor, encoder (2021)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Zoha Nadeer</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Bri Perea</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Carrie Pirmann</persName>
               <resp>HTR editor, encoder (2023-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Ricky Rodriguez</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
               <resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Valeria Riley</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Zaely Rodriguez</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2025-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2025)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Kelly Troop</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-2025)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Lucy Wadswoth</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2022-2025)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Anna Marie Wingard</persName>
               <resp>Editor (2023-2025)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Olivia Wychock</persName>
               <resp>Graduate Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
            <funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
            <funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
            <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <name>Bucknell University</name>
               <address>
                  <street>One Dent Drive</street>
                  <settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
                  <region>Pennsylvania</region>
                  <postCode>17837</postCode>
               </address>
            </distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0
                  International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
               <licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title>The Great Goddess</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and Politics</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>
                        <address>
                           <name>Heresies</name>
                           <postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
                           <settlement>New York</settlement>
                           <region>New York</region>
                           <postCode>10013</postCode>
                        </address>
                     </pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         			<div>
				<pb n='106'/>
			<p>
				<lb/>Masks, Power and Sisterhood
				<lb/>in an African Society
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>Carolee Thea
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>European and eastern matriarchal traditions, rites and
				<lb/>art forms have been obscured and even obliterated, but in
				<lb/>certain areas of the world, women have managed to retain
				<lb/>much of their heritage and a measure of political equality.
				<lb/>The means have often been compromises —at a cost that
				<lb/>few of us can believe would be willingly paid. Yet western
				<lb/>women have paid the equivalent price without benefit. It
				<lb/>is important for us to obtain a perspective concerning the
				<lb/>matriarchal traditions of this unique and spiritual society
				<lb/>at a time when we are struggling to discover and create
				<lb/>our own.
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>The tribal societies of rainy West Africa still maintain
				<lb/>traditions developed over years ot experience in a harsh
				<lb/>environment. The secret societies of these cultures are
				<lb/>responsible for teaching social values and celebrating the
				<lb/>rites of passage. In effect, they are the perpetuators of
				<lb/>traditional codes. Among the Mende, Vai, Temne and
				<lb/>Sherbro tribes of Sierra Leone and Liberia, there are two
				<lb/>important secret societies: the Poro for men and the
				<lb/>Bundu for women.
				<lb/>It was through their art that 1 first learned about the
				<lb/>secret order of the Bundu women. Their masks intrigued
				<lb/>me. What does a masking tradition mean in terms of the
				<lb/>lives of the women in this tribal society? How do they
				<lb/>establish sexual identities and define the status of women
				<lb/>in short, how do they perpetuate a stable social order?
				<lb/>The Bundu is the only masked secret society of women
				<lb/>in all of Africa. It functions within what appears to be a
				<lb/>male-oriented culture concurrent with the Poro to main
				<lb/>tain a balanced social order. Through the mask, Bundu
				<lb/>women obtain power beyond that granted for merely
				<lb/>domestic functions. They may hold public office, even
				<lb/>that of Paramount Chief, and they are influential in gov
				<lb/>ernment and business decisions. Their presence and their
				<lb/>political acumen permeate most tribal activity, including
				<lb/>rituals, land distribution and marriage.
				<lb/>The Bundu, like other female secret societies, prepares
				<lb/>its young women for wifehood and motherhood and trains
				<lb/>them for various vocational activities reserved by tradi
				<lb/>tion for women. It is their access to a storehouse of secret
				<lb/>knowledge that places them on the same level as mem
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>bers of the Poro. This knowledge enables them tofunction
				<lb/>in important political and decision-making capacities
				<lb/>Not to be a member of a secret society is to be exclud
				<lb/>ed from important political and social decisions, as well
				<lb/>as group functions, knowledge and powers. Moreover, it
				<lb/>is only as a Bundu member that a woman may become a
				<lb/>leader. A succession of leaders are held sacred within the
				<lb/>Chapters. That the Bundu have their own founding an
				<lb/>cestors is vital. They are the intermediaries between the
				<lb/>people and Ngewo, the apex of the spirit world. He is re
				<lb/>garded as the ultimate creator from whom everything is
				<lb/>derived.
				<lb/>Initiation to the first level of the Bundu normally oc
				<lb/>curs at fourteen or fifteen. Kenneth Little adds that among
				<lb/>the Bundu, an older woman may also be initiated if she
				<lb/>chooses. However, initiation rites of female adolescents
				<lb/>usually occur at the beginning of menstruation or preg
				<lb/>nancy, at which time the initiates are taught by those who
				<lb/>are informed or experienced.? Moreover, the extended
				<lb/>Bundu training engenders both independence and a
				<lb/>strong sense of sisterhood by permitting girls to loosen
				<lb/>ties with their mothers at the same time that they make
				<lb/>new ties with other adult women of the community.
				<lb/>The initiatory sessions are announced by means of a
				<lb/>circular sent around in the form of a small piece of sokolo,
				<lb/>tobacco. Fees, money, cloth or other commodities are
				<lb/>due at this time. The number of initiates depends on both
				<lb/>local support and available teachers. Usually the enroll
				<lb/>ment is not more than thirty.
				<lb/>The first event of the initiation tests the girl’s commit
				<lb/>ment and will mark her for life. It will also deny her the
				<lb/>full knowledge of her sexual nature, for it is at this time
				<lb/>that she must submit to the partial removal of her cli
				<lb/>toris.* The denial of women’s sexuality is a patriarchal
				<lb/>practice the world over, but in this case, the sexual mu
				<lb/>tilation of women was probably introduced and enforced
				<lb/>by Arab conquerors.» By systematically ritualizing the
				<lb/>practice, the Bundu women have brought it under their
				<lb/>control. Yet custom prevents the cessation of the practice
				<lb/>and has further distorted its original meaning. It should be
				<lb/>noted that with much less power and perspicacity, west
				<lb/>ern women have submitted to mutilation by “modern"
				<lb/>medical men.1
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>*Female circumcision, including sunna circumcision, excision
				<lb/>clitoridectomy, infibulation and pharaonic circumcision are
				<lb/>mutilations that are still practiced in Africa. According to a
				<lb/>conservative estimate, it affects the life and health of 20 to 25
				<lb/>million women.
				<lb/>Fran Hosken: “Female Circumcision and Fertility in Africa,
				<lb/>Women &amp; Health (Vol. 1, No. 6, November/December 1976,
				<lb/>p. 3.)
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>fAs late as the 1930s, clitoridectomies and female circumcision
				<lb/>were medically prescribed in various parts of the United States
				<lb/>and Europe as a cure for masturbation, psychological disorders
				<lb/>and even kleptomania.
				<lb/>G.). Barker-Benfield: “A Historical Perspective on Women's
				<lb/>Health Care—Female Circumcision," Women &amp; Health, Vol. 1,
				<lb/>No. 1, January/February 1976, p. 14.
			</p>
			<pb n='107'/>
			<p>
				<lb/>During the first stage of initiation, the girls are kept
				<lb/>secluded, out of the sight of men and other uninitiated
				<lb/>persons. They are now admitted to the "sacred bush, the
				<lb/>Bundu school, and taught the lore, the songs and the
				<lb/>dances that mark important social and religious cere
				<lb/>monies of the tribe.
				<lb/>When the initiation wounds are healed, the second
				<lb/>stage begins. On a certain day, the initiates are taken to a
				<lb/>stream and washed. A cowrie shell, hung on cotton
				<lb/>thread, is then tied around their necks. This shell (a sim
				<lb/>ulacrum of the clitoris) is an indication of their sanctity
				<lb/>henceforth and must be respected by every Mende per
				<lb/>son. The initiates then enter the town in the evening and
				<lb/>dance, showing something of what they learned in the
				<lb/>bush. In accord with the evident puberty rites, the high
				<lb/>light of the occasion is a feast featuring a communal bowl
				<lb/>with a phallus made of rice.
				<lb/>After the public ceremonies, there is a private convo
				<lb/>cation at which the girls are sworn to secrecy concerning
				<lb/>Bundu ritual and knowledge. As part of the oath taking,
				<lb/>their heads are plastered in mud, and the washing off of
				<lb/>this mud signifies the attainment of womanly status. Led
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>by the chief Bundu woman, who invokes her ancestral
				<lb/>spirit, the proud initiates return in a procession to the
				<lb/>town. The next three days are spent on the verandas of
				<lb/>their parents’ houses, where they receive the admiration
				<lb/>of friends and relatives.?
				<lb/>With the attainment of this level of initiation, awoman
				<lb/>may commission a mask to be made. She chooses a carver
				<lb/>familiar with the rituals and symbols of the society and
				<lb/>tells him the name of the ancestor for her mask; he then
				<lb/>secludes himself in the bush to visualize the spirit that will
				<lb/>eventually inhabit it. The carvers are always men, in ac
				<lb/>cord with the tradition of strict division of labor.
				<lb/>However, the mask provides a perspective on the
				<lb/>initiated woman’s power. It is during the masked ritual,
				<lb/>private and public, that the Bundu appear so formidable.
				<lb/>They surround themselves with the exotic, the mysterious,
				<lb/>and the grotesque. This aura is confirmed by the visible
				<lb/>and invisible accoutrements of masks, costumes, dances
				<lb/>and sounds—or silence and secrecy. With all of these
				<lb/>means, the Bundu invokes the Goddess of the Mask, who
				<lb/>is called Sowei.° Sowei is the personification of all those
				<lb/>aspects of the ideal and powerful associated with Earth
				<lb/>Mother and Queen. She is clearly a cult object to be wor
				<lb/>shipped and revered by men and women. The iconog
				<lb/>raphy of the mask is material and sensual, which furthen
				<lb/>reflects this ideal.
				<lb/>The mask illustrated here is from the Sherbro Islands,
				<lb/>off the coast of Sierra Leone in West Africa. The basic
				<lb/>form of the mask, and others of its kind, is a bell shape or
				<lb/>helmet. The most prominent feature is the bulging ringed
				<lb/>neck, which suggests wealth, fertility and beauty.” This
				<lb/>aspect expresses the Mende equation of corpulence with
				<lb/>fertility and is reminiscent of Goddesses and female icons.
				<lb/>The forehead and cheeks are protruding and round, also
				<lb/>implying corpulence. Erich Neumann, in his book The
				<lb/>Creat Mother, writes: “One means by which early man
				<lb/>could represent the numinous magnificence and arche
				<lb/>typal uniqueness of the Feminine consisted in an expres
				<lb/>sive ’exaggeration' of form and an accentuation of her
				<lb/>elementary character””° (suggesting her fertility).
				<lb/>The slit eyes and closed mouth symbolize the fact that
				<lb/>the Bundu spirit never speaks. Her silence is equated with
				<lb/>power and judgment. When she wishes to communicate,
				<lb/>she does so through one of the lower members of the
				<lb/>Bundu, a Ligba.
				<lb/>The elaborate braided pattern of the hair indicates the
				<lb/>importance placed on this feature. Emblematically, hair is
				<lb/>power. The braid may be interpreted in the same mannen
				<lb/>as the entwined snakes found on the waist of the principal
				<lb/>Goddess figure at Knossos or perhaps in the same way as
				<lb/>the snake hair of the Gorgons. The snake, a lower earth
				<lb/>symbol of fertility, represents the Terrible Mother."1 Em
				<lb/>bedded in the hair of this mask are small phylacteries,
				<lb/>serving as both ornamental and totemic references to
				<lb/>Islam.1
				<lb/>The horns on the helmet are considered to have special
				<lb/>energy. The Mende and other African tribes believe that
				<lb/>horns are the repository of an animal’s power or life force
				<lb/>Horns are also tied around the neck or waist of children to
				<lb/>protect them from evil spirits.13, Tribal members believe
				<lb/>that they can psychically identify with a particular animal
				<lb/>and have access to its powers to protect themselves from
				<lb/>known and unknown spirits. The adopted object or animal
				<lb/>is called a "bush soul.
				<lb/>On top of the mask is a bird perched on a cup. One
				<lb/>interpretation is that the bird symbolizes spiritual tran
				<lb/>scendence. Another, specific to the Mende, is that this is
				<lb/>a Bofio, a bird that is said by some to receive messages
			</p>
			<pb n='108'/>
			<p>
				<lb/>ith the spirits.14
				<lb/>from the spirits and, by others, tot
				<lb/>The woman who commissions a mask decides whethen
				<lb/>it is satisfactory and then performs a ritual inviting the
				<lb/>spirit to enter the mask. Before the spirit can enter, how
				<lb/>ever, the Bundu costume must be complete. Raffia, dyed
				<lb/>black, is attached to the mask, and a cloth suit with the
				<lb/>sleeve ends sewn closed is worn over long black stockinge
				<lb/>and shoes. By completely covering her body, the dancer
				<lb/>prevents the spirit from entering her rather than entering
				<lb/>the mask.15
				<lb/>The masked dancer may carry a bunch of twigs or a
				<lb/>sword in her covered hands, and she points or gesticulates
				<lb/>with it. She never speaks, but may dance to the accom
				<lb/>paniment of the Seligura, a calabash rattle. Her move
				<lb/>ments include a rhythmic swaying and various arm ges
				<lb/>tures. If the dancer becomes hot and perspires, she may
				<lb/>remove her helmet and costume only it her face remains
				<lb/>concealed by one of her attendants, who carries a mat
				<lb/>specifically to hide the dancer’s countenance from view. 16
				<lb/>When the masked Bundu woman appears in public with
				<lb/>her musicians, it generally means that somebody (usually
				<lb/>a male) is going to be accused of an offense against Bundu
				<lb/>laws.17 The violator will be brought before the masked
				<lb/>woman to confront her ancestral spirit. Concealed by her
				<lb/>mask, the Bundu woman listens without reply, but she
				<lb/>conveys her spirit’s judgment through the Ligbas, the first
				<lb/>level members of the Bundu society.18
				<lb/>To move beyond a description of the aesthetic and
				<lb/>exotic is to consider the Bundu woman as a force in a
				<lb/>patriarchal society. Historically, African societies have
				<lb/>recognized female power. The Bantu had queens without
				<lb/>prince consorts. Independent queens ruled the Fanti on
				<lb/>the Gold Coast, which was the center of a matriarchy.
				<lb/>There were female rulers throughout the entire Zambesi
				<lb/>area in the northern Congo basin. In Togoland, the queens
				<lb/>had chieftains to help rule, but the latter could make
				<lb/>decisions only with the consent of a female council. The
				<lb/>West African matriarchy extended to the Atlantic Islands.
				<lb/>Helen Diner, in Mothers and Amazons, writes: "In the
				<lb/>oldest times, there were no reigning princes in Africa, but
				<lb/>the Negroes had great Kingdoms, ruled by Goddesses
				<lb/>These Goddesses had Priests and Priestesses who took
				<lb/>care of all government business in the name of their
				<lb/>sacred Mistresses."1
				<lb/>Mystically, African societies recognize female powers
				<lb/>as directly related to the fecundity and magic associated
				<lb/>with the earth. Further, woman experienced herself as the
				<lb/>subject and object of mysterious processes and as a vessel
				<lb/>of transformation and a mana figure.“ "Man marvels at
				<lb/>these mysterious powers in woman’s body, Simone de
				<lb/>Beauvoir writes
				<lb/>Like cattle and crops he wanted his clan to engender other
				<lb/>men who could perpetuate it while perpetuating the fertility
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>of the fields; all nature seemed to him like a mother; the
				<lb/>land is woman and in women abide the same dark powers
				<lb/>as in the earth. It was for this reason in part that agricultural
				<lb/>labor was entrusted to woman able to summon ancestral
				<lb/>spirits into her body; she would also have power to cause
				<lb/>fruits and grain to spring up from the planted fields. In both
				<lb/>cases there was no question of a creative act, but of magic
				<lb/>conjuration. Yet children and crops seemed nonetheless to
				<lb/>be gifts of the gods, and the mysterious emanations from
				<lb/>the female body were believed to bring into this world the
				<lb/>riches latent in the mysterious sources of life.2
				<lb/>That women were recognized to have this magical
				<lb/>creative ability constituted a formidable power base, par
				<lb/>ticularly in a society that was dependent on the continua
				<lb/>tion of traditions and lineage. Such unassailable power
				<lb/>surely inspired in men a respect twinged with fear, a
				<lb/>factor which ultimately must have contributed to the
				<lb/>domination ot women. Consequently, male masking may
				<lb/>have developed as a redress to what was perceived as a
				<lb/>social and spiritual imbalance. For the same reason, fe
				<lb/>male masking (among the Bundu), may have developed
				<lb/>after the conquest of patriarchal Moslems and the installa
				<lb/>tion of male power figures. Female circumcision and
				<lb/>phallus worship must also be outgrowths of this patri
				<lb/>archal takeover.
				<lb/>Clitoridectomy is an operation performed to rid wom
				<lb/>en of their “maleness,” (the clitoris being likened to the
				<lb/>penis). As Aristotle said, "If the clitoris is the seat of
				<lb/>woman’s pleasure, then away with it! Women are meant
				<lb/>to bear children; that she should draw pleasure from the
				<lb/>sexual act is unthinkable."22
				<lb/>Men disliked the idea that women enjoy sex because it
				<lb/>suggested that man was made for woman's pleasure and
				<lb/>not woman for man’s convenience. Thus, in removing the
				<lb/>possibility of sexual pleasure, patriarchs could be more
				<lb/>confident that women would remain sexually faithful. 23 *
				<lb/>Phallus worship may have been a feature of late matri
				<lb/>archy, while the male generative powers were celebrated
				<lb/>as a complement to the enduringly dominant temale role.
				<lb/>The recently excavated Goddess shrines in the Near East
				<lb/>reveal phalluses of all shapes and sizes (but these fetishes
				<lb/>may as well have been offerings of male devotees to the
				<lb/>Goddess in real or pretended rites of castration). During
				<lb/>the patriarchal takeover, this tentative sacrament was
				<lb/>appropriated and eventually made into a compulsory act
				<lb/>of homage.24
				<lb/>Among the West African Mende, a similar transition
				<lb/>can be noted, although through compromise its impact
				<lb/>has been systematically muted. Although the Bundu may
				<lb/>represent a vestige of the matriarchy, the Poro presence
				<lb/>and the rigidity of sex-defined tasks for women (primarily
				<lb/>domestic) suggest a negotiated arrangement. Even though
				<lb/>chieftancies can be attained by women, property remains
				<lb/>in the control of the male head of the family. Men may be
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>*Fran Hosken, editor of the WOMEN’S INTERNATIONAL NET-
				<lb/>WORK NEWS, recently returned from a six-week visit to 15
				<lb/>countries and 25 cities of sub-Saharan Africa, where she investi
				<lb/>gated the issue of genital mutilation of women. She talked to
				<lb/>gynecologists, midwives and pediatricians who confirmed that
				<lb/>these practices continue everywhere because no one speaks
				<lb/>against them. Furthermore, men often refuse to marry girls not
				<lb/>operated upon; in some areas, it is believed the operation is
				<lb/>required by religion and by the ancestors, and that women who
				<lb/>do not have it are prostitutes. It is said that the operation is
				<lb/>needed to preserve the family, and that excised women are more
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>fertile. However, polygamy and excision have often been cor
				<lb/>related. In 1960, at a seminar on the "Participation of Women
				<lb/>in Public Life," the World Health Organization was asked by
				<lb/>the African participants to undertake a study of the medical
				<lb/>aspects ot "operations based on customs to which many women
				<lb/>were still being subjected." Subsequently, the Economic and
				<lb/>Social Council of the United Nations confirmed this request. To
				<lb/>date, no such Africa-wide study has been made.
				<lb/>Fran Hosken: WOMEN’S INTERNATIONAL NETWORK NEWS,
				<lb/>Press Release (February 1978).
			</p>
			<pb n='109'/>
			<p>
				<lb/>polygamous, whereas women may have only one hus
				<lb/>band. Furthermore, some women, selected from the high
				<lb/>est order of the Bundu, are instructed in the rituals of juju,
				<lb/>or potent magic. However, female powers in juju are so
				<lb/>feared that women may use these rituals on few occa
				<lb/>sions. The secret societies of the Bundu women may be a
				<lb/>vestige of priestly sisterhoods, but the present division of
				<lb/>power, with the greater allocation accorded to the Poro,
				<lb/>is clearly the result of a desperate compromise.
				<lb/>Obvious questions arise not only about the terms of
				<lb/>the bargain struck between the Bundu and the Poro, but
				<lb/>also about the terms we ourselves will accept in establish
				<lb/>ing a complementary relationship necessary for our per
				<lb/>sonal, economic and political stability. One cannot think
				<lb/>of the sexual repression of women in the Victorian Age or
				<lb/>of the use of pom-pom girls at male sporting events in
				<lb/>the present day without realizing that western women
				<lb/>have been forced into unnegotiated compromises. The
				<lb/>Bundu women have retained the right to define them
				<lb/>selves in their secret and elite society. They act as instru
				<lb/>ments of divine revelation and have a command of potent
				<lb/>images, which are the repositories of sacred traditions. Al
				<lb/>this thev teach their daughters, along with self-respect
				<lb/>and sisterhood. But clearly, thev have lost the power to
				<lb/>experience the fullness of their sexual pleasure, and this
				<lb/>has been accompanied by the adulation of male sexua
				<lb/>energy.
				<lb/>If vou had to bargain for not simply vour life, and not
				<lb/>simply the lives of vour children, but the way of life for
				<lb/>vour daughters and granddaughters and all of their
				<lb/>daughters to come, what would vou bargain —vour polit
				<lb/>ical equality, vour economic equity, vour sexual freedom
				<lb/>or vour spiritual sisterhood?
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>1. K.L. Little, The Mende of Sierra Leone (London: Routledge &amp;
				<lb/>Kegan Paul. Ltd. Broadwav House, 1951), p. 1.
				<lb/>2. W. I. Harris and Harr Sawver. The Sorings of Mende Belief
				<lb/>and Conduct (Freetown. Sierra Leone University Press, 1968)
				<lb/>p. 35
				<lb/>3. Franco Monti. African Masks (New York: Paul Hamlyn,
				<lb/>1969), p. 24
				<lb/>4. Harris. p. 127
				<lb/>5. Elizabeth Could Davis, The First Sex (New York: Penguin,
				<lb/>1971).
				<lb/>Harris, p. 127
				<lb/>7. Jacqueline Delange, The Art and Peoples of Black Africa
				<lb/>New Vork. E.P. Dutton &amp; Co., Inc. 1974). p.41
				<lb/>8. W.L. Hummel. Art of the Mende, catalogue (College Park,
				<lb/>Md. Universitvof Maryland Art Callen, 1974).
				<lb/>10. Erich Neumann. The Great Mother: An Analysis of the
				<lb/>Archetype (Princeton. Princeton University Press, 1972).
				<lb/>11. lbid.
				<lb/>12. Hummel, p. 19.
				<lb/>13. J.V. Olufemi Richards. The Sande Mask." African Arts
				<lb/>(Winter 1974. Vol. 7, No. 2), p. 51.
				<lb/>4. Harris. p. 15.
				<lb/>15. Hummel, p. 20.
				<lb/>16. H. U. Hall., The Sherbro of Sierra Leone (Philadelphia, Pa.:
				<lb/>University of Pennsvlvania Press. 1938), p. 8
				<lb/>17. Traditional Carvings and Craftwork from Sierra Leone, cata
				<lb/>logue (london. Commonwealth Institute, August 1961),
				<lb/>p. 4-27
				<lb/>18. Hummel. p. 21.
				<lb/>19. Helen Diner, Mothers and Amazons (New York: Anchor
				<lb/>Press, 1973), p. 76.
				<lb/>20. Neumann, p. 150.
				<lb/>21. Simone de Beauvoir, The Second Sex (New York: A. Knopf
				<lb/>Inc. 1953), p. 63
				<lb/>22. Davis., p. 154.
				<lb/>23. lbid.
				<lb/>24. lbid., 98.
			</p>
			</div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
