<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/LEAF-VRE/code_snippets/refs/heads/main/CSS/leaf.css" title="LEAF" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Women and Anarchy</title>
				<author>Lizzie Borden</author>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Eowyn Andres</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Lyndon Beier</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
					<resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Mia DeRoco</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
					<resp>Editor, encoder (2021)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Zoha Nadeer</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Bri Perea</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Carrie Pirmann</persName>
					<resp>Editor, encoder (2023-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Valeria Riley</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Ricky Rodriguez</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
					<resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Valeria Riley</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Kelly Troop</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Lucy Wadswoth</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2022-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Anna Marie Wingard</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Olivia Wychock</persName>
					<resp>Graduate Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
				<funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
				<funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
				<funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>
					<name>Bucknell University</name>
					<address>
						<street>One Dent Drive</street>
						<settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
						<region>Pennsylvania</region>
						<postCode>17837</postCode>
					</address>
				</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial
						4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
					<licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title>Patterns of Communicating and Space Among Women</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and
								Politics</publisher>
							<pubPlace>
								<address>
									<name>Heresies</name>
									<postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
									<settlement>New York</settlement>
									<region>New York</region>
									<postCode>10013</postCode>
								</address>
							</pubPlace>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb/>
			<div type="essay">
				<pb n="71"
					facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2025-02/heresies02_071.jpg"/>
				<head>Women and Anarchy</head>
				<byline>Lizzie Borden</byline>

				<quote> They say that at the point they have reached they must examine the principle
					that has guided them. They say it is not for them to exhaust their strength in
					symbols. They say henceforward what they are is not subject to compromise. They
					say they must now stop exalting the vulva. They say they must break the last
					bond that binds them to a dead culture.—Monique Wittig, Les Guérillères</quote>
				<p> In the past decade, women have worked together, met together, and talked
					together in ways that have been considered novel, emerging from and at the same
					time creating a new attitude about group organization which proposes only
					egalitarian, non-hierarchical relationships. The methods used in
					support/collaboration (such as consciousness raising) and the kind of group
					created have seemed unique. However, this attitude and these methods have been
					generally restricted to the small group, while the dominant form of mass
					organization among middle class women has been conventionally reformist, aimed
					at changing legislation, working for the ERA and so forth. This kind of
					political work relies on organizing methods historically unrelated to
					significant social change.</p>
				<p>Many women who were in radical politics in the late 1960s have fallen back on
					working methods that can have immediate, tangible effect. This is a recurrent
					problem for the left: should it work for immediate reforms, setting the stage
					for greater ones? Will reform (or opportunism, according to some) eventually
					produce a consciousness sufficiently advanced to change the social structure?
					The women's suffrage movements in England and America were also divided on this
					issue. Some saw the vote as leading to further reforms for women, while others
					saw it as leading to socialism. Today, reformist politics tactically involved
					with a more or less accepted social structure are at odds with attempts by
					radical feminists to rethink society and relationships within society. In the
					criticism of power, bureaucracy and institutional rigidity, in the emphasis on
					the personal, on the family (whatever its form), on education, child care and
					sex —feminists have proved, consciously or not, to be anarchists.</p>
				<p>The anarchist premise of radical feminism is that only through collectivity and
					equality can individuality, autonomy and independence be achieved.
					Individuality, in this sense, means something like "personal and interpersonal
					realization." This is "therapeutic" only when the group helps women "survive"
					within the system, when the group becomes estheticized or escapist and class
					analysis doesn't provide a basis for further organization. Anarchist
					egalitarianism in women's groups has been based not only on political, but on
					ethical or moral grounds which presume that women should behave in a certain
					way—openly, honestly, with integrity. Women, by requiring this of each other,
					sometimes create a feeling of moral superiority over men who, by implication,
					and often in fact, are not honest among themselves, or "in touch with their
					feelings."</p>
				<p>Historically, ethical and egalitarian relationships among women did not result
					only from choice, as was the case with anarchists, but from material conditions
					excluding women from full participation in production and power—and thus from
					the hierarchies of production. Whenever women began to work together, each
					contributing what she knew, there was relatively the same level of experience
					and skill—a necessary or "natural" equality, which often made democracy
					intrinsic to organization. Because woman's domain was traditionally more
					personal, women's political activities tended to center around personal
					questions. (Sheila Rowbotham suggests that this focus is a necessary
					precondition for the mobilization of women en masse.<note>1. Sheila Rowbotham,
						Women, Resistance and Revolution (New York: Vintage Books, 1974), p.
						124.</note>) But the moral imperative, when elicited as a response to
					oppression, often bogs down in the attempt to reconcile morality with
					revolutionary strategy. The impetus behind a moral position is more often
					rational than revolutionary; it is a call to reason, to the recognition of how
					things should be and the decision to make them that way. But the idea that
					change is effected only by reason and understanding can be utopian and/or
					reactionary, since recognition of class and economic contradictions alone cannot
					affect the power relationships behind these conflicts. On the other hand, the
					alliance of feminism with political ideologies that stress revolution,
					especially marxism-leninism, has often been destructive to the radical content
					of feminism. The real question is, then: how can the content of change be
					maintained within a confusion about form? What organizational form will work
					without sacrificing feminist content to political ideologies that maintain
					sexist social institutions?</p>
				<quote>"The law of evolution is that the strongest survives!" "Yes, and the
					strongest, in the existence of any social species, are those who are most
					social. In human terms, most ethical... There is no strength to be gained from
					hurting one another. Only weakness."—Ursula LeGuin, The Dispossessed</quote>
				<p>Thus, feminism's major problem—how to concretize ideas about personal liberty
					within a form of organization that is not hierarchical, that does not contradict
					individual freedom, and that is not utopian—has been anarchism's traditional
					dilemma as well. Anarchist and often feminist arguments tend to be predicated on
					a moral-philosophical belief in a "natural" social state without government or
					male-created institutions—a condition that would be "naturally" reinstated if
					government or male institutions were abolished; that is, Nature herself, or
					women, would produce a better social organism.</p>
				<p>Some of the most influential anarchists—Godwin, Proudhon, Bakunin, Kropotkin, and
					later, Emma Goldman and Federica Montseny—provide the historical precedents for
					many aspects of women's groups. It must be kept in mind, however, that
					anarchists and feminists have often reached the same conclusions from different
					directions, which raises the question of intentionality. For example, William
					Godwin, husband of Mary Wollstonecraft and father of Mary Shelley, imagined the
					world <pb n="72"
						facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2025-02/heresies02_072.jpg"
					/> structured around discussion groups with a purpose similar to consciousness
					raising. His ideal society, as described in Political Justice (1793) was based
					on "public inspection," "positive sincerity, and "political simplicity"—the
					foundation for the first two. This meant reorganization through federalism,
					nations broken down into small autonomous units. Psychological pressure would
					replace force, for people would have to be honest and virtuous in face-to-face
					confrontations. Small discussion groups would encourage the pursuit of
					knowledge, extending laterally to become a universal movement. Godwin's
					speculations, however, were based not in practice but in reaction against the
					retardation of the French Revolution by governmental authority.</p>
				<p>The major impetus of consciousness raising has been Godwinian, centering around
					discussion and inquiry with trust, loyalty and honesty as criteria for respect.
					According to the Red Stockings, the purpose of consciousness raising was to
					"develop female class consciousness through sharing experience and publicly
					exposing the sexist foundations of all our institutions. While the call-to-arms
					was political, the methods were personal, based on the idea that the subjective
					experience of objective conditions can lead to objective analysis. "We regard
					our personal experience, and our feelings about that experience, as the basis
					for an analysis of our common situation.... The notion of equality, as conceived
					by feminists, has had a double mean ing: the struggle to be recognized as equal
					to men (the oppressors) and the struggle to maintain equality among women (so as
					not to oppress each other). "We are committed to achieving internal democracy.
					We will do whatever is necessary to ensure that every woman in our movement has
					an equal chance to participate, assume responsibility, and develop her political
						potential."<note>2. All quotations in this paragraph are from the
						Redstockings Manifesto, July, 1969.</note> Methods like "going around the
					circle" have been used to prevent dominance—and to recognize that personality is
					an instrument of domination.</p>
				<p>However, when consciousness raising fails to distinguish between sex and class
					consciousness and does not acknowledge middle- and working-class contradictions,
					it falls into liberalism —"a moralistically humanitarian and egalitarian
					philosophy of social improvement through the re-education of psychological
						attitudes."<note>3. Charnie Guettel, Marxism &amp; Feminism (Ontario,
						Canada: Women's Educational Press, 1974), p. 3</note> From a marxist point
					of view, there can be no radical analysis if the critique of society rests upon
					change within the individual (or in self-help and education) rather than
					relations of production. While small-group interaction can extend laterally to
					become a mass movement, consciousness raising includes no strategy for mass
					organization. Consequently, while personal interaction can be helpful as a
					beginning—generating support building up individuals' confidence—it remains
					idealistic if every thing stops there.</p>
				<quote>"...wasn't it Odo who said that where there's property there's theft?" "[She
					said] To make a thief, make an owner; to create crime, create laws.' The Social
					Organism. —Ursula LeGuin, The Dispossessed</quote>
				<p>Another strain of feminism is related to the theories of Pierre Joseph Proudhon,
					who carried anarchism into more concrete forms of organization. He wanted to
					rebuild society by creating a federation of communes and cooperatives based on
					"Mutual Aid," through contract and mutual credit, replacing "economic powers"
					with "economic forces. In his statement, "property is theft," Proudhon opposed
					the exploitative accumulation of capital but not property for use.</p>
				<p>Some feminist organizations, such as health centers, credit unions and food
					co-ops, are Proudhonian in their reliance on mutual aid, on exchange of skills
					and services. While such groups can often radicalize a particular community,
					they restrict them selves to immediate need, affecting consumption rather than
					production, and they do not in themselves deal with the sources of production or
					help analyze the power of women in the labor force. This kind of cooperative
					activity is still linked to household activity, which is also about consumption,
					contrary to what the Wages for Housework women argue.</p>
				<p>Cooperative organizations are Proudhonian in their hope that cooperation can
					extend laterally to change the economic and psychological bases of society. If
					the cooperative form is that of the extended family, if it is apolitical, and
					isolationist, like most communes, it simply avoids the realities of production.
					A commune is similar to a consciousness-raising group, it can radically change
					the individuals within it but it is imperialized, economically and socially, by
					external institutions, and can serve only as an example rather than as a
					political force.</p>
				<quote>The women say they have learned to rely on their own strength. They say they
					are aware of the force of their unity. They say, let those who call for a new
					language first learn violence. They say, let those who want to change the world
					first seize all the rifles. They say that they are starting from zero. They say
					that a new world is beginning.—Monique Wittig, Les Guérillères</quote>
				<p>Mikhail Bakunin's influence—on both anarchists and women—seems to be emotional;
					his ideas are based in conventionally "female" modes: "revolution is instinct
					rather than thought, it operates as an instinct, and as an instinct gives first
						battle."<note>4. Mikhail Bakunin, quoted in Eugene Pyziur, The Doctrine of
						Anar chism of Michael A. Bakunin (Baltimore: Gateway Editions, 1955), p.
						17</note> Unlike Proudhon, he did not think institutions could be rebuilt;
					they were to be demolished in a revolution that would culminate in the
					construction of a world where everyone would be free and equal. Bakunin was the
					only influential anarchist to make a constant litany of violence, and his
					statement, "the passion for destruction is a creative passion," became a
					romantic battle cry.</p>
				<p>American middle-class feminist activism has usually not included physical
					violence, although from the time of the temperance societies and the
					suffragettes there have been bloodless demonstrations and guerrilla
					actions—women chaining them selves to benches and fences, hunger strikes, bar
					smashing, window breaking. In England, upper- and middle-class guerrilla actions
					were more violent than those of working-class women because poor wage-earners
					could not risk jail. For middle-class feminists, prison brought class conflict
					into the public eye; upper-class women were given privileges, while bourgeois
					women were treated miserably. They often left jail determined to work for prison
						reform.<note>5. Sheila Rowbotham, "The Vote," Hidden from History (New York:
						Vintage Books, 1976), pp. 77-89.</note> Contemporary feminists who have
					advocated violence and terrorism (such as the Weatherwomen and Susan Saxe) often
					operate in the Bakuninist spirit of acts that seem to be political theater
					rather than effective strategies, ever though these women are not professed
					anarchists. Being forced underground, however, away from usefulness in
					organization, has fostered greater impotence. It is ironic that the legal
					defense of some of these fugitives, once they have been caught, has become an
					organizational focus. Jane Alpert's surrender was an exception, because it
					appeared that she collaborated with the government in locating and arresting her
					friend Pat Swinton. To be jailed for being in contempt of grand juries, for
					refusing to turn state's evidence, has at times been seen as a high honor,
					serving to focus class and sex contradictions better than the original bank
					robberies or bombings.</p>
				<quote>Decentralization had been an essential element in Odo's plans for the society
					she did not live to see founded. She had no intention of trying to de-urbanize
					civilization. Though she suggested that the natural limit to the size of a
					community lay in its dependence on its own immedi- <pb n="73"
						facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2025-02/heresies02_073.jpg"
					/> ate region for essential food and power, she intended that all communities be
					connected by communication and transportation networks, so that goods and ideas
					could get where they were wanted, and the administration of things might work
					with speed and ease, and no community be cut off from change and interchange.
					Ursula LeGuin, The Dispossessed</quote>
				<p>Pêtr Kropotkin may have set the most useful anarchist precedent. Many strands of
					feminism stem from his thought—from anthropologists and historians attempting to
					rewrite the history of women by material analysis of sexism in production in
					early societies, to socialists who have practically rejected marxist-leninist
					authoritarianism but still base their economic analyses on those theories. Both
					Emma Goldman and Federica Montseny were strongly influenced by Kropotkin's
					ideas, especially by his attempt to place anarchism on a scientific and
					evolutionary rather than moral ground. All three advocated a communism that went
					beyond collectives and mutualism, which Kropotkin saw as reflections of
					"mitigated individualism." He argued that communist possession of land and
					individualist production were too contradictory to survive, that the wage system
					should be abolished, that common possession of the means of production implied
					equal consumption, that people should be provided for according to their needs
					rather than the amount of labor they performed. Dismissing any technical
					necessity for large-scale industrialization, Kropotkin argued that the tendency
					of industry was toward decentralization. But small scale was also important for
					the same reason it was for Godwin and for today's feminists —for its reliance on
					trust and honesty in making and keeping agreements. However, Kropotkin's belief
					that change would come through evolution, shared by some feminists, is
					optimistic but utopian. Past glory is as problematic as future glory, and as
					useless to speculate about.</p>
				<quote>We have nothing but our freedom. We have nothing to give you but your own
					freedom. We have no law but the single principle of mutual aid between
					individuals We have no government but the single principle of free association.
					You cannot buy the Revolution. You cannot make the Revolution. You can only be
					the Revolution. It is in your spirit, or it is nowhere.—Ursula LeGuin, The
					Dispossessed</quote>
				<p>During and after the Russian Revolution, anarchists in Russia and elsewhere,
					hoping to create a political science by basing their analyses more concretely on
					economics, rejected the romantic utopianism of their nineteenth-century
					predecessors. There were two major lines of social-anarchist thought—that of the
					anarcho-communists, who were opposed to large-scale industry, and that of the
					anarcho-syndicalists, such as Emma Goldman, who supported trade unionism and
					thought that anarchists should use the capitalist system of production
					progressively to liberate rather than to alienate people. Both groups agreed in
					their opposition to the Bolsheviks when they saw that the "dictatorship of the
					proletariat" really meant the "dictatorship of the Social Democratic Party."</p>
				<p>Emma Goldman, the most famous female anarchist, was one of the harshest critics
					of the Bolshevik government. She came to America as a young Russian immigrant
					and was radicalized by the condition of the working class—long hours in
					sweatshops, unsafe conditions, the sexual exploitation of women workers, the
					prejudice against Jews. Objecting to communist authoritarian ism, she was drawn
					to anarchism. Goldman was influenced by Bakunin's passion for revolt—("As to
					methods. Anarchism is not, as some may suppose, a theory of the future to be
					realized through divine inspiration. It is a living force in the affairs of our
					life, constantly creating new conditions"<note>6. Emma Goldman, Anarchism and
						Other Essays (New York: Dover, 1969), p. 63.</note>)—and by Kropotkin's
					economic analyses of decentralization, his attempt to make anarchism
					scientific—("Just as the animal cells, by mutual cooperation, express their
					latent powers in formation of the com plete organism, so does the individual, by
					cooperative effort with other individuals, attain Ithe) highest form of
					development ..."<note>7. Ibid., p. 36.</note>). Goldman became an
					anarcho-syndicalist, agitating for women's rights, birth control, and labor
					reforms. She was not primarily a feminist, although feminism was part of her
					anarchism, and she criticized women who were committed only to women's suffrage,
					asking why they would want the same right to be oppressed as men. She also
					lambasted middle-class suffragettes for failing to understand the problems of
					working-class women.</p>
				<p>When Goldman was deported during the Red Scare after World War I, she went to
					Russia, but was bitterly disappointed by what she saw as the betrayal of the
						revolution.<note>8. See "The Revolution Betrayed," Patterns of Anarchy
						(Garden City, N.Y.: Anchor Books, 1966), pp. 98-115.</note> She argued that
					the people's passionate yearning for liberty had made the revolution possible,
					in spite of industrial backwardness. The "spirit of mutual purpose" in the labor
					organizations and cooperatives emerged in response to the need for them.
					However, the Bolsheviks limited the scope of popular power. Seeing that the
					Soviets threatened the supremacy of the state, Lenin put a "new economic policy"
					into effect, destroying the Soviets, the trade unions and the cooperatives in
					order to further centralize the political state. The revolution, though, had
					been fought with a different objective—the negation of authority and centralism.
					Goldman blamed not only the Bolsheviks, but the "fanatical governmentalism" of
					marxism—and felt that only anarcho-syndicalism—"the industrial power of the
					masses expressed <pb n="74"
						facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2025-02/heresies02_074.jpg"
					/> through their libertarian associations"—could organize economic life. The
					power of the masses represented revolution to her: "The inherent tendency of the
					state is to concentrate, to narrow, and to monopolize all social activities; the
					nature of Revolution is, on the contrary, to grow, to broaden, and disseminate
					itself in even wider circles. In other words, the State is institutional and
					static, Revolution is fluent, dynamic.."<note>9. Ibid., p. 110.</note> Goldman
					also criticized the Russian Revolution for propagating anti-humanitarian
					feelings in its criticism of all ethics. The Bolsheviks saw the desire for
					justice, equality, and liberty as sentimental, bourgeois, superstitious and
					counter-revolutionary, this last a criticism especially leveled against
					outspoken women. All of history, she wrote, "is continuous proof of the maxim
					that to divest one's methods of ethical concepts means to sink into the depths
					of utter demoralization."<note>10. Ibid., p. 113.</note></p>
				<p>For Goldman, the primary ethical precept was the identity of means and ends. Like
					Kropotkin, she found ethics involved more than morals. How, in practice, could
					the dictatorship of the intelligentsia transform itself into the dictatorship of
					the proletariat? Wouldn't any class dictatorship be the same as any other? How
					could a revolution attempting to free the masses do away with all ethical
					concepts about why they should be free? This means-ends contradiction is
					important for feminists, preventing the advocation of revolutionary action where
					revolutionary method and end are not compatible.</p>
				<quote>They say that they foster disorder in all its forms. confusion troubles
					violent debates disarray upsets disturbances incoherences irregularities
					divergences complications disagreements discords clashes polemics discus sions
					contentions brawls disputes conflicts routs débâcles cataclysms disturbances
					quarrels agitation turbulence conflagrations chaos anarchy—Monique Wittig, Les
					Guérillères</quote>
				<p>It is interesting to compare Goldman's ideas with those of some of the leading
					female communists, for many of these women, no matter how allied their ideas
					were to an orthodox marxist line, tended to separate from their male compatriots
					and come closer to anarchism in their opposition to bureaucracy, to the
					subversion of revolution by the Bolsheviks, and to the use of purely efficacious
					means. Some of them resisted official policy so strongly that they were silenced
					by not receiving appointments, dismissals from posts or absurd "propaganda"
					missions to the hinterlands.</p>
				<p>It has often been pointed out both in criticism and support that Rosa Luxemburg's
					treatment of the nature of organization, her belief in the creative power and
					spontaneity of mass action and her advocation of the mass strike were replete
					with anarchist assumptions. Though she was, in fact, strongly opposed to
					anarchism in any form, in relation to Lenin's authoritarian political analysis,
					Luxemburg's refusal to support any rigid relationship of leadership to masses
					seems more sensitive to the complexities of struggle. While her goal was the
					same as Lenin's the destruction of capitalism by the working class—she believed
					in creative improvisation of leadership rather than in precisely planned
					strategies. She did, of course, believe in leadership, but considered good
					organization the product of action rather than its precedent and saw
					organization as growing out of struggle.</p>
				<p>While Luxemburg understood the necessity of centralism as a reaction against the
					"autonomy and isolation of the old organizational type, against localism and
						federalism,"<note>11. The quotations in this and the following paragraph are
						from Rosa Luxemburg: Selected Political Writings, ed. Robert Looker (New
						York: Grove Press, 1974), pp. 96, 99, 101, 102, 104.</note> the task was "to
					unite all workers and all worker organizations in a single party" despite
					national and religious differences. In the German Social Democratic Party, this
					was predicated upon the "direct, independent action of the masses," where the
					workers would "develop their own political activity through direct influence in
					public life." However, Luxemburg objected to Lenin's principles of centralism:
					"1. The blind subordination, in the smallest detail, of all party organs, to the
					party which alone thinks, guides, and decides for all. 2. The rigorous
					separation of the organized nucleus from its social-revolutionary surroundings.
					. . ." The German Social Democracy, she insisted, was not joined to the
					proletariat, it was the proletariat. The party was synonymous with the masses;
					it was to provide the "spirit of movement" to the masses. Luxemburg objected
					that the power of the Central Committee would be comprehensible only if it took
					the initiative of a "vast revolutionary act," paralleling Goldman's means-ends
					argument.</p>
				<p>Luxemburg saw the development of class consciousness as a product of the
					frictions between the party and trade union activity. Lenin, denying this
					dialectical function, saw trade union activity as a mere reflection of bourgeois
					consciousness in the working class. Through her belief that continued agitation
					was the only way to prevent the retardation of the struggle, Luxemburg supported
					the traditionally anarchist idea of the mass strike. "Spontaneity, as she used
					the term, meant action as opposed to static or reformist attitudes; it was
					misinterpreted by the Bolsheviks to mean confusion or to suggest that the
					party's rational policies should be determined by the "spontaneous" desires of
					the masses. "But what has been the experience of the Russian socialist movement
					up to now? The most important and most fruitful changes have not been the
					inventions of several leaders and even less so of any central organizational
					organs. They have always been the spontaneous product of the movement in
					ferment." The tactical policy of social democracy was not "invented" but was the
					"product of a series of great creative acts." Luxemburg argued that Lenin's was
					not a "positive and creative spirit," that he tried to "narrow the movement
					rather than to develop it, to bind it rather than to unify it....For us it is
					not the letter but the living spirit carried into the organization by the
					membership that decides the value of this or that organizational form." It is
					here that she seems closest to anarchism. She wanted to replace system not with
					another system, but with the opposite — movement and dynamism.</p>
				<p>Clara Zetkin, a close friend of Luxemburg, agreed with most of her ideas.
					However, Zetkin was a feminist, working for women's rights, editing a socialist
					women's paper, organizing biannual women's conferences in the German Social
					Democratic Party, the International Socialist Women's Conference, and
					International Women's Day. She felt that as long as there were sexist attitudes
					in the party, there was a need for separate women's organizations, meetings and
					groups for self-education and political agitation. She compared woman's relation
					to man to that of the worker to the capitalist (a favorite quotation was from
					Engels: "He is the bourgeois in the family, the woman represents the
						proletariat"<note>12. Peter Nettl, Rosa Luxemburg (New York: Oxford
						University Press, 1966), p. 415n.</note>), and she believed that economic
					independence through socially productive labor was the key to women's freedom.
					Because of this, she thought at first that the destruction of private property
					would free women by transforming the family from an entity bound by economic
					ties to a "moral entity" united by love, understanding, and respect."<note>13.
						There is very little available in English on Zetkin. Thus, a valuable essay
						is "Clara Zetkin: A Socialist Approach to the Problem of Women's Oppression"
						by Karen Honeycutt, Feminist Studies (Spring Summer, 1976), pp.
						131-144</note> But like Goldman, Zetkin later recognized the difference
					between the role of women's rights for bourgeois women and for working-class
					women. Middle-class women could focus on issues of personal liberation and more
					individual concerns, while working-class women, exploited as women and as
					workers, did not have that kind of leisure. Because she believed that biological
					as well as social factors created oppression, she concentrated, perhaps too
					heavily in later life, on motherhood as the primary defining characteristic and
					fulfillment of women. Because of her feminism, Zetkin was victimized by the
					party and excluded from important positions.</p>
				<pb n="77"/>
				<p> Angelica Balabanoff, active primarily in Italy, was like Kropotkin a Russian
					aristocrat who rejected family and back ground for communism. Compared with
					Luxemburg and Zetkin, she seems a bit simplistic, naive about the political
					machinations going on around her, but she was broad-minded and loyal to her
					sense of what was right. She too initially criticized anarchy because it lacked
					a basis in objective conditions, but she changed her mind upon meeting Emma
					Goldman, realizing that she had accepted without question the official charges
					against anarchist dissenters. Balabanoff's objections to the Bolsheviks were
					similar to Goldman's and Luxemburg's. In her autobiography, <title>My Life as a
						Rebel</title>, she wrote: "I have always believed that the emancipation of
					labor must be achieved primarily by awakening and educating the masses to a
					consciousness of their human and social rights, whereas the Bolsheviks have
					maintained that the transformation of the social system must be accomplished by
					a rela tively small minority."<note>14. The quotations of Balabanoff are from My
						Life as a Rebel (Blooming ton, Ind.: Indiana University Press,
					1973).</note></p>
				<p>Balabanoff not only opposed minority rule, but the cult of leadership, convinced
					that revolutionary work should be anonymous "in order to prevent the development
					of hero-worship and the undue influence of the individual upon the movement.
					Objecting to the idea of revolution imposed from above, she argued that method
					must come from the experience of the workers themselves, as an exploited class,
					if the revolution were to maintain itself against reaction. She despised the
					Bolshevik practice of exterminating the opposition —the "path of least
					resistance, advocating instead the discussion of conflicting methods and the
					confrontation of honest differences of opinion rather than discrediting or
					buying off opponents. When she made these objections, she was accused of being
					too "soft-hearted" to understand the necessities of the revolution — that is,
					too female and sensitive, which amounted to being "counter-revolutionary" and
					"bourgeois."</p>
				<p>Balabanoff's autobiography is informative on the subject of her comrade,
					Alexandra Kollantai, who led the first organized opposition to the policies of
					Lenin and Trotsky.</p>
				<quote>Alexandra was not an Old Bolshevik, but she had joined the Bolshevik Party
					even before Trotsky had done so and much earlier than I. During these first few
					years of the Revolution she was a frequent source of both per sonal and
					political annoyance to the Party leaders. On more than one occasion, the Central
					Committee had wanted me to substitute for her in the leadership of the women's
					movement, thus facilitating the campaign against her and isolating her from the
					women of the movement. Fortunately I understood this intrigue and refused these
					offers...By the Ninth Congress of the Russian Party, the last vestige of
					trade-union autonomy and workers' control in industry was swept away to be
					replaced by the control of the political commissars over the trade unions and
					the workers' soviets. Kollantai had become the leader of the "Workers'
					Opposition, a protest movement against the bureaucratic suffocation of the labor
					unions and the democratic rights of the workers. As there was no possibility,
					even at that time, of publicly criticizing the Central Committee or of placing
					an unofficial opinion before the Party rank and file, she was courageous enough
					to have a pamphlet secretly printed for distribution to the delegates of the
					Party I have never seen Lenin so angry, as when one of these pamphlets was
					handed to him at the Convention... Taking the platform, he denounced Kollantai
					as the Party's worst enemy, a menace to its unity...</quote>
				<p>Kollantai was accused of being an anarchist (a "syndicalist") because of her
					criticisms of the party for the absence of worker participation, its
					substitution of "specialists" for the working masses in decisions, its fear of
					criticism and freedom of thought. The Workers' Opposition, which demanded real
					participation of the workers in economic self-administration and the
					organization of production, was condemned by Lenin as "a petty bourgeois
					anarchist element hiding behind the back of the proletariat. Kollantai's view of
					revolution parallels that of Luxemburg and Goldman in its emphasis on
					spontaneity and creativity: "We can not decree Communism. It can be created only
					through active searching, through temporary setbacks but, at all events, through
					the creative force of the working class itself." <note>15. The quotations of
						Kollantai are from Autobiography of a Sexually Emancipated Communist Woman
						(New York: Schocken Books, 1971).</note></p>
				<p>Kollantai also extended her criticisms to the absence of equality for women,
					arguing that the party was not genuinely concerned with women's liberation in
					practice. Women "still lived under the same yoke: without authority in family
					life, enslaved by a thousand menial household tasks, bearing the whole burden of
					maternity...." When she went to Germany and joined the Social Democratic Party,
					she was influenced by Zetkin and took part in the International Conference of
					Socialist Women. In Russia, as Minister of Social Welfare after the revolution,
					she was interested in redefining not only political conditions but social and
					psychological attitudes concerning women; she worked for maternity welfare,
					prenatal care and day nurseries, as well as birth control, and strove to change
					ideas about sexuality and the structure of the family. Like Goldman, Kollantai
					distinguished the existing bourgeois women's liberation movement (which was not
					primarily concerned with creating a new social order) from the need for a
					working-class movement based on the <pb n="76"
						facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2025-02/heresies02_076.jpg"
					/> recognition of class contradiction. She was "accused" by the party of being a
					"feminist" for putting too much emphasis on matters concerning women. But even
					though she believed that women have special needs arising from their biology (a
					materialist argument), she criticized feminism for making only abstract demands
					for equal rights without any concrete material analysis of the situation for
					women at the time. This was her distinction between feminism and socialism,
					between the bourgeois and the working-class women's movements, which amounted to
					a distinction between liberalism and radicalism.</p>
				<p>Tension between Kollantai and the party became more and more severe. "Now began a
					(dark time) of my life which I cannot treat of here since the events are still
					too fresh in my mind ... (There were differences of opinion in the Party.) I
					resigned from my post as People's Commissar (on the ground of total disagreement
					with current policy)."<note>16. Ibid., p. 40. Parentheses indicate the passages
						Kollantai deleted from the published book, demonstrating her reluctance to
						reveal the con flicts between herself and the Party.</note> She was sent on
					a "diplomatic mission" to Oslo as ambassador—supposedly a prestigious assignment
					but intended to get her out of the way. After years of being suppressed, her
					spirit of resistance was broken and she stopped publicly criticizing the party
					and adopted the official line.</p>
				<quote>With the myth of the State out of the way, the real mutuality and reciprocity
					of society and individual became clear. Sacrifice might be demanded of the
					individual, but never compromise: for though only the society could give
					security and stability, only the individual, the person, had the power of moral
					choice—the power of change, the essential function of life.—Ursula LeGuin, The
					Dispossessed</quote>
				<p>The most extensive example of anarchism in practice occurred during the Spanish
					Civil War—a revolution that came closer to creating a stateless society on a
					large scale than any other. Aside from being a resistance to the fascist
					military take over, it was a social revolution by millions of workers and
					peasants trying to rebuild society in a libertarian way through collectives,
					self-management and changes in personal and social relationships, particularly
					in the status of women.</p>
				<p>Before the war, in the first years of the Second Republic (a coalition of
					bourgeois republicans and socialists formed after the collapse of the monarchy),
					some legislation had been passed to improve conditions for women: paid maternity
					leaves, time to nurse children during the work day, suffrage and the
					legalization of civil marriage and divorce. Anarchist women, however, did not
					organize to implement these legal changes or form separate women's organizations
					because they, like the men, wanted total social revolution rather than reform.
					Yet even with more liberal attitudes, sexism and patriarchy were not abolished.
					Women with jobs were still resented and received lower wages. Because a token
					number of well-educated women achieved good government positions, middle-class
					feminism subsided. The greatest militancy was among working-class women, who had
					the worst, lowest-paying jobs. <note>17. Little material on this period is
						translated into English. An important article, then, is by Lourdes Beneria:
						"Women's Participation in Paid Production under Capitalism: The Spanish
						Experience, Women and the Economy (Spring, 1976), pp. 18-33.</note></p>
				<p>The outbreak of the Civil War in 1936 brought vast changes, as a wartime economy
					inevitably does, because with the labor shortage, the need for women in
					factories and collectives increased, and because anarchist men and women agreed
					to fight for total social revolution. Feminism became an active political issue,
					and women felt the need to form separate organizations to work for their
					liberation. This was implemented by two major factors: formation of the women's
					group, Mujeres Libres (Free Women), and the activities of Federica Montseny, the
					only woman in Spain to hold a ministerial post.</p>
				<p>Mujeres Libres, formed in Madrid, published a journal by the same name; it
					consisted primarily of anarchist working- and middle-class women, both
					illiterate and well educated. They were joined by Barcelona's Centro de Cultura
					Feminina (Feminine Culture Group), also predominantly anarcho-syndicalist
					working and middle-class women."<note>18. An important source on Mujeres Libres
						is Temma Kaplan, "Spanish Anarchism and Women's Liberation," Journal of
						Contemporary His tory (Vol. VI, No. 2, 1971), pp. 100-110.</note> By 1938,
					Mujeres Libres and its affiliates had become a mass organization centered around
					demands for freedom from oppression by capitalism and sexism; for developing
					skills for meaningful rather than menial work; for equal wages; for access to
					social services. Many of these demands — for birth control, abortion, changes in
					the attitude toward prostitution —were influenced by Emma Goldman's essays,
					which appeared in Mujeres Libres. The organization developed into a
					decentralized federation of local, regional and national committees allied with
					various anarchist groups. While there were also rightist, leftist, and Catholic
					women's groups, they mostly concentrated on wartime services. Mujeres Libres
					also set up units for transport, sanitation, manufacturing, public services,
					communal kitchens and the organized collection of food, but mainly they strove
					for the feminist-anarchist transformation of economic, social and personal
					institutions. They set up day-care centers in factories and collectives and
					special technical schools so that new skills would give women the power and
					means for their own social liberation.</p>
				<p>Federica Montseny, under whose influence many of these aims became legal, was
					born in 1905 to anarchist parents, the publishers of the journal La Revista
						Blanca.<note>19. I have drawn a lot from the only source on Montseny I was
						able to find: an unpublished dissertation by Shirley F. Fredricks, "Social
						and Politi cal Thought of Federica Montseny, Spanish Anarchist 1923-1937'
						(University of New Mexico, March 1972). I am thankful to Lawrence Pitkethly
						for lending me the microfilm.</note> While close to the socialist tradition
					of Goldman, Kropotkin, Bakunin, and Proudhon, she was also influenced by the
					individualist anarchism of Stirner, Neitzsche and Ibsen, which stressed personal
					autonomy. While she approved the "egoism" of this position, Montseny rejected
					its often aristocratic tendency, arguing that the dialectical relationship
					between individual uniqueness and the anarchist's social commitment and
					responsibility prevented solipsism. Perhaps for a woman in patriarchal Spain, a
					more individualistic stance was necessary. In any case, it was the female
					anarchists Montseny and Goldman, who stressed the importance of the
					individualization of the masses and saw the prevailing concept of the masses as
					the annihilation of individuality and originality. Montseny's idea of revolution
					was that it had to be social, not political, internalized in each person and
					transforming all institutions; this would not be utopian because people have an
					unlimited potential for creating alternative social organizations.</p>
				<p>During the Second Republic, Montseny wrote essays criticizing the government and
					propagandizing for anarchism; she organized anarchist labor groups and helped
					Mujeres Libres set up day-care centers and technical schools for women. By 1936,
					when the anarchists joined the Popular Front government, she had become a
					popular leader, as well as the leading anarchist theoretician, and was appointed
					Minister of Health and Social Services. Although she was criticized for
					accepting the "reformist" position, and betraying anarchist principles, her
					decision was affected by her sense of responsibility to society, and especially
					to women. While she worked for change in many areas — education, prison reform,
					abolishing the death penalty —she was primarily committed to changing the status
					of women. Within the deeply embedded Spanish patriarchal tradition, she realized
					that anarchist revolution alone could help women only economically; social
					attitudes would have to change if women were to be secure and independent. While
					in office, she drafted a law legalizing abortion and argued for birth control
					and the legal reform of prostitution, which she considered a result of rigid
					sexual relations and women's lack of significant work. Yet, like Goldman and
					Kollantai, Montseny was not a "feminist," and criticized the aims of feminism as
					narrow and reformist: "To propagate feminism is to foment masculinism; is to
					create an immoral and absurd struggle between the two sexes which no Natural law
					would tolerate ... Feminism? Neverl Humanism? Always!"<note>20. Fredricks, p.
						131, from Montseny, "Feminismo y Humaniso, p. 14.</note></p>
				<p>Because political upheavals forced the anarchists out of government, Montseny
					held her ministerial post for only a year. After <pb n="77"
						facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2025-02/heresies02_077.jpg"
					/> the Civil War, the strong anti-feminism that emerged in the right wing
					government wiped out most of the women's gains.</p>
				<quote>I think men mostly have to learn to be anarchists. Women don't have to
					learn.—Ursula LeGuin, The Dispossessed</quote>
				<p>Why are women attracted to the most basic anarchist premises? Why do women tend
					to believe that the highest development of the individual, that which leads to
					the least oppression, takes place within collective forms; that change has to
					come from below; that any "human" society must be based on direct contact, the
					destruction of hierarchy and ethical behavior? Women have always distrusted
					leadership and, in fact, there have been no powerful and charismatic female
					leaders who influenced anarchism or feminism in the way that, say, Marx and
					Lenin influenced communism. Anarchist and feminist emphasis is on the quality of
					life, on the basic structures of community, family and education. Many anarchist
					attitudes are seen as culturally female — the emphasis on intuition, instinct,
					feeling and spontaneity, the distrust of logic as authoritarian and dominating.
					While anarchism has directed its argument against government, women have fought
					against patriarchy as such, private as well as public. It may be that this
					rebellion against all patriarchal institutions is what has led women into
					anarchist positions. Paralleling a retrograde anarchism that sees freedom only
					in liberation from industry (non-syndicalist anarchism) is that retrograde
					feminism that sees freedom only in liberation from men (separatism). As the
					Spanish experience of feminism shows, permanent liberation depends upon a total
					social structure. Sexism must be fought as an integral part of the class
					contradiction, for it cannot be explained without it, but it must always be
					recalled that feminism is only part of the primary focus on class contradiction.
					The history of the socialist struggle in Russia and China, of feminist
					anarchism, and even of the Weather Underground, shows how easily feminist
					demands, expectations and rights get lost in or exaggerated by male habits of
					dominance.</p>
				<p>Anarchist tendencies in feminism could come from two sources. The first is the
					concept that women are "naturally" more anarchistic because woman's "nature" is
					closer to the earth, to the anarchist idea of the "natural state." The second
					possibility is historical and cultural. Women have been excluded from full
					participation in government and industry, and have been confined to the smaller,
					more immediate contexts of family and community where harmony and cooperation
					are desirable and important. Because talk, gossip and expressing emotion were
					for so long the only expressions permitted women, direct contact in small groups
					seemed appropriate and necessary for the beginning of social transformation. But
					there have always been at least two women's movements. The middle-class
					movement, historically originating from the free time and the good education
					that permit women to rebel against the emptiness of their leisure and the
					absurdity of female roles, has been able to concentrate on issues of
					personality, personal freedom, structures of language and art, social
					interaction and individual response to conditions of oppression. More recently,
					middle-class women have been able to work in small groups in an attempt to build
					up mutual confidence. The work ing-class women's movement, on the other hand,
					has sometimes been invisible because it has been aligned with socialist
					struggles and unionism. For these women, oppressed by class as well as by
					sexism, feminism is not usually the primary strategy; they seek more immediate
					changes, tied to conditions in the working place, and often ignore their
					extension in the home. While their demands are often feminist —for equal pay,
					pay during maternity leave, day-care centers —these are sought within sexually
					integrated contexts. The task now seems to bring these two feminist movements
					together.</p>
				<p> Anarchism presents an unresolvable contradiction. How can it be achieved in a
					world where everything is leading toward greater centralization? As soon as
					anarchists begin to build practical systems, they are forced to approach a more
					centralized communism through the necessity for concentration of capital. But in
					spite of this contradiction, anarchism is important, particularly to women.
					Perhaps it can't be put into effect unless allied with another system
					(socialism, communism); perhaps it has to serve as a constant criticism of
					authoritarianism, bureaucracy, paternalism, protesting the erosion or
					obfuscation of liberty. Its role may be to serve as a moral reminder that social
					change is, and always should be, for people.</p>
				<p>There is a lesson in all of this: if in the entire history of women's struggles,
					we have been opposed to authoritarianism and hierarchy, it is masochistic and
					self-destructive to align feminism with party lines advocating what Goldman
					called "fanatical governmentalism." Marxism, for example, can also provide an
					economic analysis of the contradictions of capitalism, but there has to be, in
					addition, a movement toward direct democracy, self-management and freely
					associated workers —a feminist anarchist-socialism?</p>
				<p>Extracts are from: Monique Wittig, Les Guërillères, trans. Peter Owen (New York:
					Viking Press, 1971); Ursula LeGuin, The Dispossessed (New York: Harper and Row,
					1974). </p>
			</div>
		</body>
		<back>
			<p> Lizzie Borden, a filmmaker and writer, lives in New York. </p>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
