<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/LEAF-VRE/code_snippets/refs/heads/main/CSS/leaf.css" title="LEAF" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Ways of Change Reconsidered: An Aoutline and Commentary on Women and Peace in
					Northern Ireland</title>
				<author>Sarah Charlesworth</author>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Eowyn Andres</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Lyndon Beier</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
					<resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Mia DeRoco</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
					<resp>Editor, encoder (2021)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Zoha Nadeer</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Bri Perea</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Carrie Pirmann</persName>
					<resp>Editor, encoder (2023-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Valeria Riley</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Ricky Rodriguez</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
					<resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Valeria Riley</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Kelly Troop</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Lucy Wadswoth</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2022-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Anna Marie Wingard</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Olivia Wychock</persName>
					<resp>Graduate Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
				<funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
				<funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
				<funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>
					<name>Bucknell University</name>
					<address>
						<street>One Dent Drive</street>
						<settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
						<region>Pennsylvania</region>
						<postCode>17837</postCode>
					</address>
				</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial
						4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
					<licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title>Patterns of Communicating and Space Among Women</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and
								Politics</publisher>
							<pubPlace>
								<address>
									<name>Heresies</name>
									<postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
									<settlement>New York</settlement>
									<region>New York</region>
									<postCode>10013</postCode>
								</address>
							</pubPlace>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="78"
				facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2025-02/heresies02_078.jpg"/>
			<div>
				<head>Ways of Change Reconsidered: An Outline and Commentary on Women and Peace in
					Northern Ireland</head>
				<byline>Sarah Charlesworth</byline>
				<epigraph>
					<p> Compared to the devoted and laborious build-up that took place before all
						the other peace rallies that I have at tended in Belfast — the advertising,
						the canvassing, the care fully balanced composition of the platform party
						—here there was apparently no planning at all. No platform, no loudspeakers,
						no stewards, no prepared order of service. Just a vast throng of women,
						gathered at the spot where shortly before, the war between the terrorists
						and the army had cost the lives of three children.... One had a gnawing
						uneasiness that nothing more was going to happen.</p>
					<p>What did happen was a sudden burst of derisive yells and taunts from a band
						of youths defiantly brandishing the tricolour flag from a vantage point on
						the roof of a nearby garage. At that moment perhaps nothing could more
						effectively have rallied the rally." Suddenly it seemed we knew what we were
						there to do. From one to another the word threaded like quicksilver through
						the crowds: "We're going to walk down to the Falls." And walk we did —
						pushchairs and all — along the road that has become so notorious for
						violence and anger. Here and there spectators jeered and flaunted the
						slogans of hatred, but calmly and steadily the column of women — in the most
						casual fashion — walked on. As we walked, we talked. "They say," said the
						woman beside me, "that there's Protestants walking with us.""That's right,"
						said I... "Tm one of them." The response was immediate: hands shot out to
						grasp mine, heart-warming ejaculations of welcome fell on my ears. I felt
						simultaneously the reality of the division and the unity.<note>1. Margaret
							McNeil, "They Say That There's Protestants Walking With Us," <title
								level="j">The Friend</title> (London, Sept. 1976)</note>
					</p>
				</epigraph>
				<div>
					<head>Peace women hit Ulster streets despite threats</head>
					<p> BELFAST, Northern Ireland (AP)- The Peace Women of this turbulent British
						province take to the streets of violence-scarred Belfast Saturday, defying
						terrorist death threats in their campaign to end seven years of sectarian
						bloodshed.</p>
					<p>"There's no way we're going to give up now," declared Mrs. Betty Williams,
						the Roman Catholic housewife launched the burgeoning movement 10 days ago
						after three children were killed by Irish Republican Army gunmen fleeing
						British troops.</p>
					<p>Thousands of Catholic and Protestant women, setting aside the centuries-old
						hatreds that have separated Northern freland's feuding communities, were
						expected to gather for a rally in Ormeau park in Protestant East
						Belfast.</p>
					<p>The attendance at the rally will be a crucial test of the strength of the
						campaign, the latest in a long string of peace movements in Ulster. All the
						earlier campaigns fizzled out.</p>
					<p>Last Saturday, more than 10,000 women and a handful of men attended a peace
						rally organized by Mrs. Williams in Belfast's staunchly Catholic
						Andersonstown suburb at the spot where the three children were slain.</p>
					<p>Mrs. Williams, 32, and many other Catholic women at that rally were branded
						"touts terrorist parlance for informers and pro-British collaborators - by
						the IRA's "Provisional" wing.</p>
					<p>Young IRA supporters last week tried to burn Mrs. Williams' house down. She
						and other women received death threats from the mainly Catholic "provos" who
						are fighting to end British rule and Protestant domination in Ulster.</p>
					<p>Despite the threats, the peace movement has spread. Mrs. Williams said groups
						in other parts of the province have voiced support and local peace
						committees have sprung up in both Catholic and Protestant quarters.</p>
					<p>But the violence has continued unabated. At least six persons have been
						killed since the peace campaign began and dozens have been wounded by
						gunfire and bombings.</p>
					<p>Government officials, community leaders experienced observers who have seen
						earlier movements fail are still sceptical that Mrs. Williams campaign will
						change anything.</p>
					<p>"The sad truth is," said Catholic community leader Tom Conaty, a onetime
						adviser to the British administration in the province, "that the IRA and the
						Protestant paramilitary groups do not depend on popular support for their
						survival "They have shown this in the past and, despite courageous display
						by women, I believe they will be around for a long time."</p>
					<p>However, IRA sources said the guerrillas' leaders are taking the
						emotion-charged campaign "seriously." The provisionals have cracked up their
						well-oiled propaganda machine in a bid to counter the movement's growing
						support.</p>
					<p>The Republican news, the provisionals' mouthpiece in Ulster, Friday vowed:
						"the struggle goes on." The headline was printed over a big photo of a
						hooded gunman brandishing a U.S. made armalite automatic rifle.</p>
					<p>The Andersonstown news, a flourishing newssheet that has supported the
						provisionals in the past, stridently attacked the "peace-at-any-price
						brigade."</p>
					<p>Both papers published articles and letters denouncing the peace campaign as
						pro-British. However, Mrs. Williams stressed that her movement is not just
						opposed to the IRA, but Protestant terrorist organizations as well as Ulster
						police officers and British troops who "commit cowardly acts."</p>
					<p>Provisional sympathizers have organized a counter-demonstration in south
						Armagh, an IRA stronghold, at the spot where a 12-year-old Catholic girl was
						killed, apparently by army fire, last Saturday.<note>2. <title level="j"
								>Daily American</title> (Rome, Aug. 22, 1976).</note>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div>
					<head>1.</head>
					<p>In August 1976, there emerged in Belfast, Northern Ireland, apparently quite
						"spontaneously," a movement, which although it was later to be dubbed "The
						People for Peace" movement, was quite without a doubt a women's movement,
						initiated, supported and sustained primarily by women. From the perspective
						of classic political forms, it was and is both extremely traditional and
						profoundly radical, and it is particularly within the context o Irish
						politics that it becomes so.</p>
					<p>My initial interest in the peace movement grew out of a feel ing of
						solidarity and empathy with both the frustration and the positive vision
						these women revealed. As I followed its progress my interest began to turn
						increasingly to its larger political and social implications, not simply in
						relation to the situation of Northern Ireland, but also in regard to basic
						issues posed by feminism in relation to traditional patriarchal political
						analysis and practice. What became increasingly apparent as I continued my
						research was the fact that the peace movement could not be understood and
						evaluated either on the basis of the primary social-political traditions of
						Northern Ireland or from the perspective of an abstract marxist or feminist
						analysis. These model must themselves be continually measured against the
						social realities which they presume to appraise.</p>
					<p>The peace movement, to the extent to which it can be called a "women's
						movement," is interesting precisely because it is not in any sense
						"sophisticated." Its values and the forms of its organization are a direct
						manifestation of the attitudes of women <pb n="79"
							facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2025-02/heresies02_079.jpg"
						/> historically isolated from one another within a social structure over
						which they exercise minimal control. Within the context of American
						feminism, the questions posed by the peace movement are relevant to the
						extent to which they underline and elaborate some of the more complex issues
						pertaining to the gender bias inherent in the very "logic" of commonly
						accepted political norms. As Michelle Zimbalist Rosaldo points out:
							<quote>Since women must work within a social system that obscures their
							goals and interests, they are apt to develop ways of seeing, feeling,
							and acting that seem to be "intuitive" and "unsystematic"—with a
							sensitivity to other people that permits them to survive. They may,
							then, be "expressive." But it is important to realize that cultural
							stereotypes order the observer's own perceptions. It is because men
							enter the world of articulated social relations that they appear to us
							as intellectual, rational, or instrumental; and the fact that women are
							excluded from that world makes them seem to think and behave in another
								mode.<note>3. Michelle Zimbalist Rosaldo, <title level="m">Woman,
									Culture, and Society</title>, ed. Michelle Z. Rosaldo and Louise
								Lamphere (Stanford, Calif.: Stanford University Press,
							1974).</note></quote>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div>
					<head>2.</head>
					<p>The Province of Ulster was born in conflict. The partition of Ireland was a
						highly artificial solution to an age-old problem. The question of whether
						the current crisis is a religious war, a class war, or a war of national
						liberation is in many ways a false one. It is all of these at once. The
						peculiar complexity of the situation stems from the fact that the political
						and religious identity of each community is coincident in broad terms, and
						it is with these political and religious groups that individuals have from
						birth learned to define themselves.</p>
					<p>The sources of bigotry in Ireland as well as the mechanisms of its
						maintenance are ancient. In the Protestant community, patriotic songs and
						yearly festivals celebrate the siege of Londonderry and the assent of
						Protestant rule. These are matched in Catholic culture by a heritage which
						stresses the heroism and glory of national revolt as well as an almost
						mystical alliance with the church. According to the Irish Republican
						tradition to which the modern Provisionals are heir, "Ireland unfree shall
						never be at peace."</p>
					<p>The Catholic population in general has tended traditionally to identify with
						a united and independent Ireland and was in fact instrumental in winning
						support for the Home Rule Bill by which the Republic of Ireland was
						established in 1922. The Protestants, who form a minority within Ireland as
						a whole, had been success ful in their violent opposition to what they
						termed "the papist state," which led to Britain's partition of Ireland in an
						attempt to pacify loyalist Protestants in the North. The long-term and
						blatant suprematism of the Protestants concentrated in Northern Ireland,
						their overt domination of political and civil institutions, is countered by
						a Republican commitment to "victory through physical force" — a form of
						patriotism which finds its most extreme manifestation in the IRA tradition
						of blood sacrifice, in which each death only serves further to legitimize
						the unquestioned heroism and "justice" of the nationalist cause.</p>
					<p>With the outbreak of widespread and violent sectarian rioting in 1969, the
						collapse of the repressive Protestant-controlled Stormont Government was
						achieved only through the further intervention of the British, "justified"
						at the time by continuing paramilitary violence and the threat of civil war.
						This was to mark the beginning of a period of intense segregation and
						economic disintegration in Northern Ireland, during which a climate of
						hostility, combined with a complete lack of dialogue and a military
						standoff, has made the possibility of further political and social
						development virtually impossible.</p>
					<p>When the IRA split in 1969, the Official IRA (increasingly concerned with
						developing economic and class consciousness) apparently dwindled in
						effectiveness. The "Provisionals," on the other hand, with their more
						traditional focus on militarism and nationalism, were able to take advantage
						of the already tense political climate, playing into and further aggravating
						sectarian hostilities. They became self-appointed "people's protectors,"
						like the Protestant paramilitaries in their own districts. The British
						policy of internment and torture of IRA militants only served to further
						escalate guerrilla activities. The vicious circle was complete.</p>
					<p>During the last seven years, continued paramilitary and military violence
						have all but wrecked large sections of both the residential and commercial
						areas of Belfast, Derry and Armagh. Industry has declined and unemployment
						is soaring. Meanwhile, among the general population, apathy, fear,
						frustration and poverty have begun to flourish. Amid invariably righteous
						claims to the representation of "justice, hatred and despair have
						increasingly come to dominate "political" life in the Northern State.</p>
					<p>While numerous "brave and valiant" soldiers have lost their lives, countless
						ordinary citizens, often women and children, have also been the victims of
						this ancient and unending cycle of fear, recrimination and violence. The
						deaths of the three McGuire children, killed on August 10 by an IRA getaway
						car in Belfast's Andersontown district, were just another "accident." It
						was, however, to have a resounding effect. Betty Williams, an Andersontown
						resident who had witnessed the incident, and Mairead Corrigan, the
						children's aunt, "had had enough." Within hours they began organizing their
						neighbors to protest the senseless violence of a war which had long since
						become a way of life.</p>
				</div>
				<div>
					<head>3.</head>
					<p>The peace movement was from the start fueled by an emotional commitment which
						was not without its own particular rationality. To the skeptics who denied
						the possibility of a peaceful resolution to a feud stemming from deeply
						ingrained attitudes and opposing loyalties, the women replied that three
						hundred years of warfare had likewise accomplished nothing, that the
						Northern Irish people had been for too long divided against themselves.</p>
					<quote><p>Thank God I'm still angry enough to do this, because I'd march
							anywhere in Northern Ireland. I don't give a darn what the fellow's
							beliefs are. Everybody has got a right to believe in exactly what they
							want to believe in, but there is no one in this whole wide world has any
							right to kill for it. So, when l'd seen the children die or the awful
							accident—my daughter also witnessed this —she has screamed about it
							since, my five-year-old daughter who was unfortunately in the car with
							me at <pb n="80"
								facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2025-02/heresies02_080.jpg"
							/> the time—I went home and sat down. Did you ever get sick inside, so
							sick that you didn't even know what was wrong with you? I couldn't cook
							a dinner. I couldn't think straight. I couldn't even cry, and as the
							night went on I got angrier and angrier. And my sister came up. She
							lives quite close to where I live, and I had a cousin in the house at
							the time. And I just said—and I don't mean to swear, I'm very sorry—I
							said, "Damn it, we have got to do something." And my husband was at sea,
							and I an air-mail writing pad, and I went right up into the heart of
							provisional IRA territory in Andersontown and I didn't knock at that
							door very nicely, by the way, I didn't say, "Excuse me. Would you like
							to sign this? We all want peace." I was spitting angry, and I banged the
							woman's door and she came. I frightened the life out of her. I really
							did.</p>
						<p>When she came out, I said, "Do you want peace?" She said "Yes!"</p>
						<p>"Yes, then sign that." It sort of started off like that, and it went
							on...further down the street, every door you knocked. All the women felt
							that way. I just lifted the lid. They all poured out. I mean, I ended up
							rather like the Pied Piper of Hamlin because I had a hundred women in
							provie territory collecting signatures for peace.</p>
						<p>We had 3,000 or 6,000 signatures in three hours. We went back to my home.
							They were in the lounge. They were in the living room. They were in the
							kitchen. They were in the hall. They were lined up the stairs. They were
							in the bathroom, the two bedrooms. There just wasn't enough room to hold
							them all, and they were all just as angry as I was...that we had let
							this go on for so long.</p></quote>
					<cit>
						<ref>[Betty Williams<note>4. Betty Williams on <title level="s"
									>Woman</title> program, moderator Sandra Elkin (Buffalo: WNEDTV,
								Oct. 1976).</note>]</ref>
					</cit>
					<quote><p> You see, unfortunately, in a long time in Northern Irish society and,
							indeed, in the world we have glorified the man with the guns. Do you
							know we sit in our clubs and we sing about the brave man who took life?
							Now, we're going to say in Northern Ireland, we want a complete new
							change of society. The hero in Northern Ireland is going to be the guy
							who stands up against the man with a gun in his hand and said, "You're
							not speak ing for me. I haven't got a gun. l'm not prepared to take your
							life, but you're most certainly not speaking for me.</p>
						<p>The guy who gets involved with the man next door, with the old-age
							pensioner; the guy who recognizes the Protestant and the Shankhill to be
							his brother or the black man across the road to be his brother. The man,
							who, in society, acknowledges his brother. ..the man next door to be his
							brother. This is the kind of whole new society that we want to create in
							Northern Ireland, Indeed, we want to say that we have led the world in
							guerrilla warfare for years; we are going to lead the war in peace and
							we say to the people of the world, "Watch us." Because we are going to
							do it, and not only watch us but imitate us because the whole world is
							led by violence and it doesn't pay. One thousand six hundred people dead
							in Northern Ireland.</p>
						<p>My sister was lying in a hospital after losing three babies, and do you
							know her major concern? There was a bomb the previous week in a bar
							where a guy had gone out to have a drink—and he was lying across the
							ward from her—one of those open plan wards, and he had no legs,
							seventeen years of age—he had no legs and he kept squealing all day,
							"Please take my hands off. My hands hurt so much." That is only one
							awful incident of what's going on in Northern Ireland with guns coming
							into Northern Ireland. That's got to stop. That's no answer, but to the
							gunman we say, "We acknowledge that the gunman in Northern Ireland has
							taken guns perhaps because of their political ideals, perhaps because
							they were never offered a way, but there's a new way. There's another
							way, and we say to them, "Put up your guns, and if you really care for
							the people, come into society. Let's talk about it." We're not telling
							them to "get lost or go under the carpet because it'Il fester in thirty
							years, but let's talk about it. Let's hear what you are saying, but not
							by the gun.</p></quote>
					<cit>
						<ref>[Mairead Corrigan]</ref>
					</cit>
					<note>5. Mairead Corrigan on <title level="s">Woman</title> program (Buffalo:
						WNED TV, Oct. 1976).</note>

					<p> During the weeks that followed the initial demonstration at the site of the
						McGuire children's death, Betty Williams and Mairead Corrigan continued to
						publicize the incident and organize for an all-out assault on violence. This
						took the form of massive demonstrations for peace. The first demonstration
						(August 14)lic Andersontown district. Provo supporters jeered the rally and
						denounced Williams as a traitor, but she was not dissuaded and the following
						week brought 20,000 people together in one of Belfast's few remaining
						"mixed" neighborhoods. The third weekend the peace movement returned to the
						hard-core Protestant Shankill Road area where close to 30,000 demonstrators
						showed up. The fourth rally was held in Derry, Ulster's second largest city,
						on Craigavon Bridge, which connects the Protestant and Catholic sections of
						town. Again approximately 30,000 people turned out. By this time the Provos
						were saying that they did not oppose the peace movement, but supported
						"Peace with justice." Meanwhile, in Dublin, the capital of the Irish
						Republic, a march by 20,000 was organized in support and smaller marches
						were held in Corm, Galway, Carlon and Castlebar.</p>
					<p>The unexpected popularity and energetic style of these initial marches
						contributed to their dramatic impact. Both support and criticism abounded.
						Within weeks of the first rally, smaller community "peace" groups began to
						spring up throughout the province, with no apparent orientation other than a
						commitment to peace, to furthering dialogue within the community and to
						constructive non-sectarian local action.</p>
					<p>Provisional "support," however, was to prove short-lived. The weekly marches
						were disrupted on October 2 by small IRA counter-marches in which several of
						the peace marchers were assaulted. Death threats against Betty and Mairead
						were occasionally found scrawled on Belfast walls. The Provos, claiming that
						there had been an increase in British army raids, arrests and harassment,
						issued a statement warning that if any women from the peace movement
						cooperated with security forces, they would be treated as informers and
						shot.</p>

					<pb n="81"
						facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2025-02/heresies02_081.jpg"/>
					<p> From the onset there has been confusion in the press about the attitude of
						the peace marchers toward the British and the RUC (Royal Ulster Constabulary
						— the "legitimate" police who have been theoretically neutral but
						effectively on the side of the Protestants). While the peace leaders have
						been extremely outspoken in their criticism of the Provisionals and of the
						UDA and the UVF (Ulster Defense Association and Ulster Volunteer Force, the
						Protestant paramilitary equivalents of the Provisional IRA), they have been
						less direct in their denunciation of the British and of the legitimate"
						Ulster security forces. Though they have consistently condemned all "men of
						violence, their position on "legal" military forces is more ambiguous. While
						this is a crucial issue and one on which the peace leaders are perhaps most
						vulnerable to criticism, IRA supporters have consistently twisted its
						significance to imply that they are pro-British — unlikely, as the movement
						is both Catholic-led and strongly backed by non-violent Catholic
						Nationalists. There is in fact a simple and rational explanation for their
						hedging on the question of British intervention. Since one of the main
						thrusts of the movement is its anti-sectarian character, and since it is the
						first major popular grass roots movement uniting both Catholics and
						Protestants, its very existence is dependent on widespread support from both
						camps.</p>
					<p>The vast majority of Protestants (two-thirds of the population in Northern
						Ireland) for the most part do not favor British withdrawal, and many
						Catholics, including the Official IRA Sinn Fein <note>6. Sinn Fein (means
							"we ourselves"), founded in 1916, has functioned since the 1930s mainly
							as the political wing of the IRA. In the 1960s it swung to the left as
							did the IRA and became involved in social and economic agitation and in
							1970 split along the same lines as the IRA into Sinn Fein, Kevin Street
							(Provisional) and Sinn Fein, Gardiner Street (Official). The names come
							from the streets in Dublin where they have their headquarters. Both
							groups use the name Sinn Fein, however, in spite of the fact that their
							views are widely divergent. The Provisionals are more militant and
							nationalist while the Officials are marxist and not militant.</note> do
						not advocate an <emph>immediate</emph> withdrawal, so that any public
						position in regard to either imperialism or British "security" forces is
						indeed difficult and problematic. Due to this fact, as well as to the
						general diversity of political sentiment within the movement, the leaders
						have confined themselves to taking general positions against violence,
						encouraging local initiative toward peace and speaking in very broad terms
						about the need for the "Northern Irish" people to resolve their own
						differences "from the bottom up.</p>
					<p>Although heavy criticism from both the Provisionals and extremist Protestant
						groups may have slightly affected the movement's popularity, demonstrations,
						rallies and meetings throughout the fall of 1976 continued to draw wide
						support. Several supportive demonstrations were organized by feminist groups
						in Germany and the Netherlands; a rally in London on November 28 drew a
						crowd of approximately 15,000.</p>
					<p>The movement now has a magazine (<title level="j">Peace by Peace</title>), a
						small office in Belfast, and over 125 local groups "organizing for peace" in
						Northern Ireland. "Support," however, is not what the movement is all about.
						In terms of opening up effective channels of discourse and creating a
						climate in which constructive non-sectarian political development can occur,
						there is no way at present to estimate its success.</p>
				</div>
				<div>

					<head>4.</head>
					<p>The current peace movement is not the first of its kind in Ireland. Two
						others in the recent past have attempted to dispel sec tarian violence by
						non-violent and non-sectarian means. Both times they were eclipsed by
						British military escalations which rallied Catholics to the IRA. In 1971, an
						organization called "Women Together" gained considerable support, but lost
						ground when the British introduced internment. Another movement sprang up in
						Derry in 1972. After a British soldier had killed a Catholic youth, the IRA
						"executed" a young man from Derry who had joined the British army. That was
						the last straw for Margaret Doherty, who organized her neighbors to
						demonstrate their anger. This was effective to the extent that the Official
						IRA declared a cease-fire which they maintain to this day. The 1972 movement
						collapsed however, when the British invaded the Catholic no-go areas in what
						was known as "Operation Motor man." Once again the Provisionals were
						vindicated by British actions. With the rebirth of the peace forces this
						year, Margaret Doherty, who had been viciously harassed for her peace
						activities in 1972, again came forward and has participated in the
						organization of the present campaign.</p>
					<p>Even these recent interventions on the part of women are not unique in Irish
						history. In 1921, during the struggle for Home Rule, the British section of
						the Women's International League for Peace and Freedom, headed by Jane
						Addams, sent their own commission to study Irish self-rule, clearly opposing
						the interests of their own government. The Irish section of the WILPF, led
						by Louie Bennett, was active in organizing women to employ
						passive-resistance techniques in a struggle against the British. Their view
						as women was that human life was precious and that war was an outmoded way
						of dealing with imperialist rivalries. While the women supporters of the
						1921 struggle were largely middle-class suffragettes organized
						internationally behind a pacifist ideology, the current peace campaign is
						indigenous, widely supported by both middle- and working-class people, and
						relatively "unorganized."</p>
					<p>The peace movement, as Bernadette Devlin has pointed out, is not a feminist
						movement. There is in fact virtually no feminism in Ireland in the sense in
						which we as Americans understand it. While there have been several notable
						female political activists in the Republican movement (Bernadette Devlin,
						now associated with the Irish Republican Socialist Party, Marin de Burca,
						joint general secretary of Sinn Fein, and Maire Drumm, the recently
						assassinated Provisional IRA spokeswoman), the vast majority of Irish women,
						oppressed as they are by poverty, war, extremely discriminatory employment
						and pay practices, and perhaps most importantly, by a strong religious and
						patriarchal family structure, have, by and large, remained unorganized as
						women.</p>
					<p>For Catholic women, a very intense religious indoctrination which places a
						strict taboo on birth control, abortion and divorce is still a major
						obstacle. While as citizens of a Commonwealth nation, Northern Irish women
						are technically entitled to equal pay, and according to an
						anti-discrimination law passed at Westminster in December 1976, they are
						protected against job discrimination, the fact is that women's employment
						opportunities lag far behind not only those of men, but behind those of most
						European women as well. While the legal status of Ulster women is superior
						to that of women in the Catholic Republic of Ireland where women still have
						almost no independent legal rights, a very strong patriarchal ideology still
						prevails throughout Ireland, and Northern Irish women are for the most part
						still politically subservient to their husbands as well as being
						educationally and economically disadvantaged. While these conditions can
						ultimately be traced to the relatively low level of industrial and economic
						development of Ireland as a whole, and to the powerful religious
						infrastructure, they do underline some of the reasons why feminism has
						failed to develop, as well as the crucial importance of independent women's
						organizations.</p>
					<p>How then can we evaluate the effectiveness of the peace movement from a
						feminist perspective? While its prevailing attitudes are traditional, in
						that they are not activist from a feminist or socialist perspective, the
						movement does potentially represent an important step forward in both of
						these directions. The self-initiated emergence into the political sphere of
						a large sector of the female population which has heretofore remained
						inactive, or at best has existed in an exclusively supportive role in
						relation to those very male modes of political activity which they are now
						so explicitly criticizing, is not without significance to the development of
						either.</p>
					<pb n="82"
						facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2025-02/heresies02_082.jpg"/>
					<quote><p> The rallies do help to get rid of a certain amount of fear. You are
							going to such-and-such a place and at one time you would have been
							frightened to go there. But at the rally you're a bit frightened but you
							just go on. Each time you come back from a rally, you have more courage
							to keep going. It's because you're meeting with people.</p>
						<p>Let's face it, for seven years we went about the city and sat in our
							homes, all the time wrapped up in our own family and our own home and
							our own constant worry that something would happen to them. You felt it
							was just yourself had all this worry. Going out to the rallies is making
							people realize that other people have the same fears and the same
							worries. We are able to talk to each other about it. It's bringing a new
							closeness.</p></quote>
					<cit>
						<ref>[June Campion, member of a local peace group in Knoknagoney]</ref>
					</cit>
					<note>7. June Campion, quoted in <title level="m">Peace by Peace</title>
						(Belfast, Oct. 16, 1976).</note>
				</div>
				<div>

					<head>5.</head>
					<p>It is also important to remember that the current peace movement is at
						present not a political organization; it is perhaps misleading to consider
						it as such. While plans for the future include meetings designed to develop
						a more explicit form of organization, the movement as yet has no formal
						structure and no official platform. It is a phenomenon that can accurately
						be termed "spontaneous" in that it has not been planned and the form it has
						taken to date can be regarded primarily as a demonstration of solidarity
						around a commitment to peace.</p>
					<p>The three most visible leaders at present are Betty Williams, Mairead
						Corrigan and Ciaran McKeown, a journalist who has given up his newspaper
						position to support the women in their struggle. The organizational network
						as a whole, however, is neither centralized nor highly controlled by those
						who are apparently most prominent. Indeed, there has been a consistent
						effort by all concerned to systematically locate the basis for participation
						and direction within the numerous communities where peace groups have been
						emerging.</p>
					<p>While direct support for the movement is clearly widespread (estimates range
						from 170,000 to 250,000 people in Northern Ireland alone), it is extremely
						hard to gauge its size or class composition on the basis of mass rallies and
						demonstrations. When I criticized the somewhat naive character of some of
						the statements by movement leaders, an American woman who had gone to
						Northern Ireland to participate in one of their rallies told me that it was
						precisely this tone that contributed to the movement's popularity among
						working-class women. It is certainly true that there has been a very
						deliberate attempt by the peace people to avoid direct affiliation with any
						specific political groups, and certain of the more politically
						"sophisticated" women supporters have deliberately remained in the
						background, not wishing to "take over' or divert the movement from its
						primary focus, that is, bringing an end to violence and encouraging local
						initiative toward non-sectarian community development.</p>
					<p>Marin de Burca, a socialist and leader of Sinn Fein (Official IRA) spoke of
						the peace movement in an interview during a recent tour of the U.S.: "We go
						to the marches as individuals. It would be the kiss of death if we openly
						supported them. We have issued statements supporting them, but I don't agree
						with trying to move in and take them over."</p>
					<note>8. Marin de Burca, quoted by David Moberg, <title level="m">In These
							Times</title> (Jan. 1977).</note>
					<p>De Burca believes that if the British withdrew the Provos would be
						politically undermined. She argues that unification of the country is still
						the solution but that it can be achieved only through unification of the
						various factions around initially modest reforms.</p>
					<quote><p>The demand for peace is not Marxist, but in the context of Northern
							Ireland it is very revolutionary at the mo ment... The reason we're
							looking for peace is to allow us to operate openly and intensively in a
							political way to unite Protestants and Catholics. If we have to look for
							something that sounds as reactionary as peace, then we look for it. If
							people can't see behind the facade to the reality then it's their
							problem.</p></quote>
					<note>9. Ibid.</note>
					<p>When Marin de Burca speaks of working in a political way to unite Catholics
						and Protestants, she is speaking as a marxist attempting to organize working
						people to assume greater economic control. While, as a member of the
						Official IRA, de Burca definitely supports an anti-imperialist struggle, she
						feels that in the long run the sectarian disputes dividing the Catholic and
						Protestant working populations are perhaps an even greater obstacle to the
						struggle for self-determination. As the situation exists now, separate
						Catholic and Protestant labor unions render the labor movement as a whole
						relatively ineffectual, and continued economic disintegration due to
						sectarian violence has left large sections of the Catholic and Protestant
						population unemployed.</p>
					<p>It is interesting to note the difference between de Burca's marxist analysis,
						which views the entire Irish working class as the oppressed class and the
						type of marxist analysis supported by other Republicans, which views the
						Catholic minority in the North as the oppressed class. The Provisionals, who
						are not necessarily socialists but prefer to think of themselves as
						consistently on the left, persist in opposing both the British and the
						Protestant paramilitary and are engaged in a constant struggle for
						unification with the Catholic South. Bernadette Devlin, a socialist and an
						aggressive Republican, generally supports this form of analysis where
						class—purely in economic terms—is secondary to anti-imperialism and a class
						analysis stressing the political and economic discrimination that the
						Catholic population as a whole has suffered at the hands of a
						Protestant-controlled government and industry.</p>
					<p>The complexity of the situation and the relative inadequacy of this approach
						is apparent when one considers, even in crude terms, the economic
						composition of the Catholic and Protestant population. While it is
						definitely true that the Protestant majority, as a group, has greater
						economic control, and that the highest levels of unemployment in the North
						are in Catholic districts, the large majority of the Protestant population
						is also working class. It is, in fact, the youths of these two communities
						who are fighting one another, while the small minority of Protestants who
						are wealthy maintain an economic advantage and have an interest in
						continuing sectarian hostilities for precisely this reason.</p>
				</div>
				<div>
					<head>6.</head>
					<p>It would be a mistake, however, to attempt to evaluate the significance of
						the peace movement on the basis of its potential effectiveness in furthering
						the cause of other political movements. It is perhaps more useful to
						consider the way in which the peace movement is indicative of an entirely
						different struggle for self-determination, as well as a profoundly different
						approach to these issues. It is significant that what is being questioned by
						the peace people is not the ends of political struggle so much as the means
						by which ideas, opinions and interests are both culturally reinforced and
						socially imposed.</p>
					<p>The critical issue which is the historical source of internal Irish conflict
						is that of the relationship between Ireland and the British Empire. This has
						not only kept Catholics and Protestants feuding for generations, but has
						also led to innumerable splits within both camps. It is paradoxical that
						within this context British imperialism is the one issue on which the peace
						campaign has most consistently refused to take a stand. This is not because
						individual participants have no opinions on this question, but rather
						because the movement locates the "solution" in people, in a process of
						interaction and definition rather than in abstract "positions." </p>
					<pb n="83"
						facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2025-02/heresies02_083.jpg"/>
					<p> For the peace people, the question of the relative legitimacy of opposing
						traditions is momentarily suspended. What is revealed instead is the logical
						perfection of institutionalized conflict. Military, political and even
						religious leaders are themselves to blame, claim the peace organizers, not
						because of this or that 'position" in relation to government, but because
						they have kept the Irish people divided among themselves. "Rationality" is
						for them not merely a question of "right" and "wrong," but rather begins
						with the realization of how two non-dialectical visions of "right" are
						sustained by a culture which is imperialist and authoritarian in its very
						mode of thought.</p>
					<p>Problems arise, claim the peace workers, because we have "lost sight of a
						basic respect for the individual." "Solutions," they assert, cannot be
						artificially constructed and then imposed but must arise through a process
						of creative interaction in which government does not exist to control
						people, to violently suppress dissent, but rather as an extension of the
						more or less clearly articulated needs and desires of <emph>all</emph> the
						people.</p>
					<p>These concepts, while they may reveal an element of political naiveté which
						translates as liberalism, are not rhetorical. The practical orientation of
						the movement to date, with its emphasis on open and careful discussion and a
						decentralized approach to developing democratic forms, is indicative of this
						fact.</p>
					<p>From this perspective we might examine Bernadette Devlin's claim that the
						peace movement is "dangerous" because it "dulls consciousness." "We were
						stupid," she claims, "never to have organized the women." <note>10.
							Bernadette Devlin, quoted by Lucinda Franks, "We Want Peace, Just
							Peace," <title level="j">New York Times Magazine</title> (Dec. 19,
							1975).</note> Both the truth and the potential fallacy of this statement
						are apparent. From the standpoint of almost any traditional political
						perspective, assertions of the sanctity of life, of respect for the
						individual and of a genuine "creative form of democracy" must appear naive
						without a "program" or a definition of the specific conditions under which
						such values can be realized. The peace people, however, do not qualify these
						conditions; the values themselves must define the very process of political
						interaction. If this is the case, how then can we interpret Bernadette's
						regret at not having "organized" the women? Is it conceivable that the women
						supporting the peace movement are not in fact organizing themselves,
						organizing in such a way as to deny the legitimacy of those very political
						forms into which others seek to recruit them?</p>
					<p>A supportive statement by the Provisionals, in which the peace movement is
						described as a "spontaneous overreaction led by the photogenic Mrs. Betty
						Williams" reveals both the condescension and lack of reflexivity which
						typify those attitudes the women are most directly challenging.</p>
					<quote>We are not necessarily in opposition to the peace people. But we want to
						explain to the people that there cannot be peace without justice. We just
						want to explain to the people turning out to these marches what the
							<emph>true position</emph> is and show them the road to real
						peace.</quote>
					<note>11. Irish Republican Information Service (Dublin, Oct. 14, 1976). Italics
						the author's.</note>
					<p>This raises the most subtle and yet critical issue of the peace movement's
						significance. The whole notion of a "true position" is what the peace
						movement calls into question—it is not the political views of the opposing
						factions that are being attacked; even the "violence" the movement condemns
						is but a manifestation of something far more profoundly significant. The
						peace people are, in my opinion, not reacting simply to a specific incident
						of violence, nor even to violence in the abstract. They are (perhaps naively
						but nevertheless insightfully) challenging a whole tradition. What is
						fundamentally being questioned is the legitimacy of the imposition of the
						will of one group upon another. "Justice" is not being challenged so much as
						how justice is socially defined. imperialism, in this context, is not simply
						a question of national or international conquest. Imperialism is the
						imposition of a social order, whether through military force or political
						manipulation, by those with power on those without. The very question of how
						Northern Ireland can be governed, says Ciaran McKeown, "is an imperialist
						question" because it implies the imposition of political forms by
						politicians on people who are for the most part excluded from the process of
						a creative democracy. Thus all extant political solutions are inevitably
						violent, whether the violence is "legal"<note>12. Ciaran McKeown, "The Price
							of Peace" (Belfast, 1976).</note> or "illegal," because they require
						military force to secure them.</p>
					<p>From this perspective, British colonialism, Protestant political suprematism
						and IRA military violence can be seen as identical in their implicit
						attitudes toward the imposition of social order. In every case, whether
						justified or not, "justice" is an extension of self-interest and democracy
						is a rhetorical, not a methodo logical phenomenon. While it would be absurd
						to consider the peace movement as a feminist or a socialist movement, it
						expresses values that are fundamentally in accordance with both socialist
						and feminist thought, in that it addresses the whole issue of power and
						questions the way the right of self-determination has been eclipsed, not
						only by those in power, but by those who conceive of power alone—economic,
						military or political—as the just determinant of social order.</p>
					<quote>Perhaps it's been our fault, you see, because we have sat back—as
						ordinary people—which is the fault everywhere—where the ordinary people sat
						back and let a few extremists say, "We are speaking and we are working for
						the people." We should have long ago stood up and said, "They're not
						speaking for us." I mean, people have been coming out from Ireland
						representing the people—the ordinary people, perhaps people like our selves,
						who never had the nerve. I mean, just to be here takes all the courage one
						has got, you know.</quote>
					<cit>
						<ref>[Mairead Corrigan]</ref>
					</cit>
					<note>13. Mairead Corrigan on <title level="s">Woman</title> program (Buffalo:
						WNED TV, Oct. 1976).</note>
				</div>
			</div>
		</body>
		<back>
			<p> Sarah Charlesworth is an artist and photographer who lives and works in New York.
				Her previously published writings have dealt with art and social theory. She was a
				founding editor of The Fox and is a member of the anti-catalog collective. </p>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
