<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/LEAF-VRE/code_snippets/refs/heads/main/CSS/leaf.css" title="LEAF" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Skyscraper Seduction, Skyscraper Rape</title>
				<author>Dolores Hayden</author>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Eowyn Andres</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Lyndon Beier</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
					<resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Mia DeRoco</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
					<resp>Editor, encoder (2021)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Zoha Nadeer</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Bri Perea</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Carrie Pirmann</persName>
					<resp>Editor, encoder (2023-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Valeria Riley</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Ricky Rodriguez</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
					<resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Valeria Riley</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Kelly Troop</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Lucy Wadswoth</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2022-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Anna Marie Wingard</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Olivia Wychock</persName>
					<resp>Graduate Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
				<funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
				<funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
				<funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>
					<name>Bucknell University</name>
					<address>
						<street>One Dent Drive</street>
						<settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
						<region>Pennsylvania</region>
						<postCode>17837</postCode>
					</address>
				</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial
						4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
					<licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title>Patterns of Communicating and Space Among Women</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and
								Politics</publisher>
							<pubPlace>
								<address>
									<name>Heresies</name>
									<postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
									<settlement>New York</settlement>
									<region>New York</region>
									<postCode>10013</postCode>
								</address>
							</pubPlace>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb/>
			<div type="essay">
				<pb n="108"
					facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2025-02/heresies02_108.jpg"/>

				<head>Skyscraper Seduction Skyscraper Rape</head>
				<byline>Dolores Hayden</byline>
				<epigraph>
					<p>Once you learn to look upon architecture not merely as an art, more or less
						well, more or less badly, done, but as a social manifestation, the critical
						eye becomes clairvoyant, and obscure and unnoted phenomena become
						illuminated.</p>
				</epigraph>
				<cit>
					<ref>—Louis Sullivan, Kindergarten Chats, 1901</ref>
				</cit>
				<div>
					<p> The skyline of Manhattan tells the dynamic story of the growth of American
						capitalism in the past century; we see a few lively Gothic and Art Deco
						towers marked with the names of individual tycoons, then many bland
						International-style office towers built by industrial corporations, real
						estate developers, and the government; and finally, a limited number of
						super towers, remote and anonymous, like the multi-national corporations or
						multi-jurisdictional bureaucracies which inhabit them. A complex national
						symbol, the American skyscraper has been associated with military force and
						corporate expansion during various phases of American economic and urban
						growth. In popular culture, skyscrapers have also symbolized personal social
						mobility and personal sexuality for those who commission, design, or use
						these buildings. In the history of world architecture, the skyscraper ranks
						as America's most distinctive technical innovation; in the history of human
						settlements, the skyscraper dominated city is America's legacy to the world.
						For a century most American architectural historians have busily
						rationalized the aesthetic, functional, and social distress the skyscraper
						creates, nurturing the prevalent belief that the skyscraper is a glorious
						triumph of engineering, a natural part of urban life, and an inevitable
						result of urban concentration.</p>
					<note>1. For an aesthetic justification, see Louis Sullivan, "The Tall Office
						Building Artistically Considered,"" in <title>Kindergarden Chats and Other
							Writings</title> (New York: Wittenborn, 1947). For an aesthetic analysis
						focusing on analogies with classical columns, see Winston Weisman, "A New
						View of Skyscraper History," in Edgar Kauffman, ed., <title>The Rise of an
							American Architecture</title> (New York: Praeger, 1970). Diana Agrest,
						in "Le Ciel est la limite," adds to this with a discussion about towers
						reaching into outer space, <title>L'Architecture d'aujourd'hui</title>
						(sky-scraper issue) (March-April 1975), pp. 55-64. Cass Gilbert, in his
						intro duction to Skyscrapers of New York by Vernon Howe Bailey (New York:
						Rudge, 1928), goes on about "Mt. Woolworth" and the "Singer-horn," viewing
						skyscrapers as mountains and cliffs created in the city. Many other
						architects take up this last image, Hugh Ferriss and Raymond Hood being
						notable examples. Manfredo Tafuri has criticized it in the
							<title>L'Architecture d'aujourd'hui</title> issue. A brief article which
						provides welcome relief from the usual romanticization is by Elizabeth
						Lindquist Cock and Estelle Jussim, "Machismo in American Architecture,"
							<title>Feminist Art Journal</title> (Spring 1974), pp. 8-10, but the
						authors conclude, "...at what cost these expressions of machistic corporate
						power? ... Perhaps it is time to in sist that women be given the chance to
						design our buildings." This suggestion bypasses the economic demand for
						skyscrapers rather naively, assuming that female architects employed by
						large corporations would actually be in a position to create real
						alternatives. Gertrude Kerbis, Chicago architect, makes a more realistic
						assessment of the small changes possible when she states that men have
						designed high-rises as sexual symbols and that if she got a chance to design
						a skyscraper, it would have some air spaces for wind to pass through. On
						Kerbis, see Donna Joy Newman, "High-rise-ing Women, Making a Mark on the
						Skyline," <title>Chicago Tribune</title> (August 8, 1976), Sec. 5, p.
						7.</note>
					<p>While the skyscraper is a cultural artifact reflecting the economic
						developments of the past century, it is also a building type designed to
						affect both economic activity and social relations. As a result, a fuller
						history of the skyscraper reveals a century of struggles and protests
						against the tendency to build ever higher. The builders' fantasies alternate
						with grim reality. Each new argument in favor of the skyscraper may
						incorporate some response to previous urban protests against it. Yet there
						is no escape from the contradictions of the capitalist city; as an
						instrument for enhancing land values and corporate eminence, the sky scraper
						consumes human lives, lays waste to human settlements, and ultimately
						overpowers the urban economic activities which provided its original
						justification.</p>
					<p>Perhaps the metaphor of rape suggested by the strongly phallic form of the
						skyscraper can illuminate the process by which American urban residents and
						workers have, at times, resigned themselves to this oppressive architectural
						form. In our literature, as in our judicial system, rape has often been
						presented as seduction. The aggressor "couldn't help himself," we are told,
						or the victim "really wanted it." The skyscraper is justified by builders
						with the same rhetoric: developers "can't help themselves," or the city
						"really wants it," despite the economic and social anguish it brings. A
						brief review of skyscraper history illuminates a painful dialectical process
						with alternating themes of reality and fantasy, rape and seduction. </p>
				</div>
				<div>
					<head>First Fantasy: "Manifest Destiny"</head>
					<p>The earliest tall structures in the United States, monumental military
						obelisks and columns like the Bunker Hill Battle Monument (completed in
						1843), provided symbolic as well as technological precedents for skyscraper
						construction. These monuments usually included observatories which became
						popular spots for surveying the surrounding urban and rural landscape. Such
						grand vistas were associated with the cry for westward expansion or
						"manifest destiny" accepted by many patriotic Americans as a political goal
						during the mid-nineteenth century. John Zukowsky has described the
						experience of the ascending observers, ...afforded seemingly endless
						panoramic views, and visual participation in those expansionist concepts
						without facing the dangers, hardships, and expense of physical relocation
						west." He adds that "the military connotations inherent in those monuments
						reminded all that this westward expansion would be protected, and policies
						of Manifest Destiny upheld through force if necessary."</p>
					<note>2. John Zukowsky, "Monumental American Obelisks—Centennial Vistas,"
						unpublished paper (1975).</note>
					<p>The symbolic imagery of military monuments was first transformed into a
						vision of the American city by Erastus Salisbury Field, an itinerant painter
						from westem Massachusetts. His Historical Monument of the American Republic
						combined in one large canvas ten columns which implied "visual participation
						in expansionist concepts, as well as militarism appropriate to the 1876
						centennial celebration of American independence. He composed these columns,
						usually seen as isolated monuments, into a spectacular urban design with an
						elevated railway linking the observatories at their tops. During the
						following decade, the American city began to evolve dramatically in the
						direction Field had whimsically imagined.</p>
					<p>In the 1850s, 1860s and early 1870s, the elevator and the cast iron frame
						boosted the size of commercial buildings, which still tried to conceal their
						height under gawky mansard roof lines; in the 1880s and 1890s, such
						traditional roof lines were abandoned in favor of competition for height,
						and steel-framed towers began to fill the business districts of New York and
						Chicago. Some of these tall buildings included observatories similar to
						those atop the traditional monuments, so visitors to skyscrapers could also
						have panoramic views. Private offices, conference rooms, and clubs were also
						located at the tops of the towers, from which executives could overlook the
						cities their enterprises dominated. Just as the centennial obelisks and
						columns had been decorated with statues of heroes, so the new skyscrapers
						often bore the names of tycoons, and, sometimes, their statues looming
						against the sky, proclaiming not the patriotic warriors' slogan, "manifest
						destiny," but the corporate imperative, "survival of the fittest." </p>
				</div>
				<pb n="109"
					facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2025-02/heresies02_109.jpg"/>
				<div>
					<head>Reality: Workers' Funerals</head>
					<p>The social Darwinist motto, "survival of the fittest," was an accurate
						description of the skyscraper construction process. At the turn of the
						century, competition for height and eagerness to realize a return on
						investments led builders to encourage architects and engineers to strain the
						limits of existing technology with each new tower. "Survival of the fittest"
						in the builders' world of financial speculation thus became the excuse for
						casual attitudes toward safety conditions for construction workers. One
						British reporter lugubriously observed public reactions to the deaths of
						workers on the Woolworth Building, constructed between 1911 and 1913:
						"Anybody in America will tell you without tremor (but with pride) that each
						story of a skyscraper means a life sacrificed. Twenty stories—twenty men
						snuffed out; thirty stories thirty men. A building of some sixty stories is
						now going up sixty corpses, sixty funerals, sixty domestic hearths to be
						slowly rearranged." <note>3. Arnold Bennett, "Your United States," quoted in
							Harlan Paul Douglas, <title level="m">The Suburban Trend</title> (New
							York: Century Co., 1925), p. 305.</note> By 1930, Fortune magazine
						claimed that this estimate was no longer correct, commenting, "In general,
						deaths run from three to eight on sizable buildings," but conceded that "a
						bloodless building is still a marvel."</p>
					<note>4. "Skyscrapers: Builders and Their Tools," in <title level="m">The
							Skyscraper</title>, reprinted from <title level="j">Fortune</title>
						magazine (New York: American Institute of Steel Construction, 1930), p.
						29.</note>
					<p>Ironworkers (who erect structural steel) endure the greatest risks. Often
						builders and journalists use the language of militaristic, romanticized
						machismo to describe the "raw danger" of a "daredevil" ironworker's job, and
						the Stars and Stripes is always unfurled whenever a building is topped out
						suggesting a patriotic conquest. Yet ironworkers themselves may feel
						fearful, since Mike Cherry reports in his autobiography, <title level="m">On
							High Steel</title>, that one out of fifteen dies within ten years of
						entering this risky trade. <note>5. Mike Cherry, <title level="m">On High
								Steel: The Education of an Ironworker</title> (New York: Ballantine
							Books, 1975), p. 27.</note> Cherry recounts his gut reaction to a look
						at the New York skyline: "the anxiety that I'd thought I'd conquered came
						running back at me all over again. ..The city had never struck me as so tall
						before.. .I drove past several buildings that were nearing completion, twice
						pulling over to the curb to stare at them, developing a slight case of the
						shakes."</p>
					<note>6. Ibid., p. 169.</note>
					<p>Theodore James, author of a recent history of the Empire State Building,
						constructed between 1929 and 1931, recalls the days when ironworkers were
						called by the condescending, romantic nickname, "sky-boys," (perhaps
						relating them to military air heroes called fly-boys), yet he passes lightly
						over the fourteen fatalities and numerous injuries that occurred during the
						building process. <note>7. Theodore James, Jr., <title level="m">The Empire
								State Building</title> (New York: Harper and Row, 1975), p. 68. In
							contrast to many American projects, the Eiffel Tower, a tall and complex
							engineering project, was built in Paris in 1889 without a single
							fatality; the effort and resources expended on safety equipment matched
							the desire for spectacular height.</note> Cherry has a grimmer view of
						the trade in New York in those years, claiming that foremen could insist on
						work in hazardous wet weather, or cut off a man's pay at the moment of an
						accident. He states that during the Depression "gangs of out-of-work
						ironworkers hung about on the streets around job sites, so that when a man
						fell, they would be instantly available to take his place." <note>8. Cherry,
							pp. 26-27.</note> In the 1930s, the best workers in each building trade,
						alive and walking at the end of a skyscraper job, were awarded Certificates
						of Superior Craftsmanship" and gold buttons for their skill by a building
						contractors' association, but both union and insurance company safety
						campaigns got nowhere because of the developers' pressure to build
						quickly.</p>
					<note>9. Fortune, p. 29.</note>
					<p>Today, construction workers' unions are stronger. No one has to work in the
						rain, and a fallen worker (or his widow) at least gets paid for a full day's
						work. Still the grim process of building a skyscraper continues to take its
						toll of lives, as Cherry described a death on a New York job in 1972:
						"Somehow, Timmy, in hurrying from one side of the bay to the other, managed
						to put his inside foot down an inch to the right of where he should have,
						and the plank, which had a slight warp in it, rocked...He fell in silence,
						and no sound from the impact of his body on the concrete plaza reached up to
						us." <note>10. Cherry, p. 232.</note> Some of the highly skilled, agile iron
						workers willing to endure the risks of this trade are American Indians, and
						in their employment the symbolism of manifest destiny turns in an ironic
						circle. Descendants of the native Americans who survived the white man's
						self-righteous westward ex pansion in the nineteenth century, they build the
						secular monuments of a redefined, corporate, manifest destiny.</p>
				</div>
				<div>
					<head>Second Fantasy: "Procreant Power</head>
					<p>In the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries, while tycoons battled
						for top positions on the skyline, and "sky-boys' fell to their deaths,
						skyscraper architects began to use the imagery of male sexuality to describe
						these buildings. The earlier monuments had celebrated military conquests,
						and now towers did the same for economic conquests. Just as American authors
						like Theodore Dreiser and Henry James used the imagery of male potency to
						enhance the moneymaking activities of fictional entrepreneurs like Frank
						Cowperwood or Caspar Goodwood, so many American architects began to express
						the economic power of their corporate clients through metaphors of sexual
						power. Thus the <pb n="110"
							facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2025-02/heresies02_110.jpg"
						/> imagery of war and patriotic death was overlaid with an imagery of
						fecundity and generative power. However, as skyscraper architects added the
						office tower to the procession of phallic monu ments in history—including
						poles, obelisks, spires, columns, and watchtowers—very few designers asked
						what the effects would be of insisting that ordinary people regularly
						inhabit such extraordinary, tall, erect structures.</p>
					<p>In 1901 Louis Sullivan praised the design of a commercial building (which was
						not a skyscraper) by H. H. Richardson: "...here is a man for you to look at.
						..a real man, a manly man; a virile force...an entire male. ..a monument to
						trade, to the organized commercial spirit, to the power and progress of the
						age...a male...it sings the song of procreant power...." <note>11. Louis
							Sullivan, <title level="m">Kindergarden Chats</title>, pp. 29-30. He
							refers to the Marshall Field Wholesale Warehouse, Chicago.</note> As
						Sullivan himself and other architects built commercial skyscrapers, this
						language of male identification was extended. One designer saw skyscrapers
						as "symbols of the American spirit—that ruthless, tireless, energeticism
						delightedly proclaiming What a great boy am I!'" <note>12. Claude Bragdon,
							"Skyscrapers, in <title level="m">The Architecture Lectures</title>,
							(Chicago: Creative Age Press, 1942), p. 103.</note> In 1936 Le Corbusier
						identified himself with America's vital economic forces, using phrases which
						recalled Sullivan's "song of procreant power." He observed "an erect
						Manhattan, the drives of Chicago, and so many clear signs of youthful
						power." Viewing the skyline of New York, he wrote, "Feeling comes into play;
						the action of the heart is released; crescendo, allegro, fortissimo. We are
						charged with feeling, we are intoxicated, legs strengthened, chest expanded,
						eager for action, we are filled with a great confidence. <note>13. Le
							Corbusier, "I Am an American," in <title level="m">When All the
								Cathedrals Were White</title> (1936) (New York: McGraw Hill, 1964),
							pp. 90, 149</note> The architectural historian Vincent Scully carried
						this celebration of skyscrapers, money and sex into the 1960s when he
						praised Rockefeller Center as ...one of the few surviving public spaces in
						America that look as if they were designed and used by people who knew what
						stable wealth was and were not ashamed to enjoy it. Flags snap, high heels
						tap: a little sex and aggression, the city's delights."</p>
					<note>14. Vincent Scully, <title level="m">American Architecture and
							Urbanism</title> (New York: Praeger, 1969), p. 154.</note>
					<p>The erotic charge of the skyscraper was more explicitly related to phallic
						erection and penetration in formal discussions of towers as including base,
						shaft, and tip, and in graphic visions of the skyscraper. A rendering of
						Louis Sullivan and Dankmar Adler's Fraternity Temple scheme of 1891 shows a
						phallic tower on a broad base with a pointed tip piercing the sky. Many
						architectural renderers of the 1920s, such as Hugh Ferriss, often utilized
						perspective to convey a sense of upward thrust, enhanced by strong lighting
						from below. Lighting could suggest ejaculation as well as erection, as in a
						view of the Chrysler Building ejaculating light into the night. (Its
						articulated tip anticipates today's skyscrapers with brightly lit revolving
						restaurants, where diners can rotate tirelessly in the night skies above
						American cities.)</p>
					<p>Architects' words and graphics encouraged their clients to phallic, urban
						displays, but occasionally architects might do more. A 1931 photograph shows
						seven men positioned in an irregular line, wearing cloth costumes banded
						with vertical or horizontal stripes. Tall cones or ziggurats cover their
						heads. Six levels of sharp-edged points culminate in an eighteen-inch rod
						atop the leader's mask, making his total stature nine feet. Are <pb n="111"
							facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2025-02/heresies02_111.jpg"
						/> these tribesmen about to execute some primitive ritual celebrating male
						fertility? Below the photograph the caption reads: "Famous architects
						forming a miniature skyline of New York as they don their Beaux Arts
						costumes." The symbolic predilections of skyscraper architects have rarely
						been shown so clearly: urban professional men require a social occasion to
						turn themselves into a Dionysian landscape, a miniature version of the
						revenue-generating skyline they promote in their daily work.</p>
				</div>
				<div>
					<head>Reality: Urban Bankruptcy</head>
					<p>Whatever the myths about their phallic power, towers have proved economically
						powerful, but in a negative as well as a positive way. The glorification of
						the "procreant power" of the skyscraper serves to obscure the drain on
						municipal finances which towers create. Many urban historians have described
						the American urban downtown as a three-dimensional graph of land
						speculation, and locating clusters of towers is a quick way to guess at land
						values. Yet although tall buildings reflect the desire for maximizing
						private investment in a city based upon private land ownership, skyscrapers
						are not always profitable for their developers. For whom is skyscraper
						revenue generated? And how is it calculated?</p>
					<p>A need for immediate usable space is never enough reason for building a
						skyscraper. The construction cost of several low-rise buildings is almost
						always less than the cost of equivalent space in a skyscraper since
						expensive foundations and unusable space for elevators and mechanical
						equipment increase as the tower goes higher. Land cost, rather than building
						cost, is the justification: a very expensive piece of downtown land may be
						said to "require" a skyscraper to explain its price. <note>15. One example
							of the older literature describing economic "rationality" is William C.
							Clark and J. L. Kingston, <title level="m">The Skyscraper, A Study in
								the Economic Height of Modern Office Buildings</title> (New York:
							American Institute of Steel Construction, 1930). Clark and Kingston
							rationalize a profitable 75 stories. During this period 75 stories was
							often exceeded and the Empire State Building was under construction
							including 102 stories.</note> But the height of such a skyscraper will
						not be calculated on the city's needs, nor even on the current value of the
						land and the existing density of the area. Rather, a developer calculates
						the rising land values created by present and future skyscrapers, and makes
						a guess about how much more land speculation the neighborhood will bear.
						Developers who try to profit from the inflation of urban land values in this
						way almost always leverage their capital with large bank loans. Banks of
						course receive large amounts of interest. Developers therefore attempt to
						minimize their indebtedness by hastening the construction process (with the
						hazardous consequences for workers previously described) and by taking
						advantage of the federal tax structure and selling tax "shelters" (derived
						from real estate tax loopholes) to profit-making industrial
						corporations.</p>
					<p>While banks and large tax-sheltered, industrial corporations can always
						profit from the "procreant power" of the skyscraper, real estate developers
						hope for rising land values to justify their investments. Meanwhile,
						taxpayers bear the huge public costs of infrastructure and services for
						skyscraper developments. As Stephen Zoll argues in "Superville," "an
						increasing CBD (central business district) bulk becomes, itself, the
						principal sink in the municipal treasury." <note>16. Stephen Zoll,
							"Superville: New York, Aspects of Very High Bulk, <title level="m"
								>Massachusetts Review</title> (Summer 1973), p. 538. Zoll provides
							an eloquent discussion of political and economic factors in skyscraper
							construction with an extended bibliography. A former New York City
							employee, he sees the need for cities to reform their accounting systems
							and show the social costs of CBD density.</note> His persuasive
						historical analysis of high rise economics in New York explains why
						skyscraper construction is disastrous for the city's budget: municipal tax
						revenues never catch up with the spiraling costs of infrastructure which the
						city must provide. Attempts to control urban density through zoning or to
						raise taxes are usually met with corporate threats to leave the city
						altogether, which would cause unemployment. Caught between financial drain
						and the skyscraper and the threat of unemployment, the city loses either
						way.</p>
					<p>The tactics of land speculation and of transferring infrastructure costs to
						the city budget explain some of the reasoning behind the craze for
						skyscraper height, but there is still more to explore. Since the turn of the
						century many developers, aware of the economically and technologically
						"optimal" level of speculation on a given parcel of urban land, have chosen
						to build ever higher, and urban officials have accepted this. The builders
						have sacrificed high economic returns in order to enter a citywide,
						nationwide, or worldwide competition for height and prestige. <note>17. Many
							cities are engaged in such symbolic battles. Perhaps the most extreme
							ironies are the deliberately misleading understatements issued by
							builders during construction, in order to fool competitors into thinking
							that the new structure is less tall than it really will be. Suzanne
							Zwarun, in "The Calgary Tower," <title level="m">Interlude</title>
							(Oct.-Nov. 1976), p. 9, writes about Calgary's Husky Tower. The
							developers lied, she explains, boasting of 613 feet when all the time
							the structure was 626 feet. "The developers kept thirteen extra feet in
							reserve to protect the image of the Canadian west.....They knew some
							dirty rat would toss a few more feet on a project somewhere, just so it
							would out-tower the Husky Tower... Take that, San Antonio.</note> In
						terms of monopoly capitalism, although the tallest building in town may not
						be quantitatively efficient as office space or housing it is qualitatively
						efficient in promoting dominance over an urban region: towers are landmarks
						which can be seen from many distant viewpoints. They become symbols of
						corporate dominance over the city as well as the city's dominance over the
						region.</p>
					<p>The goal in building these extremely tall skyscrapers is psychological
						"procreant power" or awe. Awareness of the power this kind of architecture
						offers is reflected by the skyline of Washington, D.C., where skyscrapers
						over 90 feet tall are forbidden by law, so that the Capitol reigns as the
						highest structure. For many years, beginning in 1931, the Empire State
						Building was the tallest in the world; its pretentious name and an
						overbearing lobby mural showing the building dominating a map of New York,
						"the Empire State," enhanced its awesomeness. The World Trade Center rose
						higher in 1969. Its even more imperial name reflected an obvious attempt to
						supercede the Empire State Building. Yet in both cases symbolic posturing
						concealed unrented space, as these hulking developments were planned to
						exceed all calculations of needed office space in the city. Knowing that the
						World Trade Center was not fully rented, the owners of the Empire State
						threatened to build just enough extra structure to overtop them in the
						1970s, and triumph again. They didn't pursue this competition however, and
						as a result the 1976 version of the film <title level="m">King Kong</title>
						transferred the symbolic confrontation of the "natural" ape and the
						"civilized" capitalists from the Empire State, where it was set in 1933, to
						the World Trade Center, now the tallest structure in New York.</p>
				</div>
				<div>
					<head>Third Fantasy: "Tm Taking the Town!"</head>
					<p>While municipal governments struggle with the high costs of the skyscraper,
						and builders seek both financial and psychological "procreant power,"
						popular novels and films employ skyscraper imagery to create fantasies about
						sexual power and upward mobility for "ordinary" people in capitalist
						society. In the 1970s, women may be cast as executives or stockbrokers in
						these fables of success. A fashion advertisement compresses many strains of
						oppressive imagery—militarism, sexual power, false social mobility. Two
						models wearing suits with military tailoring pose holding statuettes of the
						Empire State Building. "Thinking positive... The way to make things happen
						in the city where everything's possible," reads the copy. "In soft, smokey
						officer's pink, I'm in my element, making strides and taking them.... My
						head's in the clouds and the view's terrific. Officer's pink in sleek new
						shapes, that are budding with potential. I'm perfectly suited to the pace of
						The City...." The dialogue concludes, "I'm <emph>taking the
						town</emph>...."</p>
					<p>In the movies of the 1920s and 1930s, it was more common to see women
						encountering skyscrapers as stage-struck young things coming to the big city
						to seek stardom. Sustaining individual competitiveness in times of
						collective difficulty, the most successful films of the Depression years, as
						Martin Pawley has observed, "dealt with the random access to power and
						influence in high society of 'ordinary' people." <note>18. Martin Pawley,
								<title level="m">The Private Future</title> (London: Pan Books,
							1974), p. 30.</note> Often such hopeful movie romances occurred in
						skyscraper offices, skyscraper penthouses, and skyscraper night clubs.</p>
					<p>In a production number from the 1933 film musical <title>42nd Street</title>,
						miniature skyscraper tips, glowing with colored lights, saluted Ruby Keeler
						as a sweet kid who managed to become a <pb n="112"
							facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2025-02/heresies02_112.jpg"
						/> star, and the manipulation of skyscraper scale made her seem larger than
						life. A film critic recently commented on the effects of this process:
						"...life in New York is made more than bearable by the fine romance this
						city has always had with the movies. We have been exalted by a Hollywood
						version of ourselves that is often no closer to reality than this scene.
						This is Big Flick City— and welcome to it." <note>19. "New York's Love
							Affair with the Movies," <title level="j">New York</title> (Dec. 29,
							1975), p. 33.</note> Another Ruby Keeler film, <title>Go Into Your
							Dance</title> (1936), elaborates the cinematic process by which New
						York's hostile environment is "made more than bearable" by the association
						of the skyscraper with themes of personal success and imperialist corporate
						expansion. In a night club at the top of a New York tower, Al Jolson in
						blackface sings, "She's a Latin from Manhattan," about the fantasy of one
						"ordinary" person making it in the big city. Then Ruby Keeler and other
						performers in evening dress engage in a dance routine of world domination,
						climbing up and down a globe, tap dancing on various countries of the
						Northern Hemisphere to the tune of the title song with its catchy Depression
						lyrics, "When you feel sad and blue now, go into your dance!"</p>
					<p>While these examples show women succeeding, most American skyscraper
						fantasies have dealt with male success and mo bility, suggesting that an
						industrious young fellow may develop a personal empire of banks, shipping
						lines and factories, and build a skyscraper from which to look down on them.
						Architect Howard Roark, hero of Ayn Rand's novel, <title level="m">The
							Fountainhead</title>, and of the 1949 film based on it, endows this plot
						with an artistic rather than an entrepreneurial tone. Roark, played by Gary
						Cooper, stands for the survival of the fittest. A poor boy who made good, he
						fights the "creeping socialism" of his time by designing buildings for
						tycoons so he can develop his creative genius. At the film's end, Roark
						stands, remote and supreme, atop a new skyscraper he designed. He is joined
						there by Dominique Francon, an architectural critic who has been moved to
						ecstasy by an elevator ride up the side of this building. Roark "takes" both
						the town and the world of cultured society Francon represents; in fact,
						early in the story he rapes her and she is rapturous.</p>
					<p>Skyscraper restaurants and hotels trade on the renewal of this sort of
						cinematic fantasy. For the price of a drink or a meal, you can share the
						reflected power of a skyscraper location. One nationwide chain of penthouse
						restaurants advertises, "Make a top decision," <note>20. Make a Top
							Decision," Stouffer advertisement, <title>Mainliner</title> (United
							Airlines' Magazine, Nov. 1976), p. 100.</note> implying executive
						success for those who dine at at the top of a tower. Woody Guthrie made fun
						of such aspirations when he sang about the Rockefeller Center bar and grill,
						This Rainbow Room is up so high/ That John D.'s spirit comes a-driftin' by..
						" <note>21. Woody Guthrie, <title level="m">Bound for Glory</title> (New
							York: New American Library, 1970), p. 292.</note> but this did nothing
						to affect its popularity. Although the tip of a skyscraper is an especially
						charged location, the rest of the skyscraper also has powerful symbolic
						associations: one foreign resort hotel advertises its advantages to New
						Yorkers with a photograph of a phallic building superimposed on the
						bikini-bared torsos of three models. <note>22. Smack-Dab in the Middle,"
							advertisement for Rio Orthon Palace, <title level="j">New York</title>
							(Dec. 13, 1976), p. 139.</note> Whether they want to be chief executives
						or simply sophisticated playboys, clients of skyscraper restaurants or
						hotels are encouraged in their fantasies of power and control.</p>
				</div>
				<div>
					<head>Reality: Urban Oppression</head>
					<p>In the romantic world of popular films and advertisements, life in the
						skyscrapers is a whirl of money, power and sex. But as more and more people
						of all economic classes live and work in skyscrapers, the oppressiveness of
						these environments cannot be denied. In the 1960s and 1970s, community
						groups and workers' organizations began to detail the social and physical
						problems of skyscraper life. Injuries to workers building skyscrapers
						continued, accompanied by the problems created by the completed skyscrapers
						themselves.</p>
					<p>Ever more gigantic skyscrapers, when placed in urban plazas, could create
						dangerous wind forces (up to 175 m.p.h.) that hurled pedestrians off their
						feet. The towers themselves had to be designed to resist wind forces, but
						unforeseen difficulties could occur, as in the John Hancock Tower in Boston,
						where winds wrenched gigantic sections of mirror glass from the curtain
						wall, hurling them to the sidewalks below, terrorizing citizens with
						resounding smashes. Amazingly, there were no pedestrian fatalities.</p>
					<p>Urban residents also complained of enormous skyscraper shadows darkening
						whole neighborhoods and changing the ecology of local parks. Motorists and
						pedestrians found shadows were only half the problem with mirror glass
						buildings which, on their sunny sides, reflected blinding flashes of light
						into cars and homes. Community groups in San Francisco documented such
						difficulties when they fought construction of the Transamerica Building and
						other high-rises. <note>23. Greggar Sletteland and Bruce Brugmann, eds.,
								<title level="m">The Ultimate Highrise: San Francisco's Rush toward
								the Sky</title> (San Francisco: San Fran cisco Bay Guardian,
							1971).</note> In Boston, community groups have slowed but not halted
						construction of the Park Plaza project, whose shadows will darken the Public
						Garden.</p>
					<p>Workers inside the towers have added their complaints to those articulated by
						urban residents. Endlessly repeated sky-scraper floor plans reflect
						hierarchical design which allots interior fluorescent-lit spaces to
						predominantly female clerical workers, and exterior offices with natural
						light and views to predominantly male executives. New trends in office
						landscaping" using low partitions and plants may mute the most obvious
						effects of such plans, but light and space are always assigned according to
						status. In the John Hancock Tower, formal rules allow a senior vice
						president 406 square feet of space compared to a clerical worker's 55.
							<note>24. Susan Quinn, "My Desk Is Bigger Than Your Desk: Playing the
							New Office Status Game," <title level="j">Boston</title> (March 1977),
							p. 78.</note> If clerical workers constitute the majority of the towers'
						populations during the day, cleaners work predominantly at night—squads of
						men and women, poor white, black and foreign born workers. The best paid
						have extremely perilous daytime jobs washing windows or polishing facades,
						hanging on scaffolds as high above the streets as the ironworkers. The night
						shift works for lower wages, and the thrill of seeing the city lit up at
						night is, after all, the frisson of watching thousands of these cleaners at
						work.</p>
					<p>One of the most serious hazards to all workers in high-rise buildings, by day
						or by night, is fire. The skyscraper is constructed to resist fire, but if
						faulty wiring or a smoldering cigarette causes a blaze, then escape from a
						burning tower can be extremely difficult. Stairwells may fill with smoke,
						elevator shafts can act like <pb n="113"
							facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2025-02/heresies02_113.jpg"
						/> chimneys, and traditional firefighting ladders cannot reach the upper
						floors. The Towering Inferno, a film about skyscraper conflagration, was
						playing in New York on the evening of Valentine's Day, 1975, when a
						moderately serious fire broke out in one of the two World Trade Center
						buildings there. Because the fire took place at night, most of the thirty
						injured were fire fighters and cleaners. Building officials managed to calm
						the thousands of daytime workers, who were unnerved to learn that New York
						fire codes had not been followed in the construction of the complex. But as
						skyscraper fires occur every few months around the country, one expects
						protests to increase. <note>25. Trade Center Fire Stirs Row," <title
								level="j">New York Daily News</title> (February 15, 1975), p.
							1.</note></p>
					<p>Since the skyscraper has been established in popular culture as a place for
						"taking the town," personnel in skyscraper offices are exposed increasingly
						to scenes of conflict at skyscraper tips, which are harrowing to the police,
						firemen, or passing workers who are involved. Bomb threats are not
						infrequent in corporate towers, and sometimes there are explosions and
						kidnappings as well. A <title level="j">Los Angeles Times</title> story for
						December 7, 1976, headlined "Gunman Holds Hostage Atop Skyscraper: Youth
						Gives Up After Antismoking Message Is Read On Radio," tells the sad story of
						a youth trying to attract attention in his crusade against lung cancer by
						"taking the town" with a weapon and a hostage.</p>
				</div>
				<div>
					<head>Fourth Fantasy: "Within the City, Without the City's Problems"</head>
					<p>In the movies the skyscraper was first presented as a place for dramatic
						encounters, celebrations, and awe, but as it became the standard building in
						the center city, the alienation of workers and residents increased. Pre-war
						fantasies of beautiful, shining tower cities—such as Hugh Ferriss' romantic
						renderings and Le Corbusier's plans for a Radiant City—led to extensive
						urban renewal programs in the 1950s and 1960s, when office towers and
						upper-class housing were joined by the grim, stripped-down tower in a field
						of asphalt as the preferred solution for public housing, a vertical filing
						cabinet for the urban poor. While such programs added towers to the already
						densely built-up cities of New York and Chicago, other American cities like
						Boston and San Francisco were "Manhattanized," developing predominantly
						skyscraper skylines for the first time. During these years the expanded
						activities of many American corporations and American architects abroad led
						to the exportation of the skyscraper, promoting corporate visibility and
						land speculation from Paris to Nairobi.</p>
					<p>The builders of this era succeeded in realizing the goal of an earlier
						generation of architects—a city composed largely of towers. As a result,
						they multiplied the economic problems of the metropolis and the social
						problems of skyscraper workers and urban residents, but the next generation
						of fantasizers never let up. Although the city was being turned into a field
						of towers, the supertower could still stand above it. Frank Lloyd Wright
						produced a plan for a mile-high skyscraper in 1956. Urban mega- structures
						proliferated on drafting boards in the 1960s, and in the 1970s, Paolo Soleri
						continues to lead the utopian skyscraper architects with endless plans for
						"Arcologies" with towers hung upon towers. (He uses the Empire State
						Building as a scale symbol to dramatize the size of structures many times
						its height.) The World Trade Center in New York, the Transamerica Building
						in San Francisco, and the Sears Tower in Chicago have all set new records
						for skyscraper height in these cities, but the quest for architectural
						dominance does not rest with the supertower which is the tallest building in
						town.</p>
					<p>The 1970s have brought a new kind of skyscraper which simply swallows up the
						city. Instead of a tower being presented as the typical building in the
						center city, it becomes a substitute for the city. More and more resources
						and activities are concentrated inside, while problems—wind, shadows, glare,
						utilities, transportation—are left outside for the municipality to deal with
						as best it can. In New York, Rockefeller Center anticipated this trend with
						offices, shops, restaurants, pedestrian spaces, and a skating rink. The
						World Trade Center is a city of 50,000 within a city of 8,000,000. With its
						own police force, newspaper, and restaurants, the complex is in many ways a
						private urban realm of government agencies and corporations set down in the
						public city of New York. This is a workaday complex, even more deserted at
						night than Rockefeller Center. Chicago's John Hancock tower, in contrast,
						functions as a 24-hour skyscraper city, providing housing as well as stores,
						restaurants and offices. Some residents may rarely emerge; others call the
						doorman to check the weather (which they live above) before they venture
						down from the clouds into the real Chicago below.</p>
					<p>The ultimate skyscraper development goes even further than these giant
						towers, incorporating urban landscape as well as residential, commercial,
						and recreational facilities into its interior design. John Portman's hotels
						in Atlanta, Cambridge, and San Francisco are hollow towers or pyramids
						advertised as being as exciting as (and implicitly safer than) the city
						outside. Interior courtyards and glass elevators allow for the traditional
						skyscraper observation to occur within rather than outside of the tower. The
						visitor experiences the thrill of riding to the top of the tower, but the
						views are carefully controlled vistas of the circumscribed, artificial,
						urban life within the hotel. Going them one better, two new Atlanta
						complexes include a lake and an ice skating rink as private skyscraper
						landscapes on their ground floors. Other build ings reveal the same
						privatization of landscape. The Ford Foundation Building in New York
						surrounds an interior garden. The penthouse farm of Stewart Mott, with its
						"natural" earth loaded onto a New York tower, shows that"nature" can be put
						on top of a skyscraper rather than left in a public place.</p>
					<p>As the American city is economically drained and environmentally destroyed by
						the skyscraper, developers of tower apartments, hotels, and office blocks
						sell back a limited, guarded version of urban life to those who can afford
						it. (This is, after all, what Disney and the'developers of "adventure parks"
						have done, selling synthetic American rural and small town landscapes.) The
						new, private tower cities exclude the poor, minorities, the aged, and the
						unemployed. Fortified by private police forces and by the best technology
						industrial security firms can supply, these private towers recall the
						militarism associated with the centennial obelisks and military watchtowers.
						They pose an extreme answer to urban oppression, selling the urban
						experience without an urban <pb n="114"
							facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2025-02/heresies02_114.jpg"
						/> reality. They want customers to "take the town," and since the real town
						is too far gone, they offer a substitute.</p>
					<p>While urban escapism flourishes and builders construct skyscrapers of the
						present decade, satirists and science fiction writers have provided strong
						critical images of a world of urban towers being erected amid urban rubble.
						"Superstudio, a collective of Italian architects, mocks the trend in their
						"Twelve Cautionary Tales," with a design for a skyscraper factory stretching
						around the earth, churning out new towers as fast as the old ones cruble.
							<note>26. Superstudio, "Twelve Cautionary Tales for Christmas:
							Premonitions of the Mystical Rebirth of Urbanism," <title level="j"
								>Architectural Design</title> (Dec. 1971), pp. 737-742.</note> On
						the same theme, J.G. Ballard's story, "Build-Up, describes a world where
						high-rises cover the earth, except for blacked-out spaces where they have
						collapsed, and subways and high-speed trains are replaced by vertical and
						horizontal ele vators. <note>27. J. G. Ballard, "Build-up," in
								<title>Cronopolis</title> (New York: 1971), pp. 218-240.</note> For
						every such satirist, there are many more individuals planning new
						supertowers, perhaps justifying their projects with the rhetoric of a New
						York housing developer who advertises his expensive high-rise apartment
						block as being "within the city but without the city's problems." <note>28.
							The Century, ""Look Up, New York!" advertisement, <title level="j">New
								York</title> (Nov. 22, 1976), p. 45.</note> Skidmore Owings and
						Merrill offers the perfect architectural expression of this slogan in two of
						their newest commercial blocks on 57th and 42nd Streets in Manhattan. On
						each building, a concave facade covered in mirror glass manipulates the view
						so it appears from below that all the rest of the city is toppling, giving a
						doomsday twist to the perennial competition for skyscraper size as well as
						reinforcing the idea that the only city worth experiencing is inside, not
						out side, the skyscraper.</p>
				</div>
				<div>
					<head>Making Changes—Fantasy and Reality</head>
					<p>Criticizing the design of skyscrapers will not make them disappear, whether
						the criticism comes from a revisionist historian, an outraged citizen, or a
						pragmatic urban budget analyst. Patterns of corporate growth and patriarchy
						have determined the <pb n="115"
							facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2025-02/heresies02_115.jpg"
						/> history of the skyscraper. The economics of urban land development today
						make it impossible to effect major changes in present building trends
						without a political revolution to socialize all urban land. In the meantime,
						at least some attempts in changing consciousness can begin. To understand
						the skyscraper and its place in the American city, we need the perceptions
						of all skyscraper workers and urban residents, women and men, as well as the
						specialized insights of architects, artists, and social critics.</p>
					<p>As a nation, we have exported the skyscraper around the world. Like
						pre-Copernicans who dismissed anyone who disputed the place of the earth as
						center of the solar system, today's American design professionals often
						exclude from serious architectural and urban discourse anyone who refuses to
						accept the importance of the skyscraper to "rational" urban design. Romantic
						notions of military preparedness and "manifest destiny, dreams of economic
						conquest and "survival of the fittest," fantasies of social mobility and
						sexual power, all have been marshaled in support of the skyscraper during
						the past century. All still flourish as skyscraper fantasies today. Designed
						first as urban monuments, then as typical urban buildings, then as synthetic
						cities, American skyscrapers attest to the power of fantasy to confuse our
						perceptions of urban reality. If we look up, we can read in the skyscrapers'
						looming shapes a reminder that our culture depends on false hopes of
						economic mobility as well as on rigid hierarchy, and that it thrives on
						social seduction as well as on architectural rape.</p>
				</div>
				<div>
					<p> I presented a preliminary version of this paper at the Woman's Building in
						Los Angeles in March 1974 at a conference on Women and Design. I would like
						to thank Whitney Chadwick, Robert Manoff, David Hodgdon, Peter Marris, Jean
						Strouse and Susana Torre, who made extensive com ments on early drafts, as
						well as Sheila de Bretteville, David Gordon, Rosaria Hodgdon, Jane
						McGroarty, and Gwen Wright, all of whom sup plied encouragement, material or
						important perspectives. Klaus Roesch did expert photographic research; Ets
						Otomo and Thea Muscat typed with precision and speed; members of the
						Heresies staff helped enormously with the final version. Copyright 1977.
						Please do not quote without written per mission of the author.</p>
				</div>
			</div>
		</body>
		<back>
			<p> Dolores Hayden is a fellow at the Radcliffe Institute and assistant professor of
				architecture and history at MIT in Cambridge. This essay is part of a book in
				progress that deals with contemporary American cityscapes, entitled The Dream at the
				End of the Line.</p>
		</back>

	</text>
</TEI>
