<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/LEAF-VRE/code_snippets/refs/heads/main/CSS/leaf.css" title="LEAF" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>From the Pink and Yellow Books</title>
				<author>Poppy Johnson</author>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Eowyn Andres</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Haley Beardsley</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Lyndon Beier</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Erica Delsandro</persName>
					<resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Mia DeRoco</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Margaret Hunter</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Diane Jakacki</persName>
					<resp>Invesigator, encoder</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Sophie McQuaide</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Olivia Martin</persName>
					<resp>Editor, encoder (2021)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Zoha Nadeer</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Bri Perea</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Carrie Pirmann</persName>
					<resp>Editor, encoder (2023-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Valeria Riley</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Ricky Rodriguez</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2022-2023)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Roger Rothman</persName>
					<resp>Investigator, editor</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Valeria Riley</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Kaitlyn Segreti</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2021-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Maggie Smith</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2021-2024)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Maya Wadhwa</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2021-2023)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Kelly Troop</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Lucy Wadswoth</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2022-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Anna Marie Wingard</persName>
					<resp>Editor (2023-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName>Olivia Wychock</persName>
					<resp>Graduate Editor (2024-Present)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<funder>Bucknell University Humanities Center</funder>
				<funder>Bucknell University Office of Undergraduate Research</funder>
				<funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
				<funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>
					<name>Bucknell University</name>
					<address>
						<street>One Dent Drive</street>
						<settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
						<region>Pennsylvania</region>
						<postCode>17837</postCode>
					</address>
				</distributor>
				<availability>
					<licence>Bucknell Heresies Project: Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial
						4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0)</licence>
					<licence>Heresies journal: © Heresies Collective</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title>Patterns of Communicating and Space Among Women</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>HERESIES: A Feminist Publication on Art and
								Politics</publisher>
							<pubPlace>
								<address>
									<name>Heresies</name>
									<postBox>P.O. Boxx 766, Canal Street Station</postBox>
									<settlement>New York</settlement>
									<region>New York</region>
									<postCode>10013</postCode>
								</address>
							</pubPlace>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb/>
			<div>
				<pb n="93"
					facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2025-02/heresies02_093.jpg"/>
				<head>From the Pink and Yellow Books</head>
				<byline>Poppy Johnson</byline>

				<epigraph>
					<p>The context of my writing is the performance situation which I set up at
						Artists' Space, the Leo Castelli Gallery, and the Whitney Downtown, where a
						video camera on a tripod behind me instantaneously transmitted the image of
						the letters, words, sentences as they were written to a video monitor across
						the room. The pink book was written in anticipation of performing, the
						yellow book is one-third performance and the blue and sub sequent books
						consist only and totally of material written in performance.</p>
				</epigraph>
				<div>
					<head>Pink Book</head>
					<p>Beginning at the beginning. Which is rock bottom. To be an artist who has not
						made any art for two years is very depressing. I have been very happy and
						absorbed. I had two perfect little bodies come out of my body. My body was
						huge and soft and full of milk. I held and nursed and fondled and fed and
						dressed and undressed and talked to and listened to my babies in an unending
						orgy of interdependence. Since Mira and Bran were born I have had no time to
						myself except sleep. But now I have been hired by Carl Andre to do this job
						of sitting for three hours a day in an old green space with a sign eight
						feet from my right eye about possibilities for art production.... So Carl is
						unwittingly my first patron (this work), my inspiration and my competition.
						My materials were paper and pen, now I have a typewriter here so that what I
						am doing now is part typing what I have already written and part writing now
						and it all has to do with the future. My economic resources are not vast,
						but neither are my needs. I figure I need $500 a month to support myself and
						half of two children which works out to $8.20 an hour if I work three hours
						a day five days a week which is all I want to spare right now from my
						children. The economic resource I have right now from this job is really
						time. The rest is all my subjective characteristics which will be manifest
						in the work which is to write whatever I am thinking publicly so that it can
						be simultaneously read. I am not being particularly clear, but this is the
						boring part where I am trying to elicit interest and support and
						collaboration or patronage or whatever. Already I feel a need to rewrite the
						beginning. This work is writing about this work.</p>
					<p>Writing about this work is this work. I am keeping my private journal
						publicly. I am the Delphic oracle. I am studying to be a shopping-bag lady.
						I am redefining art. I want to be in a public room with a typewriter and
						some machinery, maybe video, that could shoot a written page of 8½ by 11"
						paper and project the image of it on a wall or screen, but so it is easily
						legible. The room is somewhat dark except for a good light on my typewriter.
						I am writing down whatever I am thinking as fast and completely and well as
						I can. People come in and watch and read. There is a xerox machine somewhere
						so that xeroxes of pages may be made. I want to find out what and how I
						think. I want the publicness of it to interact with the process of finding
						out. I like using machines although I am not technically proficient and
						comfortable with them because they and art are the two metaphors for the
						mind that I am always bumping up against ... It isn't terror. It isn't joy.
						It's some sort of physical sensation which starts from the very top of my
						head and ripples down to my buttocks since I'm sitting. If I were standing
						it would ripple to my feet and make my insteps tingle. I'm stoned. If I
						thought it were terror I would be terrified. If I thought it were joy I
						might be still and meditative and happy, but that is different from this
						absorbed state of working that I am in. This is where there is that
						possibility of inarticulableness, either stoned or orgasming or making or
						con templating art or mystical experiences. There is the temptation of
						feigning speechlessness because of fearing the inadequacy of words. It can't
						be the words that are at fault, but my laziness.</p>
					<p>Outside there is a New York sirocco blowing hot restless moving air all
						around my legs and hair. It's exciting but disturbing since I'm wearing only
						a light short cotton dress and a pair of under pants. A pair of underpants
						is only one thing unlike a pair of mittens. I feel naked and lustful and
						agitated. I just thought about Gertrude Stein and Jill Johnston as heroines,
						but I didn't like to think it because it broke my other train of thought.
						I'd rather stay physical today. While digging in my purse for cigarettes (a
						man wouldn't have written that) I found a three-inch high light gray plastic
						horse, missing its flowing tail but complete with flowing darker mane and
						red indented nostrils and lips, that belongs to my children. Well, I bought
						it for them but it's questionable if children actually own things at all....
						I remember Lambie, a big soft stuffed white lamb I slept with, and later
						used to dust with my mother's perfumed talcum powder to make him white
						again. Funny that I thought he was male. I wonder when I started dividing
						the world that way and what arbitrary rules did I make up in unknown gender
						cases like toy animals and why.</p>
					<p>I did write a list of the first hundred words the babies spoke, but I haven't
						written them a journal of their daily activities. That's their bedtime story
						every night anyway so I suppose I could tape it and save it for them for
						eternity. “Once upon a time there was a little boy named Bran and a little
						girl named Mira and this morning they woke up very early and woke up their
						mommy and daddy and had eggs for breakfast and...." Every once in a while I
						get conscious of switching the order girl/boy, boy/girl, every alternate
						night, but often slide back to Bran/Mira several nights in a row. I even
						started telling it “Once upon a time there were two children, one named Mira
						and one named Bran... so that there wouldn't even be the boy/girl
						differentiation at all, but I'm afraid that they and I are already
						conditioned that way. Bran is masculine and Mira is feminine and they get
						more and more different every day. I hope that Mira won't hate me when she
						grows up. I hope that all the femininity that I have inevitably inculcated
						in her will be perceived as positive and valuable instead of the degrading
						powerlessness I have often been made to feel. The only way I can attempt to
						assure that is to make sure she grows up with good images of female power
						surrounding her, starting with my own self. And that means not totally
						answering her current demands of all my time and affection and attention so
						that I can go out and get myself powerful and make sure that I feel it and
						feel good about it. Which is difficult to do.</p>
					<p>Which I'm not pretending to do for her sake, but knowing that it is also for
						her makes me stronger. It's for Bran too but not as empathetically. For a
						long time I was taught to see my mother, and she was being convinced to see
						herself, as a mean, castrating, frigid, evil bitch. I don't blame her for
						that, but I would blame myself if I let Mira suffer the same thing. She will
						have to suffer something else. Some new pattern. In my mother's family one
						only talks about the women, at least as far back as the civil war, because
						they were the interesting ones and/or they lived longer.</p>
					<p>Anyway it is the female line that is traced. I read a diary of my mother's
						mother's mother's mother who was a southern belle named Emma Munnerlin,
						daughter of a rice plantation and slave owner, who married Charles Stocking,
						a yankee whose family had been long settled in the Connecticut River valley.
						He made a small fortune and then the civil war broke out and his brothers
							<pb n="94"
							facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2025-02/heresies02_094.jpg"
						/> and cousins were all fighting for the union. He got wiped out financially
						and went catatonic for a while and then just psychotically morbid and
						depressed and afunctional. Emma's brothers and father were killed and ruined
						so she had to move north with two infant daughters and a crazy husband and
						support every body by giving french and music lessons to the local yankee
						daughters. She didn't complain in her diaries and they are not too exciting
						to read unless you already know the story and empathize a lot. She had been
						brought up with a personal slave companion, a girl a little older than
						herself, who brushed her long hair for her every morning and every night.
						They must have started out like twins or best friends or lovers and been
						trained to accept their difference in status. Her slave would have been the
						real child of the black woman who suckled her and the reason the woman was
						still full of milk for the little white baby. It is easier to imagine the
						rage that the black baby girl woman might have felt but probably didn't than
						to understand what subtle unconscious mixtures of interdependence and guilt
						and affection and tyranny Emma might have felt. Either way there's no record
						of it. Only imaginings based on experience or literature or movies. One of
						my best friends throughout high school was a very brilliant, angry, tricky
						and unfathomable black girl, one of the three or four blacks in the whole
						hypocritical elitist bourgeois school. I am a complex and conscious racist.
						I wish I weren't a racist at all, but l am a racist and a sexist and would
						probably be a capitalist imperialist if I had the chance. Fighting those
						things personally can either give or take away the strength to fight them on
						a political level....</p>
					<p>When Eva Hesse died, some friends of mine were moving into her place on the
						Bowery, and they knew how poor I was, and they said I could have any of the
						materials I could salvage from the heaps on the floor. I took inks and
						charcoals and water color sets and oilpaints and cords and tubing and
						strings and bits of rubber and everything. I figured it might be magic and I
						needed all the money I was making (working for a real estate agent in
						Brooklyn) for food anyway. I can never have too many bottles of
						half-evaporated foul-smelling multicolored Higgins ink and little wads of
						used art gum erasers. I carry it all with me from studio to studio. First to
						the 5th floor of 323 Greenwich St, then to Mulberry St, then to the country,
						then to the 4th floor of 323 Greenwich St, then to 319 Greenwich St. It
						comes in handy. Except for the horrid little nose masks for working with
						plastic.</p>
					<p>One time I used a whole lot of that material plus other stuff to make work in
						the woods. I was reading a lot about shamanism at the time and, while
						thinking, I would spend all day in the woods, one late summer into fall,
						making things from painted strings and painted wood and the trees that were
						there and the rocks and a brook and rubber slingshots and the works were
						visible enough to be photographed but invisible enough to be magical traps.
						Nobody ever saw them except the man I lived with and the man who used to own
						the woods and still walked his dogs there and perhaps an occasional hunter.
						I always wore red when I worked so I wouldn't be shot at. And big rubber
						boots so the copperheads and rattlesnakes wouldn't bite me. One weekend some
						people were coming to visit. A critic and a painter. I was very excited
						because I wanted them to come see my work. I worked hard on Friday afternoon
						in the woods (after cleaning the house and shopping and making beds etc.).
						They arrived for supper and it was dark. I woke early Saturday morning from
						excitement and anxiety and went walking to the woods to see everything once
						more alone before it became public and found everything I had done wantonly
						destroyed and stolen and dragged away and gone. This art is writing about
						this art.</p>
					<p>Writing about this art is this art. I love grammar but I don't understand its
						relation to meaning. If thoughts are born in words, as words, then the
						grammar is part of their initial existence. If thoughts are born not words,
						then the words come next and then the grammar is invented for them that puts
						them in the best order. My daughter has just invented or discovered a
						sentence that she says all the time which is the question “What is the
						-doing? -being any noun she knows, mommy, truck, daddy, brother, cookie,
						kitty, chair, table, toy, etc. I answer the question as best I can when it
						refers to anything capable of action (doing) but I get confused by "what is
						the cookie doing?" Sometimes I just say "it is" or "it is being a cookie" or
						'the cookie is sitting on the chair where Mira left it, waiting for Mira to
						hurry up and eat it before Poppy or Bran does" or "I don't know, Mira, what
						is the cookie doing?" to which she replies "UH." She has three answers to
						the kind of questions that I don't know the answers to myself, No, Yes, and
						uh. It is not grammar, anyway, which is only a structure, but the enormous
						number of words and then the mathematical infinity of combining any two,
						three, seven, twenty-four, thirty-three of them in one sentence that
						staggers the imagination....</p>
					<p>I've been thinking about Suzanne Harris' work <title>Locus Up.</title> It is
						experientially describable as a saint approaching death. It is made of sand
						and stucco walls. Suzanne looks to me like a combination of Joan of Arc and
						Saint Sebastian by various renaissance masters. I think she is very
						beautiful. That may not be relevant but I wrote it anyway. The saint
						approaches her death. She walks slowly in the sandy desert and the horizon
						melts away as the sand rises symmetrically on either side of her progress.
						She won't look back which is the only way to see the world and people and
						life she is leaving behind. She looks straight ahead at a narrow dark
						doorway cut into the mound of sand ahead. Inside is a cool, dark but short
						passageway that immediately and clearly opens into a bright round limited
						space. In the center of the bright round space, so huge that it takes up
						three-fourths of the space is an implacable white cube. The saint looks up
						into the blue sky above. She has left everything else behind and entered
						into her own metaphor for her soul, hermetic and infinite. She is not
						afraid.</p>
					<p>I wrote a very long list of all the women who I think are beautiful that I
						have been in the same room with. This is all related. I have been trained by
						art at the service of society to see certain things as beautiful: sunsets,
						flowers, stars, jewels, fruit, oceans, shells, trees, mountains, circles,
						colors, sunrises, and rocks and mothers with children and gold and sunlight
						and eyes and animals and glass and wood and shiny things; calligraphy and
						birds and structure and dragons and hills; stars and moon light, boats,
						flags, crucifixions and repetition and liquids, flight and the lives of the
						saints, altruism and patriotism and irony, rhythm and power and women. This
						list could be short if it were generalized and long if it were
						particularized. Very few of the women on my list are mothers, so why did I
						want to be a mother? I thought of two ways to be useful on this earth. One
						is to alleviate human suffering which would make one want to be a saint a
						scientist a revolutionary a doctor a politician a nurse a teacher a social
						worker a mass murderer a saint a mother an artist an entertainer a whore a
						mathematician or to add to human joy by being.</p>
				</div>
				<div>
					<head>Yellow Book</head>
					<p>It might be possible to believe that Chang Ching truly tried to revolutionize
						culture or the relationship between people and culture and that is why the
						bureaucrats who seem to be in power now are afraid of her. The New York
						Times says her revolu tionary operas were rigidly propagandistic but they
						see propa <pb n="95"
							facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2025-02/heresies02_095.jpg"
						/> ganda as a pejorative word and what do they know anyway? It interests me
						that she was an actress and perhaps an adventuress and I imagine she has
						been made to suffer because Mao sent his loyal wife of the Long March, who
						bore him children given to peasants on the route and then lost, off to
						Moscow and then divorced her so he could marry young Chang Ching. My son is
						crying in his room. It is ten o'clock at night and he is supposed to be
						learning to go to bed without me lying beside him or singing songs or
						telling stories until he goes to sleep. If I do all or any of those things
						his father gets mad at me. If I don't he cries and his father gets mad at
						him and then at me because it is my fault he cries and it takes hours before
						everyone calms down because I get mad too. All that writing was interrupted
						by my going and lying down beside Bran and holding his hand and within five
						minutes he fell asleep. The other night both children were in the bathtub
						and I gave them two roses from the dozens given me at my performance to play
						with. I dethorned them first. I got in the bathtub with them and they were
						pulling the petals off the roses and we all decorated each other with rose
						petals. But I worry about Chang Ching. What if both she and Mao had been
						mythologized together, as an inseparable passionate toward each other and
						passionate to the revolution pair. He would seem less a father if he were
						also seen as a lover. Wasn't it Justinian and Theodora who ran such an ideal
						government and she had been a dancing girl or something. I know I used to
						think that all men were republicans and all women democrats. (My daughter
						sometimes declares that all girls have blue eyes and all boys have brown
						eyes, but now she has a blue-eyed doll with a penis so her faith is a bit
						shaken.) (She also knows her brown-eyed halfsister has a cunt which is the
						word used opposite penis in this house because vagina is just not one of my
						favorite words and cunt is despite its frequent misuse as an insult.) I was
						taught that men were republicans because they had to worry about money and
						they didn't like to give it to poor people and that women, because they
						didn't have to work and are naturally extravagant and generous and
						soft-hearted, are democrats and fuzzy-headed liberals. Also because women
						can afford to be idealistic and hopeful whereas men have to be cynical to
						survive in the jungle. There is probably no demographic truth in that, it
						was only my own family. I am registered and almost always vote as a democrat
						but my real party is the changchingist communist party, which is entirely
						feminist and attempts to integrate art and life in a truly revolutionary
						manner. This party has only just now been imagined by me and its inspiration
						is languishing under house arrest in Peking on the other side of this funny
						round world, but the...</p>
					<p>Our loft is very odd now. You walk in and are confronted with what is either
						called a what-not or a marbletop, being an elaborately carved wooden object
						with a mirror and knobs for hanging coats and bags and a marble tabletop for
						throwing keys and letters and a drawer for lint brushes and miscellany, very
						victorian and handy. Then you turn right into a wall giving you three
						choices. December 2nd. You see, yesterday was short and unsatisfactory.
						There was a chinese piano tuner and a dinner party, the place I live in was
						not described, a tiny baby and very cold weather. My eyes are heavy-lidded,
						always have been. I don't look innocent. I have of course been told that my
						eyes are beautiful, but they aren't. They are hooded and abandoned and of a
						blue more organic than mineral. They feel tired except when I remember they
						are round balls mostly inside my head. They are not just what they appear.
						Once I saw a short accompanying a movie which was made for german children
						to explain the physiology and physics of the eye. I especially remember the
						waves of color, the red short and angry jumping and the blue long and
						peaceful wavy like the ocean. Then they made gray rosebushes turn all red.
						Would that it were that simple. I hate mysteries. I would truly like to know
						everything. I'd like to begin with all the most important things and then
						all the subsidiary facts would just fall into place in an orderly way and
						wouldn't be worrisome instead of just accumulating a lot of small things and
						reasoning out their places to build a structure I cannot imagine the shape
						of until I have finished building. I would like some blinding flashes like
						Einstein had on the trolley. I would like not to have to work so hard and be
						so heavy-lidded. I would also like not to think that I have to read a lot of
						books, that there I might find enough details for my constructions. No, I
						scream at myself, that is not where it is found these days, politely hiding
						on a quiet page, you might find it in the bathtub with your body or in
						socratic dialogues with your peer group or even in a cultural manifestation,
						but, no, never just sitting in a book. </p>
				</div>
			</div>
		</body>
		<back>
			<p> Poppy Johnson is an artist who lives in New York. </p>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
